<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<!DOCTYPE comref SYSTEM "comref.dtd">

<comref>
  <header>
    <copyright>
      <year>1996</year><year>2016</year>
      <holder>Ericsson AB. All Rights Reserved.</holder>
    </copyright>
    <legalnotice>
      Licensed under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the "License");
      you may not use this file except in compliance with the License.
      You may obtain a copy of the License at
 
          http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0

      Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
      distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,
      WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
      See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
      limitations under the License.
    
    </legalnotice>

    <title>epmd</title>
    <prepared>Claes Wikstr&ouml;m</prepared>    
    <responsible></responsible>
    <docno>1</docno>
    <approved></approved>
    <checked></checked>
    <date>1998-01-05</date>
    <rev>A</rev>
    <file>epmd.xml</file>
  </header>

  <com>epmd</com>
  <comsummary>
    <p>Erlang Port Mapper Daemon</p>

    <taglist>
      <tag><c><![CDATA[epmd [-d|-debug] [DbgExtra...] [-address Addresses]
        [-port No] [-daemon] [-relaxed_command_check]]]></c></tag>
      <item>
	<p>Starts the port mapper daemon.</p>
      </item>
      <tag><c><![CDATA[epmd [-d|-debug] [-port No]
        [-names|-kill|-stop Name]]]></c></tag>
      <item>
	<p>Communicates with a running port mapper daemon.</p>
      </item>
    </taglist>
  </comsummary>

  <description>
    <p>This daemon acts as a name server on all hosts involved in
      distributed Erlang computations. When an Erlang node starts,
      the node has a name and it obtains an address from the host
      OS kernel. The name and address are sent to the
      <c><![CDATA[epmd]]></c> daemon running on the local host.
      In a TCP/IP environment, the address consists
      of the IP address and a port number. The node name is
      an atom on the form of <c><![CDATA[Name@Node]]></c>.
      The job of the <c><![CDATA[epmd]]></c> daemon is to keep track of which
      node name listens on which address. Hence, <c><![CDATA[epmd]]></c> maps
      symbolic node names to machine addresses.</p>

    <p>The TCP/IP <c>epmd</c> daemon only keeps track of
      the <c>Name</c> (first) part of an Erlang node name. The <c>Host</c>
      part (whatever is after the <c><![CDATA[@]]></c>) is implicit in the
      node name where the <c>epmd</c> daemon was contacted,
      as is the IP address where the Erlang node can be
      reached. Consistent and correct TCP naming services are
      therefore required for an Erlang network to function
      correctly.</p>

    <taglist>
      <tag>Starting the port mapper daemon</tag>
      <item>
        <p>The daemon is started automatically by command
          <seealso marker="erl"><c>erl</c></seealso>
          if the node is to be distributed and no running
          instance is present. If automatically launched
          environment variables must be used to change the behavior
          of the daemon; see section
          <seealso marker="#environment_variables">Environment
          Variables</seealso>.</p>
        <p>If argument <c>-daemon</c> is not specified,
          <c><![CDATA[epmd]]></c> runs as a normal program with the
          controlling terminal of the shell in which it is
          started. Normally, it is to be run as a daemon.</p>
        <p>Regular startup options are described in section
          <seealso marker="#daemon_flags">Regular Options</seealso>.</p>
        <p>The <c>DbgExtra</c> options are described in section
          <seealso marker="#debug_flags">DbgExtra Options</seealso>.</p>
      </item>
      <tag>Communicating with a running port mapper daemon</tag>
      <item>
        <p>Communicating with the running <c>epmd</c> daemon by the
          <c>epmd</c> program is done primarily for debugging purposes.</p>
        <p>The different queries are described in section <seealso
          marker="#interactive_flags">Interactive options</seealso>.</p>
      </item>
    </taglist>
  </description>

  <section>
    <marker id="daemon_flags"></marker>
    <title>Regular Options</title>
    <p>These options are available when starting the name server. The name
      server is normally started automatically by command
      <seealso marker="erl"><c>erl</c></seealso> (if not already available),
      but it can also be started at system startup.</p>

    <taglist>
      <tag><c><![CDATA[-address List]]></c></tag>
      <item>
	<p>Lets this instance of <c>epmd</c> listen only on the
	  comma-separated list of IP addresses and on the loopback address
	  (which is implicitly added to the list if it has not been
	  specified). This can also be set using environment variable
	  <c><![CDATA[ERL_EPMD_ADDRESS]]></c>; see section <seealso
	  marker="#environment_variables">Environment Variables</seealso>.</p>
      </item>
      <tag><c><![CDATA[-port No]]></c></tag>
      <item>
	<p>Lets this instance of <c>epmd</c> listen to another TCP port than
	  default 4369. This can also be set using environment variable
	  <c><![CDATA[ERL_EPMD_PORT]]></c>; see section <seealso
	  marker="#environment_variables">Environment Variables</seealso>.</p>
      </item>
      <tag><c><![CDATA[-d | -debug]]></c></tag>
      <item>
	<p>Enables debug output. The more <c>-d</c> flags specified, the more
	  debug output you will get (to a certain limit). This option is  most
	  useful when the <c>epmd</c> daemon is not started as a daemon.</p>
      </item>
      <tag><c><![CDATA[-daemon]]></c></tag>
      <item>
	<p>Starts <c>epmd</c> detached from the controlling terminal. Logging
	  ends up in syslog when available and correctly configured. If the
	  <c>epmd</c> daemon is started at boot, this option is definitely
	  to be used. It is also used when command <c>erl</c> automatically
	  starts <c>epmd</c>.</p>
      </item>
      <tag><c><![CDATA[-relaxed_command_check]]></c></tag>
      <item>
	<p>Starts the <c>epmd</c> program with relaxed command checking
	  (mostly for backward compatibility). This affects the following:</p>
	<list type="bulleted">
	  <item>
	    <p>With relaxed command checking, the <c>epmd</c> daemon can be
	      killed from the local host with, for example, command
	      <c>epmd -kill</c> even if active nodes are registered. Normally
	      only daemons with an empty node database can be killed with
	      <c>epmd -kill</c>.</p>
	  </item>
	  <item>
	    <p>Command <c>epmd -stop</c> (and the corresponding messages to
	      <c>epmd</c>, as can be specified using <seealso
	      marker="erl_interface:ei"><c>erl_interface:ei</c></seealso>) is
	      normally always ignored. This because it can cause a strange
	      situation where two nodes of the same name can be alive at the
	      same time. A node unregisters itself by only closing the
	      connection to <c>epmd</c>, which is why command <c>stop</c>
	      was only intended for use in debugging situations.</p>
	    <p>With relaxed command checking enabled, you can forcibly
	      unregister live nodes.</p>
	  </item>
	</list>
	<p>Relaxed command checking can also be enabled by setting environment
	  variable <c>ERL_EPMD_RELAXED_COMMAND_CHECK</c> before starting
	  <c>epmd</c>.</p>
	<p>Use relaxed command checking only on systems with very limited
	  interactive usage.</p>
      </item>
    </taglist>
  </section>

  <section>
    <marker id="debug_flags"></marker>
    <title>DbgExtra Options</title>
    <note>
      <p>These options are only for debugging and testing <c>epmd</c> clients.
      They are not to be used in normal operation.</p>
    </note>

    <taglist>
      <tag><c><![CDATA[-packet_timeout Seconds]]></c></tag>
      <item>
	<p>Sets the number of seconds a connection can be
	  inactive before <c>epmd</c> times out and closes the
	  connection. Defaults to 60.</p>
      </item>
      <tag><c><![CDATA[-delay_accept Seconds]]></c></tag>
      <item>
	<p>To simulate a busy server, you can insert a delay between when
	  <c>epmd</c> gets notified that a new connection is requested and
	  when the connection gets accepted.</p>
      </item>
      <tag><c><![CDATA[-delay_write Seconds]]></c></tag>
      <item>
	<p>Also a simulation of a busy server. Inserts
	  a delay before a reply is sent.</p>
      </item>
    </taglist>
  </section>

  <section>
    <marker id="interactive_flags"></marker>
    <title>Interactive Options</title>
    <p>These options make <c>epmd</c> run as an interactive command,
      displaying the results of sending queries to an already running
      instance of <c>epmd</c>. The <c>epmd</c> contacted is always on the
      local node, but option <c>-port</c> can be used to select between
      instances if several are running using different ports on the host.</p>

    <taglist>
      <tag><c><![CDATA[-port No]]></c></tag>
      <item>
	<p>Contacts the <c>epmd</c> listening on the specified TCP port
	  number (default 4369). This can also be set using environment
	  variable <c><![CDATA[ERL_EPMD_PORT]]></c>; see section <seealso
	  marker="#environment_variables">Environment Variables</seealso>.</p>
      </item>
      <tag><c><![CDATA[-names]]></c></tag>
      <item>
	<p>Lists names registered with the currently running <c>epmd</c>.</p>
      </item>
      <tag><c><![CDATA[-kill]]></c></tag>
      <item>
	<p>Kills the currently running <c>epmd</c>.</p>
	<p>Killing the running <c>epmd</c> is only allowed if
	  <c>epmd -names</c> shows an empty database or if
	  <c>-relaxed_command_check</c> was specified when the running
	  instance of <c>epmd</c> was started.</p>
	<p>Notice that <c>-relaxed_command_check</c> is specified when
	  starting the daemon that is to accept killing when it has live
	  nodes registered. When running <c>epmd</c> interactively,
	  <c>-relaxed_command_check</c> has no effect. A daemon that is
	  started without relaxed command checking must be killed using,
	  for example, signals or some other OS-specific method if it has
	active clients registered.</p>
      </item>
      <tag><c><![CDATA[-stop Name]]></c></tag>
      <item>
	<p>Forcibly unregisters a live node from the <c>epmd</c> database.</p>
	<p>This command can only be used when contacting <c>epmd</c>
	  instances started with flag <c>-relaxed_command_check</c>.</p>
	<p>Notice that relaxed command checking must enabled for the
	  <c>epmd</c> daemon contacted. When running <c>epmd</c>
	  interactively, <c>-relaxed_command_check</c> has no effect.</p>
      </item>
    </taglist>
  </section>

  <section>
    <marker id="environment_variables"></marker>
    <title>Environment Variables</title>
    <taglist>
      <tag><c><![CDATA[ERL_EPMD_ADDRESS]]></c></tag>
      <item>
	<p>Can be set to a comma-separated
	  list of IP addresses, in which case the <c>epmd</c> daemon
	  will listen only on the specified address(es) and on the
	  loopback address (which is implicitly added to the list if it
	  has not been specified). The default behavior is to listen on
	  all available IP addresses.</p>
      </item>
      <tag><c><![CDATA[ERL_EPMD_PORT]]></c></tag>
      <item>
	<p>Can contain the port number <c>epmd</c> will use.
	  The default port will work fine in most cases. A different port can
	  be specified to allow several instances of <c>epmd</c>, representing
	  independent clusters of nodes, to co-exist on the same host.
	  All nodes in a cluster must use the same <c>epmd</c> port number.</p>
      </item>
      <tag><c><![CDATA[ERL_EPMD_RELAXED_COMMAND_CHECK]]></c></tag>
      <item>
	<p>If set before start, the <c>epmd</c> daemon behaves
	  as if option <c>-relaxed_command_check</c> was specified at
	  startup. Consequently, if this option is set before starting
	  the Erlang virtual machine, the automatically started
	  <c>epmd</c> accepts the <c>-kill</c> and <c>-stop</c>
	  commands without restrictions.</p>
      </item>
    </taglist>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Logging</title>
    <p>On some operating systems <em>syslog</em> will be used for
      error reporting when <c>epmd</c> runs as a daemon. To enable
      the error logging, you must edit the
      <path unix="" windows="">/etc/syslog.conf</path> file and add an
      entry:</p>

    <code type="none"><![CDATA[
  !epmd
  *.*<TABs>/var/log/epmd.log
]]></code>

    <p>where <c>&lt;TABs&gt;</c> are at least one real tab character.
      Spaces are silently ignored.</p>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Access Restrictions</title>
    <p>The <c>epmd</c> daemon accepts messages from both the local host and
      remote hosts. However, only the query commands are answered (and
      acted upon) if the query comes from a remote host. It is always an
      error to try to register a node name if the client is not a process
      on the same host as the <c>epmd</c> instance is running on. Such
      requests are considered hostile and the connection is closed
      immediately.</p>

    <p>The following queries are accepted from remote nodes:</p>

    <list type="bulleted">
      <item>
	<p>Port queries, that is, on which port the node with a specified
	  name listens</p>
      </item>
      <item>
	<p>Name listing, that is, gives a list of all names registered on
	  the host</p>
      </item>
    </list>

    <p>To restrict access further, firewall software must be used.</p>
  </section>
</comref>


