<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<!DOCTYPE erlref SYSTEM "erlref.dtd">

<erlref>
  <header>
    <copyright>
      <year>1998</year><year>2016</year>
      <holder>Ericsson AB. All Rights Reserved.</holder>
    </copyright>
    <legalnotice>
      Licensed under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the "License");
      you may not use this file except in compliance with the License.
      You may obtain a copy of the License at
 
          http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0

      Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
      distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,
      WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
      See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
      limitations under the License.
    
    </legalnotice>

    <title>nteventlog</title>
    <prepared></prepared>
    <docno></docno>
    <date></date>
    <rev></rev>
  </header>
  <module since="">nteventlog</module>
  <modulesummary>Interface to Windows Event Log</modulesummary>
  <description>
    <p><c>nteventlog</c> provides a generic interface to the Windows
      event log. It is part of the OS_Mon application, see
      <seealso marker="os_mon_app">os_mon(6)</seealso>. Available for
      Windows versions where the event log is available. That is, not
      for Windows 98 and some other older Windows versions, but for most
      (all?) newer Windows versions.</p>
    <p>This module is used as the Windows backend for <c>os_sup</c>, see
      <seealso marker="os_sup">os_sup(3)</seealso>.</p>
    <p>To retain backwards compatibility, this module can also be used
      to start a standalone <c>nteventlog</c> process which is not part
      of the OS_Mon supervision tree. When starting such a process,
      the user has to supply an identifier as well as a callback
      function to handle the messages.</p>
    <p>The identifier, an arbitrary string, should be reused whenever
      the same application (or node) wants to start the process.
      <c>nteventlog</c> is informed about all events that have arrived
      to the eventlog since the last accepted message for the current
      identifier. As long as the same identifier is used, the same
      eventlog record will not be sent to <c>nteventlog</c> more than
      once (with the exception of when graved system failures arise, in
      which case the last records written before the failure may be
      sent to Erlang again after reboot).</p>
    <p>If the event log is configured to wrap around automatically,
      records that have arrived to the log and been overwritten when
      <c>nteventlog</c> was not running are lost. It however detects
      this state and loses no records that are not overwritten.</p>
    <p>The callback function works as described in <c>os_sup(3)</c>.</p>
  </description>
  <funcs>
    <func>
      <name since="">start(Identifier, MFA) -> Result</name>
      <name since="">start_link(Identifier, MFA) -> Result</name>
      <fsummary>Start the NT eventlog server</fsummary>
      <type>
        <v>Identifier = string() | atom()</v>
        <v>MFA = {Mod, Func, Args}</v>
        <v>&nbsp;Mod = Func = atom()</v>
        <v>&nbsp;Args = [term()]</v>
        <v>Result = {ok, Pid} | {error, {already_started, Pid}}</v>
        <v>Pid = pid()</v>
      </type>
      <desc>
        <p>This function starts the standalone <c>nteventlog</c> process
          and, if <c>start_link/2</c> is used, links to it.</p>
        <p><c>Identifier</c> is an identifier as described above.</p>
        <p><c>MFA</c> is the supplied callback function. When
          <c>nteventlog</c> receives information about a new event, this
          function will be called as <c>apply(Mod, Func, [Event|Args])</c> where <c>Event</c> is a tuple</p>
      </desc>
    </func>
    <func>
      <name since="">stop() -> stopped</name>
      <fsummary>Stop the NT eventlog server</fsummary>
      <type>
        <v>Result = stopped</v>
      </type>
      <desc>
        <p>Stops <c>nteventlog</c>. Usually only used during
          development. The server does not have to be shut down
          gracefully to maintain its state.</p>
      </desc>
    </func>
  </funcs>

  <section>
    <title>See Also</title>
    <p><seealso marker="os_mon_app">os_mon(6)</seealso>,
      <seealso marker="os_sup">os_sup(3)</seealso></p>
    <p>Windows NT documentation</p>
  </section>
</erlref>

