<?xml version="1.0" encoding="latin1" ?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter SYSTEM "chapter.dtd">

<chapter>

<header>
<copyright>
<year>2011</year>
<holder>Ericsson AB. All Rights Reserved.</holder>
</copyright>
<legalnotice>
The contents of this file are subject to the Erlang Public License,
Version 1.1, (the "License"); you may not use this file except in
compliance with the License. You should have received a copy of the
Erlang Public License along with this software. If not, it can be
retrieved online at http://www.erlang.org/.

Software distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS"
basis, WITHOUT WARRANTY OF ANY KIND, either express or implied. See
the License for the specific language governing rights and limitations
under the License.

</legalnotice>

<title>Release Notes</title>
<prepared></prepared>
<docno></docno>
<date></date>
<rev></rev>
<file>notes.xml</file>
</header>

<p>
Releases are listed in reverse chronological order, most recent
first.</p>

<!-- ===================================================================== -->

<section>
<title>diameter 0.9</title>

<p>
Initial release of the diameter application.</p>

<p>
Known issues or limitations:</p>

<list>

<item>
<p>
Some agent-related functionality is not entirely complete.
In particular, support for proxy agents, that advertise specific
Diameter applications but otherwise relay messages in much the same
way as relay agents (for which a <seealso
marker="diameter_app#handle_request">handle_request/3</seealso>
callback can return a <c>relay</c> tuple), will be completed in an
upcoming release.
There may also be more explicit support for redirect agents, although
redirect behaviour can be implemented with the current
functionality.</p>

</item>

<item>
<p>
There is some asymmetry in the treatment of messages sent as
<c>diameter_header/avp</c> records and those sent in the "normal"
fashion, and not all of this is documented.
This is related to the previous point since this form of sending a
message was introduced specifically to handle relay agent behaviour
using the same callback interface as for client/server behaviour.</p>
</item>

<item>
<p>
The User's Guide is currently quite thin.
The introductory chapter followed by the examples (in the application
<c>examples</c> subdirectory) may be sufficient
for those having some familiarity with the Diameter protocol but the
intention is to provide more introductory text.
The reference documentation is quite complete, although some points
could likely be expanded upon.</p>
</item>

<item>
<p>
The function <seealso
marker="diameter#service_info">diameter:service_info/2</seealso>
can be used to retrieve information about a started service
(statistics, information about connected peers, etc) but
this is not yet documented and both the input and output may change
in the next release.</p>
</item>


</list>

<p>
See <seealso marker="diameter_soc">Standards Compliance</seealso> for
standards-related issues.</p>
</section>

</chapter>
