<?xml version="1.0" encoding="latin1" ?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter SYSTEM "chapter.dtd">

<chapter>
  <header>
    <copyright>
      <year>2006</year><year>2009</year>
      <holder>Ericsson AB. All Rights Reserved.</holder>
    </copyright>
    <legalnotice>
      The contents of this file are subject to the Erlang Public License,
      Version 1.1, (the "License"); you may not use this file except in
      compliance with the License. You should have received a copy of the
      Erlang Public License along with this software. If not, it can be
      retrieved online at http://www.erlang.org/.
    
      Software distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS"
      basis, WITHOUT WARRANTY OF ANY KIND, either express or implied. See
      the License for the specific language governing rights and limitations
      under the License.
    
    </legalnotice>

    <title>ASN1 Release Notes</title>
    <prepared>Bertil Karlsson</prepared>
    <responsible></responsible>
    <docno></docno>
    <approved></approved>
    <checked></checked>
    <date>06-04-24</date>
    <rev></rev>
    <file>notes_history.sgml</file>
  </header>
  <p>This document describes the changes made to the asn1 system
    from version to version.  The intention of this document is to
    list all incompatibilities as well as all enhancements and
    bug-fixes for every release of the asn1 application. Each release of asn1
    thus constitutes one section in this document. The title of each
    section is the version number of asn1.</p>


  <section>
    <title>Asn1 1.4.4.14</title>

    <section>
      <title>Improvements and New Features</title>
      <list type="bulleted">
        <item>
          <p>Data in info/0 in generated code is moved to attribute
            asn1_info, thus vsn value remains the same if compiler
            options for asn1-spec differs but the generated code is
            the same.</p>
          <p>Own Id: OTP-6462</p>
        </item>
        <item>
          <p>Dialyzer warnings on asn1 are removed, i.e. dead code
            removed.</p>
          <p>Own Id: OTP-6506</p>
        </item>
      </list>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Asn1 1.4.4.13</title>

    <section>
      <title>Improvements and New Features</title>
      <list type="bulleted">
        <item>
          <p>Now it is possible to use 'asn1config' and 'inline'
            options together. It is also possible to use 'inline' on
            a single file like:
            <c>asn1ct:compile("MyASN1spec.asn",[inline])</c>.</p>
          <p>Own Id: OTP-6405</p>
        </item>
      </list>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Asn1 1.4.4.12</title>

    <section>
      <title>Improvements and New Features</title>
      <list type="bulleted">
        <item>
          <p>As a complement to the option "{inline,OutputFile}" it is
            now possible to use the option "inline". Then asn1 creates
            an output file with the name of the source .set file.</p>
          <p>Own Id: OTP-6314</p>
        </item>
      </list>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Asn1 1.4.4.11</title>

    <section>
      <title>Fixed Bugs and Malfunctions</title>
      <list type="bulleted">
        <item>
          <p>When compiling an asn1 source that reference a type in
            another source the compiler uses the asn1db file of the
            other source to resolve the reference. It also tests
            whether the other source has been updated since the
            asn1db file was generated. This last test was to brutal
            in that it exits compilation when no source was found,
            even though a asn1db file existed. Changed behavior from
            a brutal exit to a warning.</p>
          <p>Own Id: OTP-6143</p>
        </item>
      </list>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Asn1 1.4.4.10</title>

    <section>
      <title>Fixed Bugs and Malfunctions</title>
      <list type="bulleted">
        <item>
          <p>asn1 encoding failed on BIT STRING with constraint
            <c>(SIZE (32..MAX))</c>.</p>
          <p>Own Id: OTP-5932</p>
        </item>
        <item>
          <p>Race condition removed in server for variable names for
            generated code.</p>
          <p>Own Id: OTP-6111</p>
        </item>
      </list>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Asn1 1.4.4.9</title>

    <section>
      <title>Fixed Bugs and Malfunctions</title>
      <list type="bulleted">
        <item>
          <p>Now exists a default function clause for table lookup of
            a table constraint. This causes a nice error instead of a
            crash. Did also remove some obsolete funs ({Mod,Fun}) in
            generated code.</p>
          <p>Own Id: OTP-5783</p>
        </item>
        <item>
          <p>ASN1-compiler failed to derive a value out of an external
            reference in some certain cases, when compiling specs so
            that the spec with the reference was compiled before the
            spec with the defined value.</p>
          <p>Own Id: OTP-5812 Aux Id: seq10133 </p>
        </item>
        <item>
          <p>The documentation of how records of embedded types are
            named is extended and made clearer by examples and rules.
            The section "Naming of Records in .hrl Files" in the
            User's Guide is added.</p>
          <p>Own Id: OTP-5831 Aux Id: seq10133 </p>
        </item>
        <item>
          <p>The compiler failed to give right name to record/function
            of a parameterized type that was referenced through
            another instance of a parameterized type in another
            module. The fault occurred when modules were compiled in a
            certain order. Now the compiler resolves the name
            correctly.</p>
          <p>Own Id: OTP-5832 Aux Id: seq10133 </p>
        </item>
      </list>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Asn1 1.4.4.8</title>

    <section>
      <title>Fixed Bugs and Malfunctions</title>
      <list type="bulleted">
        <item>
          <p>The dynamic sort of SET OF values now correctly handles
            values encoded in the "ber_bin, der, optimize" mode, the
            value of a SET OF is a list of binaries.</p>
          <p>Own Id: OTP-5687</p>
        </item>
        <item>
          <p>Bad code was generated for an INTEGER with value-range. If
            the value that was encoded had a lower bound with
            negative value it caused a crash. This bug is now
            removed.</p>
          <p>Own Id: OTP-5688 Aux Id: seq10049 </p>
        </item>
        <item>
          <p>Compiler now handles wrong include paths by returning an
            error if a referenced module is not available.</p>
          <p>Own Id: OTP-5689</p>
        </item>
        <item>
          <p>The bug causing a runtime error when encoding a type
            defined by: <c>BIT STRING {a(1),b(2)}</c> with the value
            [] in <c>per_bin</c> mode is now removed.</p>
          <p>Own Id: OTP-5710 Aux Id: seq10066 </p>
        </item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Improvements and New Features</title>
      <list type="bulleted">
        <item>
          <p>Better handling of filename paths</p>
          <p>Own Id: OTP-5701</p>
        </item>
      </list>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Asn1 1.4.4.7</title>

    <section>
      <title>Fixed Bugs and Malfunctions</title>
      <list type="bulleted">
        <item>
          <p>Effective constraint for <c>per</c> now corrected. For
            instance <c>INTEGER (0|15..269)</c> didn't work properly.</p>
          <p>Own Id: OTP-5477 Aux Id: OTP-5511 </p>
        </item>
        <item>
          <p>Adjusted compiler so that functions in generated code
            only are exported once.</p>
          <p>Own Id: OTP-5509</p>
        </item>
        <item>
          <p>Fixed the compiler failure when handling a value range
            constraint with an extension mark that had the Lower
            bound and/or Upper bound values as an external reference
            to a defined value.</p>
          <p>Own Id: OTP-5511 Aux Id: OTP-5466 </p>
        </item>
        <item>
          <p>Removed sorting of elements for SEQUENCE OF. It shall
            only be done in SET OF.</p>
          <p>Own Id: OTP-5602</p>
        </item>
        <item>
          <p>Corrected code that generated code causing badarith
            warning.</p>
          <p>Own Id: OTP-5616</p>
        </item>
      </list>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Asn1 1.4.4.6</title>

    <section>
      <title>Known Bugs and Problems</title>
      <list type="bulleted">
        <item>
          <p>Compiler now correctly crashes when compiling bad values.
            Failed for instance on INTEGER value that was a reference
            to a defined value. Also solved problem with a union
            constraint on an INTEGER.</p>
          <p>Own Id: OTP-5457</p>
        </item>
        <item>
          <p>Additional coverage of object set syntax.</p>
          <p>Own Id: OTP-5466</p>
        </item>
      </list>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Asn1 1.4.4.5</title>

    <section>
      <title>Fixed Bugs and Malfunctions</title>
      <list type="bulleted">
        <item>
          <p>A bug due to representation of open_type values is now
            fixed. It could cause problem if one used the EXTERNAL
            type.</p>
          <p>Own Id: OTP-5302</p>
        </item>
        <item>
          <p>Due to an internal error the same code could have been
            generated more than one time. This happened for the
            exclusive decode functionality.</p>
          <p>Own Id: OTP-5378</p>
        </item>
      </list>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Asn1 1.4.4.4</title>

    <section>
      <title>Fixed Bugs and Malfunctions</title>
      <list type="bulleted">
        <item>
          <p>Empty objects caused problems. There was trouble when an
            object set referenced imported objects that in turn
            referenced imported types. Lacked support of
            SelectionType in object. All these have been attended.</p>
          <p>Own Id: OTP-5240</p>
        </item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Improvements and New Features</title>
      <list type="bulleted">
        <item>
          <p>Now it is possible to inline asn1 run-time functionality
            in the module generated by the asn1 compiler. Thus, it
            will be only one module doing all encoding/decoding.</p>
          <p>Own Id: OTP-5243</p>
        </item>
      </list>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Asn1 1.4.4.3</title>

    <section>
      <title>Fixed errors and malfunctions</title>
      <list type="bulleted">
        <item>
          <p>A class that was referenced in two steps caused a
            compiler failure.  It is now corrected.</p>
          <p>Own Id: OTP-5103</p>
        </item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Improvements and new features</title>
      <list type="bulleted">
        <item>
          <p>Optionally make it possible to get the un-decoded rest along with 
            the return value. Compile with option <em>undec_rest</em>.</p>
          <p>Own Id: OTP-5104</p>
        </item>
      </list>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Asn1 1.4.4.2</title>

    <section>
      <title>Fixed errors and malfunctions</title>
      <list type="bulleted">
        <item>
          <p>An error due to unchecked referenced imported type resulted
            in missing tag in some table constraint cases. This error is
            now corrected. Error occurred during decode in 
            <c>ber_bin optimized</c> version.</p>
          <p>Own Id: OTP-5022</p>
        </item>
      </list>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Asn1 1.4.4.1</title>

    <section>
      <title>Fixed errors and malfunctions</title>
      <list type="bulleted">
        <item>
          <p>When a referenced value in another module in turn referenced a
            defined value the compilation crashed. This is due to the new
            routines for compilation, that external references are resolved
            during compilation, and not by the order in which modules are
            compiled. This error is now corrected.</p>
          <p>Own Id: OTP-4970</p>
        </item>
      </list>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Asn1 1.4.4</title>

    <section>
      <title>Fixed errors and malfunctions</title>
      <list type="bulleted">
        <item>
          <p>Functionality for parameterized class is added. Parsing failures on
            WithSyntax spec is corrected.</p>
          <p>Own Id: OTP-4893</p>
        </item>
        <item>
          <p>The failure due to Parameterized Type when parameter is an object
            set is corrected.</p>
          <p>Own Id: OTP-4894</p>
          <p>Aux Id: OTP-4893</p>
        </item>
        <item>
          <p>Object Identifier values with two components and the first was a
            value reference failed due to parsing conflicts. Now it is
            corrected.</p>
          <p>Own Id: OTP-4895</p>
        </item>
        <item>
          <p>The erroneous comparison of file name and asn1 module name could
            cause compilation failure. The situation for this failure is rare,
            it requires that other processes modifies the compiled file during
            the compilation procedure. It is now fixed.</p>
          <p>Own Id: OTP-4944</p>
          <p>Aux Id: seq8429</p>
        </item>
        <item>
          <p>Selective decode was ignored when exclusive decode spec in asn1
            configfile was missing. Selective decode failed when the selected
            type was the top type. These bugs are now removed.</p>
          <p>Own Id: OTP-4953</p>
          <p>Aux Id: seq8436</p>
        </item>
        <item>
          <p>The test interface asn1ct:test/1,2,3 and asn1ct:value/2 failed for
            open type and EXTERNAL. The bug is now removed.</p>
          <p>Own Id: OTP-4955</p>
          <p>Aux Id: seq8438)</p>
        </item>
        <item>
          <p>Two equal functions were generated for two components referencing
            the same type when they were picked by the action "parts". The bug
            is now fixed.</p>
          <p>Own Id: OTP-4957</p>
          <p>Aux Id: seq8434</p>
        </item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Improvements and new features</title>
      <list type="bulleted">
        <item>
          <p>INTEGER with named number list and ENUMERATED can now be sub
            constrained with names from the names list.</p>
          <p>Own Id: OTP-4917</p>
        </item>
        <item>
          <p>Now there is support for SelectionType (X 680 section 29)</p>
          <p>Own Id: OTP-4918</p>
        </item>
        <item>
          <p>The compiler now resolves circular dependencies. When asn1 specs
            IMPORTS from each other so that there are circular dependencies.</p>
          <p>Own Id: OTP-4919</p>
        </item>
        <item>
          <p>Now is the asn1 type UTF8String supported. For user instructions
            see documentation.</p>
          <p>Own Id: OTP-4965</p>
        </item>
      </list>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Asn1 1.4.3.1</title>

    <section>
      <title>Fixed Bugs and Malfunctions</title>
      <list type="bulleted">
        <item>
          <p>The <c>{internal_error,...,{ unrecognized_type,...}}</c>
            error occurring for a SET type when compiling with options
            <c>[ber_bin,optimize,der]</c> is now corrected.</p>
          <p>Own Id: OTP-4866</p>
        </item>
        <item>
          <p>False encode of BIT STRING in PER (per_bin,optimize) is fixed. The error occurred when there was a type like BIT STRING (SIZE(C)) and C &gt; 16.</p>
          <p>Own Id: OTP-4869</p>
        </item>
      </list>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Asn1 1.4.3</title>

    <section>
      <title>Fixed errors and malfunctions</title>
      <list type="bulleted">
        <item>
          <p>Functionality to handle parameterized object sets have been added.</p>
          <p>Own Id: OTP-4832</p>
        </item>
        <item>
          <p>Bug causing duplicated function definitions using exclusive decode is removed.</p>
          <p>Own Id: OTP-4833)</p>
        </item>
        <item>
          <p>The race condition when loading asn1 driver is solved.</p>
          <p>Own Id: OTP-4835</p>
        </item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Improvements and new features</title>
      <list type="bulleted">
        <item>
          <p>A specialized decode, <em>selective decode</em> is now available. It decodes a chosen internal sub-type of a constructed type.</p>
          <p>Own Id: OTP-4856)</p>
        </item>
      </list>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Asn1 1.4.2.2</title>

    <section>
      <title>Fixed errors and malfunctions</title>
      <list type="bulleted">
        <item>
          <p>Release of Asn1 1.4.2.1 on R7B, The functionality is the same, but
            the layer between the driver and the asn1 erlang code is different.</p>
        </item>
      </list>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Asn1 1.4.2.1</title>

    <section>
      <title>Fixed errors and malfunctions</title>
      <list type="bulleted">
        <item>
          <p>ObjectDescriptor does now work as part of a sequence, set or choice.</p>
          <p>Own Id: OTP-4773</p>
        </item>
        <item>
          <p>When a SEQUENCE that have extension mark was decoded inside a
            SEQUENCE OF it could cause decode error due to a failure in
            restbytes2. It is now corrected.</p>
          <p>Own Id: OTP-4791)</p>
        </item>
        <item>
          <p>Now the bug is fixed that caused the compiler crash on an untagged
            optional open type.</p>
          <p>Own Id: OTP-4792</p>
        </item>
        <item>
          <p>The earlier exit caused by bad in-data is now fixed so it will
            return an {error,Reason} tuple.</p>
            return an {error,Reason} tuple.</p>
          <p>Own Id: OTP-4797</p>
        </item>
        <item>
          <p>Open type encoded with indefinite length is now correct decoded.</p>
          <p>Own Id: OTP-4798</p>
        </item>
        <item>
          <p>Now is absent optional open types handled correctly.</p>
          <p>Own Id: OTP-4799</p>
        </item>
        <item>
          <p>Now is the necessary functions available for sorting in run-time of
            SET and SET OF components.</p>
          <p>Own Id: OTP-4809</p>
        </item>
      </list>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Asn1 1.4.2</title>

    <section>
      <title>Fixed errors and malfunctions</title>
      <list type="bulleted">
        <item>
          <p>When a component in a SEQUENCE is a CHOICE (or reference to a CHOICE)
            and the SEQUENCE's component and one of the alternatives in the CHOICE
            have identical names, an error may occur if one doesn't use the
            'optimized' versions of the compiler. In the older versions (<c>ber, ber_bin, per, per_bin</c>) one could optionally apply a value of a
            component as <c>{ComponentName,Value}</c>, and the generated code
            chooses the second element of the tuple. However, a value of a CHOICE
            must be applied as a tuple: <c>{AlternativeName,Value}</c>. Thus,
            in the rare case described above and if the value to the SEQUENCE's
            component is not in a tuple notation the
            <c>{AlternativeName,Value}</c> will be peeled off in the SEQUENCE
            and the value fed to the CHOICE will only be the <c>Value</c>
            part of <c>{AlternativeName,Value}</c>, and the encoder crashes.
            The best way to avoid this is to use the optimized version of the
            compiler where the unnecessary tuple notation
            <c>{ComponentName,Value}</c> no longer is allowed. Since it isn't
            possible to solve this bug in the compiler.</p>
          <p>Own Id: OTP-4693</p>
        </item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Improvements and new features</title>
      <list type="bulleted">
        <item>
          <p>Exclusive decode is enabled by a compiler option and a configuration
            file. It makes it possible to leave parts of an ASN.1 encoded message
            un-decoded.</p>
          <p>Own Id: OTP-4744</p>
        </item>
      </list>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Asn1 1.4.1.1</title>

    <section>
      <title>Fixed errors and malfunctions</title>
      <list type="bulleted">
        <item>
          <p>The documentation about how extensibility is handled is now corrected.</p>
          <p>Own Id: OTP-4663</p>
        </item>
        <item>
          <p>Function in object now calls the exported function</p>
          <p>Own Id: OTP-4665</p>
        </item>
        <item>
          <p>Now is tags for ObjectClassFieldType analyzed correctly.</p>
          <p>Own Id: OTP-4666</p>
        </item>
      </list>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Asn1 1.4.1</title>

    <section>
      <title>Fixed errors and malfunctions</title>
      <list type="bulleted">
        <item>
          <p>Now is the Default value for an ENUMERATED returned as the name from
            the NamedList when decoding.</p>
          <p>Own Id: OTP-4633</p>
        </item>
        <item>
          <p>It was an internal failure when permitted alphabet constraint existed
            together with for instance a size constraint. E.g. when a
            referenced type is constrained by a size constraint and the defined
            type in turn is constrained by a permitted alphabet constraint.</p>
          <p>Own Id: OTP-4559</p>
        </item>
        <item>
          <p>Record is generated in hrl file for a CHOICE with extension mark
            that has an internal SEQUENCE/SET definition.</p>
          <p>Own Id:  OTP-4560</p>
        </item>
        <item>
          <p>Now is the length of a SEQUENCE/SET OF correctly encoded/decoded (PER).</p>
          <p>Own Id: OTP-4590</p>
        </item>
        <item>
          <p>The problem with unordered decoded terms when a component is a
            ObjectClassFieldType has been solved.</p>
          <p>Own Id: OTP-4591</p>
        </item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Improvements and new features</title>
      <list type="bulleted">
        <item>
          <p>More complex definitions with TableConstraints where the SimpleTable
            and ComponentRelation are on different levels is now fully
            supported.</p>
          <p>Own Id: OTP-4631</p>
        </item>
      </list>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Asn1 1.4</title>

    <section>
      <title>Fixed errors and malfunctions</title>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Improvements and new features</title>
      <list type="bulleted">
        <item>
          <p>Each generated .erl file have now a function info/0 that returns
            information about the used compiler version and options.</p>
          <p>Own Id: OTP-4373</p>
        </item>
        <item>
          <p>When compiling an ASN.1 module the compiler generates an Erlang module
            that is compiled by the Erlang compiler. Earlier it was not possible to
            add options to the final step, the Erlang compilation. By adding any
            option that is not recognized as a specific ASN.1 option it will be
            passed to the final step like: <c>erlc +debug_info  Mymodule.asn</c> or
            <c>asn1ct:compile('Mymodule',[debug_info])</c>.</p>
          <p>Own Id: OTP-4491</p>
        </item>
        <item>
          <p>Earlier one couldn't multi file compile modules that had different
            tagdefault, which now is possible. Equal Type/Value names in different
            modules are resolved by renaming (concatenate type name and module
            name): If two types with the same name T exist in module A and module B
            they will get the new names TA and TB.</p>
          <p>(Own Id: OTP-4492)</p>
          <p>Aux Id: OTP-3983</p>
        </item>
        <item>
          <p>BER: Encode/decode of data have been significantly improved. By use of
            the compiler options <c>ber_bin</c> and <c>optimize</c>,
            optimized code will be generated and the optimized run-time module will
            be used.</p>
          <p>Own Id: OTP-4493</p>
        </item>
      </list>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Asn1 1.3.3.1</title>

    <section>
      <title>Fixed errors and malfunctions</title>
      <list type="bulleted">
        <item>
          <p>Proper length encoding and padding implemented for a <c>BIT STRING</c> with 
            NamedNumberList and size constraint as value range. This functionality 
            didn't work in the rare occasion when the NamedNumberList is shorter
            than the lower bound of the constraint.As in this example:
            <c>TestS ::= BIT STRING {a (0),b (1)} (SIZE (3..8))</c></p>
          <p>(Own Id: OTP-4353)</p>
        </item>
        <item>
          <p>Bug in compiler, when an <c>OBJECT IDENTIFIER</c> value consisting of 
            two identifiers (Defined values or Name form identifiers) was falsely
            interpreted causing a compiling error is now corrected.</p>
          <p>(Own Id: OTP-4354)</p>
        </item>
        <item>
          <p>Internal error in check phase that caused crash on 
            <c>ObjectClassFieldType</c> in ber_bin is corrected.</p>
          <p>(Own Id: OTP-4390)</p>
        </item>
        <item>
          <p>Tags for open types are handled according to <c>x.680 30.6c</c>, i.e.
            open types shall not be tagged <c>IMPLICIT.</c></p>
          <p>(Own Id: OTP-4395)</p>
          <p>(Aux Id: OTP-4390)</p>
        </item>
      </list>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Asn1 1.3.3</title>

    <section>
      <title>Fixed errors and malfunctions</title>
      <list type="bulleted">
        <item>
          <p>Now gives the compiler an appropriate error report when exported 
            undefined types are detected.</p>
          <p>(Own Id: OTP-4129)</p>
        </item>
        <item>
          <p>The type <c>ObjectDescriptor</c> is now supported, previously the
            implementation of encode/decode for this rarely used type was
            incomplete.</p>
          <p>(Own Id: OTP-4161)</p>
          <p>(Aux Id: seq7165)</p>
        </item>
        <item>
          <p>In case of per and compact_bit_string the rightmost byte were erroneous
            truncated when the rightmost bits of that byte were zeros. This is now
            corrected.</p>
          <p>(Own Id: OTP-4200)</p>
        </item>
        <item>
          <p>Bad match of return-value from decode_length in skipvalue/3 has now been
            fixed.</p>
          <p>(Own Id: OTP-4232)</p>
        </item>
        <item>
          <p>Now is decode of ENUMERATED handled correctly, when tagged EXPLICIT.</p>
          <p>(Own Id: OTP-4234)</p>
        </item>
        <item>
          <p>The compiler now parses and handles the ValueFromObject construct.</p>
          <p>(Own Id: OTP-4242)</p>
        </item>
        <item>
          <p>Now does the compiler handle the case when the object set in simple
            table and componentrelation constraints is of a CLASS without a UNIQUE
            field. In this case is the octets, which is assumed to be encoded,
            encoded as an open type.</p>
          <p>(Own Id: OTP-4248)</p>
          <p>(Aux Id: OTP-4242)</p>
        </item>
        <item>
          <p>Compiler handles objects in AdditionalElementSetSpec in ObjectSetSpec,
            i.e. the objects that are referred to after the ellipses in an object set.</p>
          <p>(Own Id: OTP-4275)</p>
        </item>
        <item>
          <p>Now are values with a component of type CHOICE encoded with indefinite 
            length correctly decoded.</p>
          <p>(Own Id: OTP-4358)</p>
        </item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Improvements and new features</title>
      <list type="bulleted">
        <item>
          <p>The language constructs (from the old 1988 standard) <c>ANY</c>
            and <c>ANY DEFINED BY</c> are now implemented.</p>
          <p>(Own Id: OTP-2741)</p>
          <p>(Aux Id: seq 1188)</p>
        </item>
        <item>
          <p>Now it is checked in run-time if a <c>OBJECT IDENTIFIER</c> value is invalid</p>
          <p>(Own Id: OTP-4235)</p>
        </item>
        <item>
          <p>The ASN.1 types EXTERNAL,EMBEDDED PDV and CHARACTER STRING now have full support in the compiler.</p>
          <p>(Own Id: OTP-4247)</p>
        </item>
        <item>
          <p>A driver in C does the final job (complete) of the PER encoding when 
            files are compiled with <c>per_bin</c> and <c>optimize</c> flags. 
            It gives significant faster encoding for PER.</p>
          <p>(Own Id: OTP-4355)</p>
        </item>
        <item>
          <p>Encode and decode of PER encoding has been made faster by moving 
            analysis done in run-time to compile-time. These optimizations are 
            available by compiling ASN.1 files with options <c>per_bin</c> and
            <c>optimize</c>.</p>
          <p>(Own Id: OTP-4381)</p>
          <p>(Aux Id: OTP-4355)</p>
        </item>
      </list>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Asn1 1.3.2</title>

    <section>
      <title>Fixed errors and malfunctions</title>
      <list type="bulleted">
        <item>
          <p>Now does the compiler check values (including referenced values), and
            formats the value so it is suitable to use as input to encoding
            functions.</p>
          <p>(Own Id: OTP-3277)</p>
          <p>(Aux Id: OTP-4103)</p>
        </item>
        <item>
          <p>Unnecessary external function calls in generated code are now generated
            as internal function calls.</p>
          <p>(Own Id: OTP-4073)</p>
        </item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Improvements and new features</title>
      <list type="bulleted">
        <item>
          <p>Now is Information Objects supported in BER encoding.</p>
          <p>(Own Id: OTP-3980)</p>
          <p>(Aux Id: OTP-3979 OTP-3978)</p>
          <p></p>
        </item>
        <item>
          <p>PER: A new option <c>per_bin</c> is now supported. When used the
            generated encode/decode functions use binaries and the bit syntax to
            get better performance than the old <c>per</c> variant which used
            lists. All values input to encode and returned from decode are
            compatible between <c>per</c> and <c>per_bin</c> except for
            open types which are represented as binaries with per_bin and octet
            lists with per. We recommend that you use per_bin instead of per from
            now on, the use of binaries will be the default in coming versions and
            all improvements and optimizations for PER will be concentrated to that
            solution.</p>
          <p>(Own Id: OTP-4094)</p>
          <p></p>
        </item>
        <item>
          <p>Support for DER implemented. Used by flag +der when compiling. Include
            the full BER encoding plus: sorting of SET components, sorting of
            encoded elements in SET OF, full check of default values in SET and
            SEQUENCE. See new documentation on DER in user_guide sections 1.3.1;
            1.4.11; 1.4.12; 1.4.14; 1.4.16 and 1.10, in the reference manual for
            asn1ct.</p>
          <p>(Own Id: OTP-4103)</p>
          <p></p>
        </item>
      </list>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Asn1 1.3.1</title>

    <section>
      <title>Fixed errors and malfunctions</title>
      <list type="bulleted">
        <item>
          <p>Do not generate record in .hrl file for SET types</p>
          <p>Own Id: OTP-4025</p>
        </item>
        <item>
          <p>Fixed internal error when using BIT STRINGs with Named Number List in combination with <c>compact_bit_string</c> and <c>ber_bin</c> options.</p>
          <p>Own Id: OTP-4026</p>
          <p>Aux Id: OTP-3982</p>
        </item>
        <item>
          <p>The atom 'com' can now be used in ENUMERATED as an EnumerationItem.</p>
          <p>Own Id: OTP-4037</p>
          <p>Aux Id: Seq 7036</p>
        </item>
        <item>
          <p>ber: Now it is possible (again) to encode data format "{Type,Value}" in a SEQUENCE OF  RequestParameter, when RequestParameter is of type ENUMERATED. The {Type,Value}
            notation is not recommended for use, it is redundant and exist only for very ancient backwards compatibility reasons. The "feature" might be removed in forthcoming versions.</p>
          <p>Own Id: OTP-4057</p>
          <p>Aux Id: Seq 7066</p>
        </item>
        <item>
          <p>A bug in the parser, that caused failure on COMPONENTS OF is now removed.</p>
          <p>Own Id: OTP-4058</p>
        </item>
      </list>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Asn1 1.3</title>

    <section>
      <title>Known problems</title>
      <list type="bulleted">
        <item>
          <p>The compiler will now check that a value referenced by name
            does exist.</p>
          <p>Own Id: OTP-3277</p>
        </item>
        <item>
          <p>BER:Decode of a type T ::= SEQUENCE OF C fails if C is encoded with indefinite length.
            This is know corrected.</p>
          <p>Own Id: OTP-3811</p>
          <p>Aux Id: seq5040</p>
        </item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Fixed errors and malfunctions</title>
      <list type="bulleted">
        <item>
          <p>The new parser handles imports when one import ends with FROM, a modulename and a reference to a objectidentifier followed by imports from other modules.</p>
          <p>Own Id: OTP-3463</p>
        </item>
        <item>
          <p>The compiler did not check that a name mentioned as EXPORTED
            actually is defined within the module.
            This is now corrected.</p>
          <p>Own Id: OTP-3659</p>
        </item>
        <item>
          <p>Removed bug caused by use of nested indefinite length</p>
          <p>Own Id: OTP-3994</p>
        </item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Improvements and new features</title>
      <list type="bulleted">
        <item>
          <p>Now supporting most common use of parameterization according to X.683</p>
          <p>(Own Id: OTP-3978)</p>
        </item>
        <item>
          <p>PER: Now supporting most common use of Information Objects according to X.681. A new parser has been implemented. The error messages due to syntax errors are slightly different than previous. TableConstraint part of X.682 now also supported.</p>
          <p>Own Id: OTP-3979</p>
        </item>
        <item>
          <p>New compiler option added: <c>ber_bin</c>. The compiler generates code with new bit syntax. Run time functions uses bit syntax when feasible. Higher encoding/decoding performance in most cases. Se also comments for Asn1 1.2.9.3.</p>
          <p>Own Id: OTP-3981</p>
        </item>
        <item>
          <p>A more compact format of BIT STRING in Erlang is now available by use of the compiler option <c>compact_bit_string</c>. It is much faster when large BIT STRINGs are used.</p>
          <p>Own Id: OTP-3982</p>
        </item>
        <item>
          <p>Now possible to merge many ASN.1 input files to one Erlang file by use of a configuration file that lists the ASN.1 files.</p>
          <p>Own Id: OTP-3983</p>
        </item>
        <item>
          <p>New documentation in <em>User's Guide</em> in section:</p>
          <p>3.1: New compile-time functions and options are described.</p>
          <p>4.6: New compact format of BIT STRING is described.</p>
          <p>4.8: Additional comments on character strings.</p>
          <p>7: New section describing ASN.1 Information Objects.</p>
          <p>8: New section describing Parameterization.</p>
          <p><em>Reference Manual/asn1ct</em> New compile options are described.</p>
          <p>Own Id: OTP-3984</p>
          <p>Aux Id: OTP-3978, OTP-3979, OTP-3981, OTP-3982, OTP-3983</p>
        </item>
        <item>
          <p>Added the functionality to invoke ASN1Mod:encode (and decode).</p>
          <p>Own Id: OTP-3985</p>
        </item>
        <item>
          <p>Performance improvements by removing not necessary use of apply when calling asn1rt:encode. Also other general improvements.</p>
          <p>Own Id: OTP-3988</p>
        </item>
      </list>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Asn1 1.2.9.6</title>

    <section>
      <title>Known problems</title>
      <list type="bulleted">
        <item>
          <p>The compiler does not check that an exported name actually exists in the ASN.1 module.</p>
          <p>Own Id: OTP-3659</p>
        </item>
        <item>
          <p>The compiler does not check that a value referenced by name does exist.</p>
          <p>Own Id: OTP-3277</p>
        </item>
        <item>
          <p>BER: The compiler does not take the extensions into account when checking if
            the tags are unique in a SEQUENCE or SET.</p>
          <p>Own Id: OTP-3304</p>
        </item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Fixed errors and malfunctions</title>
      <list type="bulleted">
        <item>
          <p>PER: Trailing zeroes in a BIT STRING declared without named bits
            should not be removed in the encodings.</p>
          <p>Own Id: OTP-3830</p>
        </item>
      </list>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Asn1 1.2.9.5</title>

    <section>
      <title>Known problems</title>
      <p>Same as for 1.2.9.3.</p>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Fixed errors and malfunctions</title>
      <list type="bulleted">
        <item>
          <p>PER: Constraints are not propagated when types are
            referring to each other. Example:</p>
          <code type="none">
 
                TBCD-STRING ::= OCTET STRING
 
                LAI ::= TBCD-STRING (SIZE(3))          </code>
          <p>The size constraint is not passed on during encode,decode
            resulting in wrong encoding for PER , it is
            coded with a length determinant which should not be there
            when the length is fixed. For BER this does not matter because the constraints does
            not affect the encodings.</p>
          <p>Own Id: OTP-3713</p>
        </item>
        <item>
          <p>The generated code gets wrong if there are several ENUMERATED fields in a SEQUENCE or SET, this is now corrected.</p>
          <p>Own Id: OTP-3796</p>
        </item>
        <item>
          <p>BER:Decode of a type T ::= SEQUENCE OF C fails if C is encoded with indefinite length.
            This is know corrected.</p>
          <p>Own Id: OTP-3811</p>
        </item>
      </list>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Asn1 1.2.9.3</title>

    <section>
      <title>Known problems</title>
      <list type="bulleted">
        <item>
          <p>The compiler does not check that an exported name actually exists in the ASN.1 module.</p>
          <p>Own Id: OTP-3659</p>
        </item>
        <item>
          <p>The compiler does not check that a value referenced by name does exist.</p>
          <p>Own Id: OTP-3277</p>
        </item>
        <item>
          <p>BER: The compiler does not take the extensions into account when checking if
            the tags are unique in a SEQUENCE or SET.</p>
          <p>Own Id: OTP-3304</p>
        </item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Fixed errors and malfunctions</title>
      <list type="bulleted">
        <item>
          <p>This version supports soft upgrade from versions 1.2.6 1.2.7.</p>
        </item>
        <item>
          <p>In an ENUMERATED type like this:</p>
          <code type="none">
\011\011T ::= ENUMERATED { blue, green}          </code>
          <p>The symbols was encoded/decoded with the wrong values, i.e in
            reverse order. This is now corrected.</p>
          <p>Own Id: OTP-3700</p>
        </item>
        <item>
          <p>PER: OCTET STRING with Size constrained to a single value i.e fixed size
            was treated wrong during encode and decode. This is now corrected.</p>
          <p>Own Id: OTP-3701</p>
        </item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Improvements and new features</title>
      <list type="bulleted">
        <item>
          <p>There is now a new compiler option <c>ber_bin</c> available that can be used to 
            generate encode/decode functions for BER that uses the new "bit-syntax" to
            make the functions more efficient. The <c>ber_bin</c> option is used
            as an alternative to the <c>ber</c> and <c>per</c> options.</p>
          <p>The encode function then produces a
            possibly nested list of binaries and integer lists. The decode function does 
            in this case require a single binary as input instead of a list.
            The modules generated with this option require that you have an R7A  or later
            system, otherwise they will not compile and the runtime module asn1rt_ber_bin
            can not be executed.</p>
          <p>The ber_bin option is not officially supported in this version (will be
            in a later version) but is provided for those who want to try it. 
            It should be significantly faster at decode and is slightly faster at encode.
            Exactly how performance differs between this binary approach and the
            list approach depends highly on the type of input.
            Another thing worth noting is that both approaches still have a lot of
            solutions in common which can be improved a lot to gain even better 
            performance.</p>
        </item>
      </list>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Asn1 1.2.9.2</title>

    <section>
      <title>Fixed errors and malfunctions</title>
      <list type="bulleted">
        <item>
          <p>BER: Encode/decode of extension components did not work properly. This is now corrected.</p>
          <p>Own Id: OTP-3395</p>
          <p>Aux Id: </p>
          <p>PER:The encode/decode of NULL as an open type has been corrected. An open type must always have a length of at least 1 byte even if the contained 
            value (e.g NULL) encodes to nothing.</p>
          <p>Own Id: OTP-3496</p>
          <p>Aux Id: </p>
        </item>
        <item>
          <p>BER:In the current implementation extension components of a SEQUENCE are required
            to be present when they are specified as mandatory. This is an error, all extension
            components are "optional" even if they are not specified to have the OPTIONAL or
            DEFAULT property. This is now corrected.</p>
          <p>Own Id: OTP-3278</p>
        </item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Improvements and new features</title>
      <list type="bulleted">
        <item>
          <p>The ASN.1 language feature <c>COMPONENTS OF</c> is now implemented.</p>
          <p>Own Id: OTP-2515</p>
        </item>
        <item>
          <p>The encoding and decoding of ENUMERATED and
            INTEGER with NamedNumbers is made more efficient and thus
            faster in runtime.</p>
          <p>Own Id: OTP-3464</p>
          <p>Aux Id:</p>
        </item>
        <item>
          <p>Added support for encode/decode of open type which is
            constrained to a specific type. Previously the value of
            an open type had to be a list of  octets, but now the Erlang
            representation of the specific type used in the constraint
            is used both as input to encode and as output from decode.</p>
          <p>Own Id: OTP-3569</p>
          <p>Aux Id: </p>
        </item>
        <item>
          <p>PER: GeneralString, GraphicalString etc. i.e all strings
            that are not so called "known-multiplier character
            string types" are now supported by the runtime 
            encode/decode functions.</p>
          <p>Own Id: OTP-3573</p>
          <p>Aux Id:</p>
        </item>
      </list>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Asn1 1.2.6</title>

    <section>
      <title>Known problems</title>
      <list type="bulleted">
        <item>
          <p>The ASN.1 language feature <c>COMPONENTS OF</c> is not implemented.</p>
          <p>Own Id: OTP-2515</p>
        </item>
        <item>
          <p>The compiler does not check that a value referenced by name does exist.</p>
          <p>Own Id: OTP-3277</p>
        </item>
        <item>
          <p>BER:In the current implementation extension components of a SEQUENCE are required
            to be present when they are specified as mandatory. This is an error, all extension
            components are "optional" even if they are not specified to have the OPTIONAL or
            DEFAULT property.</p>
          <p>Own Id: OTP-3278</p>
        </item>
        <item>
          <p>BER: The compiler does not take the extensions into account when checking if
            the tags are unique in a SEQUENCE or SET.</p>
          <p>Own Id: OTP-3304</p>
        </item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Fixed errors and malfunctions</title>
      <list type="bulleted">
        <item>
          <p>This version supports soft upgrade from versions 1.1.1, 1.1.5 and 1.1.6.
            Two new runtime modules <c>asn1rt_ber_v1</c> and 
            <c>asn1rt_per_v1</c> are delivered together with the old ones. This makes
            it possible to continue running applications with modules generated with the
            previous version of the asn1 compiler while modules generated by this version
            will use the new runtime modules. Note that it is only advice-able to continue
            running old generates if they are working perfectly and have no need 
            for the corrections made in this version of the asn1 application.</p>
        </item>
        <item>
          <p>BER: SEQUENCEs encoded with indefinite length was not correctly decoded.
            This in now corrected.</p>
          <p>Own Id: OTP-3352</p>
          <p>Aux Id: Seq 4100</p>
        </item>
      </list>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Asn1 1.2.4</title>

    <section>
      <title>Fixed errors and malfunctions</title>
      <list type="bulleted">
        <item>
          <p>The compiler now  detects multiple definitions of values and types and reports this as
            an error. Previously this was detected when the generated Erlang module was compiled.</p>
          <p>Own Id: OTP-3105</p>
        </item>
        <item>
          <p>BER: An error regarding encoding of <c>ENUMERATED</c> present in asn1-1.1.1 
            is corrected. The new version 1.1.2 of asn1 containing this correction is 
            delivered as a "patch".</p>
          <p>Own Id: OTP-3169</p>
        </item>
        <item>
          <p>BER: Decoding of <c>SEQUENCE OF</c> and <c>SET OF</c> with indefinite length is corrected.
            The correction was first delivered in version 1.1.2.</p>
          <p>Own Id: OTP-3170</p>
        </item>
        <item>
          <p>BER: Encoding and decoding of <c>ENUMERATED</c> 
            with extensionmark
            "..." did not work (crashed with a runtime error). This
            has now been corrected. If an unknown enumerated value is
            decoded (for an extensible enumerated type) 
            it is returned as <c>{asn1_enum,Value}</c> where
            <c>Value</c> is an integer. Enumerated values in this format
            are also accepted by the encoder.  
            ASN.1 modules containing 
            <c>ENUMERATED</c> with extensionmark should be 
            recompiled with the corrected
            version of the compiler. The BER runtime functions are also
            corrected.
            Note that this correction has already been delivered as a
            bugfix for R4B (OTP-2951).</p>
          <p>Own Id: OTP-3202</p>
          <p>Aux Id: Seq3745</p>
        </item>
        <item>
          <p>BER: The primitive/constructed bit in the tag byte of an encoding
            is not correct when it comes to user defined tags.
            For example in </p>
          <code type="none">
 T ::= [2] SEQUENCE { a BOOLEAN}           </code>
          <p>the tag 2 does not get the constructed bit set which it should.
            This is now corrected.</p>
          <p>Own Id: OTP-3241</p>
        </item>
        <item>
          <p>The decoder can now detect if there are unexpected bytes 
            remaining when all components of a sequence are decoded.
            The decoder will then return <c>{error,{asn1{unexpected,Bytes}}}</c></p>
          <p>Own Id: OTP-3270</p>
        </item>
        <item>
          <p>Values of type <c>OBJECT IDENTIFIER</c> was sometimes returned as an Erlang list
            (ASN.1 constants) and  sometimes as a tuple (from the decode functions). This is now
            changed so that <c>OBJECT IDENTIFIER</c> values always are represented as an Erlang
            tuple.</p>
          <p>Own Id: OTP-3280</p>
        </item>
        <item>
          <p>PER:The encode/decode functions could not handle integers with 
            a range greater than 16#7ffffff. This limit is now removed.</p>
          <p>Own Id: OTP-3287</p>
        </item>
        <item>
          <p>PER: The encoding/decoding of the length for a SET OF/SEQUENCE OF
            was wrong if there was a size constraint. This is now corrected.</p>
          <p>Own Id: OTP-3291</p>
        </item>
        <item>
          <p>PER: Encoding of a constrained INTEGER (range &gt; 16 k) was wrong for
            the value 0. This is now corrected.</p>
          <p>Own Id: OTP-3306</p>
        </item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Improvements and new features</title>
      <list type="bulleted">
        <item>
          <p>The ASN.1 module name and the filename where the ASN.1
            specification resides must match each other (has always been the
            case). This is now checked by the compiler. The check requires that
            the names match in a case or case insensitive way depending on the
            characteristics for the current system.</p>
          <p>Own Id: OTP-1843</p>
        </item>
        <item>
          <p>PER: Encode/decode of an extension value (i.e not within the root set) for
            <c>ENUMERATED</c> did not work properly. This is now corrected.
            If an unknown enumerated value is
            decoded (for an extensible enumerated type) 
            it is returned as <c>{asn1_enum,Value}</c> where
            <c>Value</c> is an integer. Enumerated values in this format
            are also accepted by the encoder (if the value is &gt;= the number of known 
            extension values).</p>
          <p>Own Id: OTP-2930</p>
        </item>
        <item>
          <p>Unnecessary printouts from the compiler are removed.
            The compiler version and the compiler options are now
            printed to stdout.</p>
          <p>Own Id: OTP-3276</p>
        </item>
        <item>
          <p>In order to better suite the use of ASN.1 in embedded systems only 
            the modules needed in runtime are now listed in the <c>.app</c> file.</p>
          <p>Own Id: OTP-3279</p>
        </item>
        <item>
          <p>The compiler now supports extensionmarker in constraint specifications.
            Example:</p>
          <code type="none">
INTEGER (0..10, ...)          </code>
          <p>In previous version this was reported as a syntax error.</p>
          <p>Own Id: OTP-3281</p>
        </item>
        <item>
          <p>A very limited part of ITU-T recommendation X.681 
            Abstract Syntax Notation One (ASN.1): Information
            object specification is now implemented. Specifically \011
            TYPE IDENTIFIER is recognized by the compiler.</p>
          <p>Own Id: OTP-3325</p>
        </item>
        <item>
          <p>Parameterization of ASN.1 specifications (ITU-T X.683) is now
            supported to a limited extent.</p>
          <p>Own Id: OTP-3326</p>
        </item>
      </list>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Asn1 1.1.3.1</title>

    <section>
      <title>Fixed errors and malfunctions</title>
      <list type="bulleted">
        <item>
          <p>BER Encoding and decoding of <c>ENUMERATED</c> 
            with extensionmark
            "..." did not work (crashed with a runtime error). This
            has now been corrected. If an unknown enumerated value is
            decoded (for an extensible enumerated type) 
            it is returned as <c>{asn1_enum,Value}</c> where
            <c>Value</c> is an integer. Enumerated values in this format
            are also accepted by the encoder.  
            ASN.1 modules containing 
            <c>ENUMERATED</c> with extensionmark should be 
            recompiled with the corrected
            version of the compiler. The BER runtime functions are also
            corrected.
            Note that this correction has already been delivered as a
            bug-fix for R4B (OTP-2951).</p>
          <p>Own Id: OTP-3202</p>
          <p>Aux Id: Seq3745</p>
        </item>
      </list>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Asn1 1.1.1</title>

    <section>
      <title>Known problems</title>
      <list type="bulleted">
        <item>
          <p>The syntactic construct <c>COMPONENTS OF</c> is not
            implemented.</p>
          <p>Own Id: OTP-2515</p>
        </item>
        <item>
          <p><c>ANY</c> and <c>ANY DEFINED BY</c> are currently not 
            supported.</p>
          <p>Own Id: OTP-2741</p>
          <p>Aux Id: seq 1188</p>
        </item>
        <item>
          <p>Multiple definitions of the same Type or Value is not detected
            by the compiler. The error occurs when the generated Erlang
            module is compiled.</p>
          <p>Own Id: OTP-3105</p>
        </item>
      </list>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Asn1 1.1</title>

    <section>
      <title>Known problems</title>
      <list type="bulleted">
        <item>
          <p>The primitive/constructed bit in the tag byte of an encoding
            is not correct when it comes to user defined tags.
            For example in</p>
          <code type="none">
 T ::= [2] SEQUENCE { a BOOLEAN}           </code>
          <p>the tag 2 does not get the constructed bit set which it should.
            This is now corrected.</p>
          <p>Own Id: OTP-3241</p>
        </item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Fixed errors and malfunctions</title>
      <list type="bulleted">
        <item>
          <p>The BER decoder failed to decode certain nested data types
            where <c>IMPLICIT</c> tags where involved. 
            This is now corrected.</p>
          <p>Own Id: OTP-2719</p>
          <p>Aux Id: seq 1148</p>
        </item>
        <item>
          <p>The handling of types with extension marker "..." is corrected.
            Earlier each SEQUENCE and SET with an extension marker got an
            extra field named <c>asn1_EXT</c> in the generated record.
            This was a mistake and that field is now removed (concerns
            both BER and BER).</p>
          <p>Own Id: OTP-2724</p>
          <p>Aux Id: seq 1148, OTP-2719</p>
        </item>
        <item>
          <p>The decoder (both BER and PER) could not handle unnamed
            bits of a <c>BIT STRING</c> if the type had any 
            named bits declared. This is now corrected and the unnamed
            bits are returned as <c>{bit,Pos}</c> where Pos is the bit 
            position. The <c>{bit,Pos}</c> can be used as input to the
            encoder too.</p>
          <p>Own Id: OTP-2725</p>
          <p>Aux Id: seq 1148,OTP-2719,OTP-2724</p>
        </item>
        <item>
          <p>The functions <c>asn1rt:decode</c> and <c>asn1ct:decode</c>
            did not always return <c>{ok,Result}</c> or 
            <c>{error,Reason}</c> as documented. This is now corrected.</p>
          <p>Own Id: OTP-2730</p>
          <p>Aux Id: seq 1158</p>
        </item>
        <item>
          <p>The compiler did not accept CHOICE types as components 
            of a SEQUENCE or SET when
            the modules tag default was IMPLICIT. 
            Example:</p>
          <code type="none">
C ::= CHOICE { ......}
A ::= SEQUENCE {
a [1] C, -- This was not accepted
.....          </code>
          <p>This was an error
            caused by a misinterpretation of the ASN.1 standard. This
            is now corrected.</p>
          <p>Own Id: OTP-2731</p>
          <p>Aux Id: seq 1163</p>
        </item>
        <item>
          <p>When decoding a SEQUENCE A which contains an OPTIONAL component
            b which is a SEQUENCE with mandatory components, the decoder
            does not detect as an error that a mandatory component of b
            is missing. The same error could occur also in other cases
            with nested types and optional components of SEQUENCE or SET.
            This is now corrected.</p>
          <p>Own Id: OTP-2738</p>
          <p>Aux Id: seq 1183</p>
        </item>
        <item>
          <p>BER Encoding and decoding of <c>ENUMERATED</c> 
            with extensionmark
            "..." did not work (crashed with a runtime error). This
            has now been corrected. If an unknown enumerated value is
            decoded (for an extensible enumerated type) 
            it is returned as <c>{asn1_enum,Value}</c> where
            <c>Value</c> is an integer. Enumerated values in this format
            are also accepted by the encoder.  
            ASN.1 modules containing 
            <c>ENUMERATED</c> with extensionmark should be 
            recompiled with the corrected
            version of the compiler. The BER runtime functions are also
            corrected.</p>
          <p>Own Id: OTP-2951</p>
          <p>Aux Id: Seq 1446 OTP-2929</p>
        </item>
        <item>
          <p>The compiler does now accept all valid value notations
            for the OBJECT IDENTIFIER type. The generated code for
            those values is also corrected.</p>
          <p>Own Id: OTP-3059</p>
        </item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Improvements and new features</title>
      <list type="bulleted">
        <item>
          <p>The code generated for BER is significantly enhanced resulting
            in less code and around 300% better performance in runtime 
            for the encoding of complex ASN.1 values. The performance of
            decoding is unchanged.</p>
          <p>Own Id: OTP-2806</p>
        </item>
      </list>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Asn1 1.0.3</title>

    <section>
      <title>Fixed errors and malfunctions</title>
      <list type="bulleted">
        <item>
          <p>The <c>asn1.app</c> file is corrected.</p>
          <p>Own Id: OTP-2640</p>
        </item>
        <item>
          <p>The encoding of integers in BER did not comply with the
            standard for all values. The values was not encoded
            in the minimum number of octets as required. This is
            now corrected in the runtime module <c>asn1rt_ber</c>.</p>
          <p>Own Id: OTP-2666</p>
        </item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Improvements and new features</title>
      <list type="bulleted">
        <item>
          <p>The compiler now generates explicit exports directives for 
            all generated
            functions that should be exported (instead of -compile(export_all)). 
            This eliminates the warnings from the Erlang compiler when 
            compiling the 
            generated file.</p>
          <p>Own Id: OTP-1845</p>
        </item>
      </list>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>R3B02 (Asn1 1.0.2)</title>

    <section>
      <title>Fixed errors and malfunctions</title>
      <list type="bulleted">
        <item>
          <p>The decoding of a BER encoded SEQUENCE with optional component
            of type SEQUENCE (also with optional components) could result 
            in an error or wrong result if the tags are equal.</p>
          <p>Own Id: OTP-2226</p>
        </item>
        <item>
          <p>The encoding of (PER) SEQUENCE with extensionmark was wrong.
            This is now corrected.</p>
          <p>Own Id: OTP-2349</p>
        </item>
      </list>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>R3A (Asn1 0.9)</title>

    <section>
      <title>Fixed errors and malfunctions</title>
      <list type="bulleted">
        <item>
          <p>The asn1 compiler now detects the use of an implicit tag before <c>CHOICE</c> as an error (in accordance with the standard)</p>
          <p>Own Id: OTP-1844</p>
        </item>
        <item>
          <p>An OPTIONAL CHOICE embedded in SEQUENCE when BER coding
            caused an error when generating decode code. This is now
            corrected.</p>
          <p>Own Id: OTP-1857</p>
          <p>Aux Id: OTP-1848</p>
        </item>
      </list>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>1 ASN1 0.8.1</title>
    <p>This is the first release of the ASN1 application. This version is
      released for beta-testing. Some functionality will be added until the
      1.0 version is released. See the release notes for the latest version
      for the exact details about new features. A list of missing features
      and restrictions can be found in the chapter below.</p>

    <section>
      <title>1.1 Missing features and other restrictions</title>
      <p></p>
      <list type="bulleted">
        <item>
          <p>The encoding rules BER and PER (aligned) is supported. <em>PER (unaligned)  IS NOT SUPPORTED</em>.</p>
        </item>
        <item>
          <p>NOT SUPPORTED types <c>ANY</c> and <c>ANY DEFINED BY</c> 
            (is not in the standard any more).</p>
        </item>
        <item>
          <p>NOT SUPPORTED types <c>EXTERNAL</c> and <c>EMBEDDED-PDV</c>. </p>
        </item>
        <item>
          <p>NOT SUPPORTED type <c>REAL</c> (planned to be implemented). </p>
        </item>
        <item>
          <p>The code generation support for value definitions in the ASN.1 notation is very limited
            (planned to be enhanced).</p>
        </item>
        <item>
          <p>The support for constraints is limited to:</p>
        </item>
      </list>
      <list type="bulleted">
        <item>
          <p>SizeConstraint  SIZE(X)</p>
        </item>
        <item>
          <p>SingleValue     (1)</p>
        </item>
        <item>
          <p>ValueRange      (X..Y)</p>
        </item>
        <item>
          <p>PermittedAlpabet FROM (but not for BMPString and UniversalString when generating PER).</p>
        </item>
        <item>
          <p>Complex expressions in constraints is not supported (planned to be extended).</p>
        </item>
        <item>
          <p>The current version of the compiler has very limited error checking:</p>
        </item>
        <item>
          <p>Stops at first syntax error.</p>
        </item>
        <item>
          <p>Does not stop when a reference to an undefined type is found , 
            but prints an error message. Compilation of the generated 
            Erlang module will then fail.</p>
        </item>
        <item>
          <p>A whole number of other semantical controls is currently
            missing. This means that the compiler will give little
            or bad help to detect what's wrong with an ASN.1
            specification, but will mostly work very well when the
            ASN.1 specification is correct.</p>
        </item>
      </list>
      <list type="bulleted">
        <item>
          <p>The maximum INTEGER supported in this version is a
            signed 64 bit integer. This limitation is probably quite
            reasonable. (Planned to be extended).</p>
        </item>
        <item>
          <p>Only AUTOMATIC TAGS supported for PER.</p>
        </item>
        <item>
          <p>Only EXPLICIT and IMPLICIT TAGS supported for BER.</p>
        </item>
        <item>
          <p>The compiler supports decoding of BER-data with indefinite
            length but it is not possible to produce data with indefinite
            length with the encoder.</p>
        </item>
      </list>
    </section>
  </section>
</chapter>

