<?xml version="1.0" encoding="latin1" ?>
<!DOCTYPE appref SYSTEM "appref.dtd">

<appref>
  <header>
    <copyright>
      <year>1999</year>
      <year>2011</year>
      <holder>Ericsson AB, All Rights Reserved</holder>
    </copyright>
    <legalnotice>
  The contents of this file are subject to the Erlang Public License,
  Version 1.1, (the "License"); you may not use this file except in
  compliance with the License. You should have received a copy of the
  Erlang Public License along with this software. If not, it can be
  retrieved online at http://www.erlang.org/.

  Software distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS"
  basis, WITHOUT WARRANTY OF ANY KIND, either express or implied. See
  the License for the specific language governing rights and limitations
  under the License.

  The Initial Developer of the Original Code is Ericsson AB.
    </legalnotice>

    <title>crypto</title>
    <prepared>Peter H&ouml;gfeldt</prepared>
    <responsible>Peter H&ouml;gfeldt</responsible>
    <docno></docno>
    <approved>Peter H&ouml;gfeldt</approved>
    <checked>Peter H&ouml;gfeldt</checked>
    <date>2003-06-01</date>
    <rev>B</rev>
    <file>crypto_app.sgml</file>
  </header>
  <app>crypto</app>
  <appsummary>The Crypto Application</appsummary>
  <description>
    <p>The purpose of the Crypto application is to provide message
      digest and DES encryption for SMNPv3. It provides computation of
      message digests MD5 and SHA, and CBC-DES encryption and
      decryption.</p>
    <p></p>
  </description>

  <section>
    <title>Configuration</title>
    <p>The following environment configuration parameters are defined
      for the Crypto application. Refer to application(3) for more
      information about configuration parameters.
      </p>
    <taglist>
      <tag><c><![CDATA[debug = true | false <optional>]]></c></tag>
      <item>
        <p>Causes debug information to be written to standard
          error or standard output. Default is <c>false</c>.
          </p>
      </item>
    </taglist>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>OpenSSL libraries</title>
    <p>The current implementation of the Erlang Crypto application is
      based on the <em>OpenSSL</em> package version 0.9.7 or higher.
      There are source and binary releases on the web.
      </p>
    <p>Source releases of OpenSSL can be downloaded from the <url href="http://www.openssl.org">OpenSSL</url> project home page,
      or mirror sites listed there.
      </p>
    <p>The same URL also contains links to some compiled binaries and
      libraries of OpenSSL (see the <c>Related/Binaries</c> menu) of
      which the <url href="http://www.shininglightpro.com/search.php?searchname=Win32+OpenSSL">Shining Light Productions Win32 and OpenSSL</url> pages are of
      interest for the Win32 user.
      </p>
    <p>For some Unix flavours there are binary packages available
      on the net.
      </p>
    <p>If you cannot find a suitable binary OpenSSL package, you
      have to fetch an OpenSSL source release and compile it.
      </p>
    <p>You then have to compile and install the library
      <c>libcrypto.so</c> (Unix), or the library <c>libeay32.dll</c>
      (Win32).
      </p>
    <p>For Unix The <c>crypto_drv</c> dynamic driver is delivered linked
      to OpenSSL libraries in <c>/usr/local/lib</c>, but the default
      dynamic linking will also accept libraries in <c>/lib</c> and
      <c>/usr/lib</c>.
      </p>
    <p>If that is not applicable to the particular Unix operating
      system used, the example <c>Makefile</c> in the Crypto
      <c>priv/obj</c> directory, should be used as a basis for 
      relinking the final version of the port program.
      </p>
    <p>For <c>Win32</c> it is only required that the library can be
      found from the <c>PATH</c> environment variable, or that they
      reside in the appropriate <c>SYSTEM32</c> directory; hence no
      particular relinking is need. Hence no example <c>Makefile</c>
      for Win32 is provided.</p>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>SEE ALSO</title>
    <p>application(3)</p>
  </section>
</appref>

