<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1" ?>
<!DOCTYPE appref SYSTEM "appref.dtd">

<appref>
  <header>
    <copyright>
      <year>1999</year>
      <year>2013</year>
      <holder>Ericsson AB, All Rights Reserved</holder>
    </copyright>
    <legalnotice>
  The contents of this file are subject to the Erlang Public License,
  Version 1.1, (the "License"); you may not use this file except in
  compliance with the License. You should have received a copy of the
  Erlang Public License along with this software. If not, it can be
  retrieved online at http://www.erlang.org/.

  Software distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS"
  basis, WITHOUT WARRANTY OF ANY KIND, either express or implied. See
  the License for the specific language governing rights and limitations
  under the License.

  The Initial Developer of the Original Code is Ericsson AB.
    </legalnotice>

    <title>crypto</title>
    <file>crypto_app.sgml</file>
  </header>
  <app>crypto</app>
  <appsummary>The Crypto Application</appsummary>
  <description>
    <p>The purpose of the Crypto application is to provide erlang
    acess to crypto graphic functions in openssl.
    </p>
  </description>

  <section>
    <title>Configuration</title>
    <p>The following environment configuration parameters are defined
      for the Crypto application. Refer to application(3) for more
      information about configuration parameters.
      </p>
    <taglist>
      <tag><c><![CDATA[debug = true | false <optional>]]></c></tag>
      <item>
        <p>Causes debug information to be written to standard
          error or standard output. Default is <c>false</c>.
          </p>
      </item>
    </taglist>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>OpenSSL libraries</title>
    <p>The current implementation of the Erlang Crypto application is
      based on the <em>OpenSSL</em> package version 0.9.8 or higher.
      There are source and binary releases on the web.
      </p>
    <p>Source releases of OpenSSL can be downloaded from the <url href="http://www.openssl.org">OpenSSL</url> project home page,
      or mirror sites listed there.
      </p>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>SEE ALSO</title>
    <p>application(3)</p>
  </section>
</appref>

