<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter SYSTEM "chapter.dtd">

<chapter>
  <header>
    <copyright>
      <year>2000</year><year>2016</year>
      <holder>Ericsson AB. All Rights Reserved.</holder>
    </copyright>
    <legalnotice>
      Licensed under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the "License");
      you may not use this file except in compliance with the License.
      You may obtain a copy of the License at
 
          http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0

      Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
      distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,
      WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
      See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
      limitations under the License.

    </legalnotice>

    <title>Running the stack</title>
    <prepared>H&aring;kan Mattsson</prepared>
    <responsible>H&aring;kan Mattsson</responsible>
    <docno></docno>
    <approved>H&aring;kan Mattsson</approved>
    <checked></checked>
    <date>2007-06-15</date>
    <rev>%VSN%</rev>
    <file>megaco_run.xml</file>
  </header>

  <section>
    <marker id="starting"></marker>
    <title>Starting</title>
    <p>A user may have a number of "virtual" connections to other
      users. An MG is connected to at most one MGC, while an MGC may
      be connected to any number of MG's. For each connection the user
      selects a transport service, an encoding scheme and a user
      callback module.</p>
    <p>An MGC must initiate its transport service in order to listen
      to MG's trying to connect. How the actual transport is initiated
      is outside the scope of this application. However a send handle
      (typically a socket id or host and port) must be provided from
      the transport service in order to enable us to send the message
      to the correct destination. We do however not assume anything
      about this, from our point of view, opaque handle. Hopefully it
      is rather small since it will passed around the system between
      processes rather frequently.</p>
    <p>A user may either be statically configured in a .config file
      according to the application concept of Erlang/OTP or
      dynamically started with the configuration settings as arguments
      to megaco:start_user/2. These configuration settings may be
      updated later on with megaco:update_conn_info/2.</p>
    <p>The function megaco:connect/4 is used to tell the Megaco
      application about which control process it should supervise,
      which MID the remote user has, which callback module it should
      use to send messages etc. When this "virtual" connection is
      established the user may use megaco:call/3 and megaco:cast/3 in
      order to send messages to the other side. Then it is up to the
      MG to send its first Service Change Request message after
      applying some clever algorithm in order to fight the problem
      with startup avalanche (as discussed in the RFC).</p>
    <p>The originating user will wait for a reply or a timeout
      (defined by the request_timer). When it receives the reply this
      will optionally be acknowledged (regulated by auto_ack), and
      forwarded to the user.  If an interim pending reply is received,
      the long_request_timer will be used instead of the usual
      request_timer, in order to enable avoidance of spurious re-sends
      of the request.</p>
    <p>On the destination side the transport service waits for
      messages. Each message is forwarded to the Megaco application
      via the megaco:receive_message/4 callback function. The
      transport service may or may not provide means for blocking and
      unblocking the reception of the incoming messages.</p>
    <p></p>
    <p>If a message is received before the "virtual" connection has
      been established, the connection will be setup automatically. An
      MGC may be real open minded and dynamically decide which
      encoding and transport service to use depending on how the
      transport layer contact is performed. For IP transports two
      ports are standardized, one for textual encoding and one for
      binary encoding. If for example an UDP packet was received on
      the text port it would be possible to decide encoding and
      transport on the fly.</p>
    <p>After decoding a message various user callback functions are
      invoked in order to allow the user to act properly.  See the
      megaco_user module for more info about the callback
      arguments.</p>
    <p>When the user has processed a transaction request in its
      callback function, the Megaco application assembles a
      transaction reply, encodes it using the selected encoding module
      and sends the message back by invoking the callback
      function:</p>
    <list type="bulleted">
      <item>
        <p>SendMod:send_message(SendHandle, ErlangBinary)</p>
      </item>
    </list>
    <p>Re-send of messages, handling pending transactions,
      acknowledgements etc. is handled automatically by the Megaco
      application but the user is free to override the default
      behaviour by the various configuration possibilities. See
      megaco:update_user_info/2 and megaco:update_conn_info/2 about
      the possibilities.</p>
    <p>When connections gets broken (that is explicitly by
      megaco:disconnect/2 or when its controlling process dies) a user
      callback function is invoked in order to allow the user to
      re-establish the connection. The internal state of kept
      messages, re-send timers etc. is not affected by this. A few
      re-sends will of course fail while the connection is down, but
      the automatic re-send algorithm does not bother about this and
      eventually when the connection is up and running the messages
      will be delivered if the timeouts are set to be long enough. The
      user has the option of explicitly invoking megaco:cancel/2 to
      cancel all messages for a connection.</p>
  </section>

  <section>
    <marker id="mgc_startup_call_flow"></marker>
    <title>MGC startup call flow</title>
    <p>In order to prepare the MGC for the reception of the initial
      message, hopefully a Service Change Request, the following needs
      to be done:</p>
    <list type="bulleted">
      <item>
        <p>Start the Megaco application.</p>
      </item>
      <item>
        <p>Start the MGC user. This may either be done explicitly
          with megaco:start_user/2 or implicitly by providing the -megaco
          users configuration parameter.</p>
      </item>
      <item>
        <p>Initiate the transport service and provide it with a
          receive handle obtained from megaco:user_info/2.</p>
      </item>
    </list>
    <p>When the initial message arrives the transport service
      forwards it to the protocol engine which automatically
      sets up the connection and invokes UserMod:handle_connect/2
      before it invokes UserMod:handle_trans_request/3 with
      the Service Change Request like this:</p>
    <image file="MGC_startup_call_flow.gif">
      <icaption>MGC Startup Call Flow</icaption>
    </image>
  </section>

  <section>
    <marker id="mg_startup_call_flow"></marker>
    <title>MG startup call flow</title>
    <p>In order to prepare the MG for the sending of the initial
      message, hopefully a Service Change Request, the following needs
      to be done:</p>
    <list type="bulleted">
      <item>
        <p>Start the Megaco application.</p>
      </item>
      <item>
        <p>Start the MG user. This may either be done explicitly
          with megaco:start_user/2 or implicitly by providing the -megaco
          users configuration parameter.</p>
      </item>
      <item>
        <p>Initiate the transport service and provide it with a
          receive handle obtained from megaco:user_info/2.</p>
      </item>
      <item>
        <p>Setup a connection to the MGC with megaco:connect/4 and
          provide it with a receive handle obtained from
          megaco:user_info/2.</p>
      </item>
    </list>
    <p>If the MG has been provisioned with the MID of the MGC it can
      be given as the RemoteMid parameter to megaco:connect/4 and the
      call flow will look like this:</p>
    <image file="MG_startup_call_flow.gif">
      <icaption>MG Startup Call Flow</icaption>
    </image>
    <p>If the MG cannot be provisioned with the MID of the MGC, the
      MG can use the atom 'preliminary_mid' as the RemoteMid parameter
      to megaco:connect/4 and the call flow will look like this:</p>
    <image file="MG-startup_flow_noMID.gif">
      <icaption>MG Startup Call Flow (no MID)</icaption>
    </image>
  </section>

  <section>
    <marker id="config_megaco"></marker>
    <title>Configuring the Megaco stack</title>
    <p>There are three kinds of configuration:</p>
    <list type="bulleted">
      <item>
        <p>User info - Information related to megaco users. Read/Write. </p>
        <p>A User is an entity identified by a MID, e.g. a MGC or a MG. </p>
        <p>This information can be retrieved using 
          <seealso marker="megaco#user_info">megaco:user_info</seealso>. </p>
      </item>
      <item>
        <p>Connection info - Information regarding connections. Read/Write.</p>
        <p>This information can be retrieved using 
          <seealso marker="megaco#conn_info">megaco:conn_info</seealso>. </p>
      </item>
      <item>
        <p>System info - System wide information. Read only.</p>
        <p>This information can be retrieved using 
          <seealso marker="megaco#system_info">megaco:system_info</seealso>. </p>
      </item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section>
    <marker id="initial_config"></marker>
    <title>Initial configuration</title>
    <p>The initial configuration of the Megaco should be defined in the
      Erlang system configuration file. The following configured parameters
      are defined for the Megaco application:</p>
    <list type="bulleted">
      <item>
        <p><c><![CDATA[users = [{Mid, [user_config()]}].]]></c></p>
        <p>Each user is represented by a tuple with the Mid of the user and a
          list of config parameters (each parameter is in turn a tuple:
          <c><![CDATA[{Item, Value}]]></c>).</p>
      </item>
      <item>
        <p><c><![CDATA[scanner = flex | {Module, Function, Arguments, Modules}]]></c></p>
<!--
  For future use
        <p><c><![CDATA[scanner = flex | {flex, Opts} | {Module, Function, Arguments, Modules}]]></c></p>
-->
        <list type="bulleted">
          <item>
            <p><c><![CDATA[flex]]></c> will result in the start of the flex scanner with default 
              options.</p>
          </item>
<!--
  For future use
          <item>
            <p><c><![CDATA[{flex, Opts}]]></c> will result in the start of the flex scanner with the 
              specified options. <c>Opts</c> is two-tuple list where the only allowed option is
              <c>{smp, boolean()}</c>, with default value being <c>false</c> and the value of 
              <c>true</c> resulting in a start of an smp-optimized scanner. </p>
          </item>
-->
          <item>
            <p>The MFA alternative makes it possible for Megaco to start and
              supervise a scanner written by the user (see 
            <c><![CDATA[supervisor:start_child]]></c> for an explanation of the 
              parameters).</p>
          </item>
        </list>
      </item>
    </list>
    <p>See also <seealso marker="megaco_encode#text_config">Configuration of text encoding module(s)</seealso> 
      for more info. </p>
  </section>

  <section>
    <marker id="changing_config"></marker>
    <title>Changing the configuration</title>
    <p>The configuration can be changed during runtime. This is done with
      the functions <seealso marker="megaco#update_user_info">megaco:update_user_info</seealso> and 
      <seealso marker="megaco#update_conn_info">megaco:update_conn_info</seealso></p>
  </section>

  <section>
    <marker id="transaction_sender"></marker>
    <title>The transaction sender</title>
    <p>The transaction sender is a process (one per connection), which handle
      all transaction sending, if so configured (see 
      <seealso marker="megaco#user_info">megaco:user_info</seealso> and 
      <seealso marker="megaco#conn_info">megaco:conn_info</seealso>).</p>
    <p>The purpose of the transaction sender is to accumulate transactions 
      for a more efficient message sending. The transactions that are 
      accumulated are transaction request and transaction ack. For 
      transaction ack's the benefit is quite large, since the transactions 
      are small and it is possible to have ranges (which means that 
      transaction acks for transactions 1, 2, 3 and 4 can be sent as a 
      range 1-4 in one transaction ack, instead of four separate 
      transactions). </p>
    <p>There are a number of configuration parameter's that control the 
      operation of the transaction sender. In principle, a message with 
      everything stored (ack's and request's) is sent from the process 
      when:</p>
    <list type="bulleted">
      <item>
        <p>When <c><![CDATA[trans_timer]]></c> expires.</p>
      </item>
      <item>
        <p>When <c><![CDATA[trans_ack_maxcount]]></c> number of ack's has been 
          received.</p>
      </item>
      <item>
        <p>When <c><![CDATA[trans_req_maxcount]]></c> number of requests's has 
          been received.</p>
      </item>
      <item>
        <p>When the size of all received requests exceeds 
          <c><![CDATA[trans_req_maxsize]]></c>.</p>
      </item>
      <item>
        <p>When a reply transaction is sent.</p>
      </item>
      <item>
        <p>When a pending transaction is sent.</p>
      </item>
    </list>
    <p>When something is to be sent, everything is packed into one message,  
      unless the trigger was a reply transaction and the added size of the 
      reply and all the requests is greater then 
      <c><![CDATA[trans_req_maxsize]]></c>, in which case the stored 
      transactions are sent first in a separate message and the reply in 
      another message.</p>
    <p>When the transaction sender receives a request which is already 
      "in storage" (indicated by the transaction id) it is assumed to 
      be a resend and everything stored is sent. This could happen if 
      the values of the <c><![CDATA[trans_timer]]></c> and the
      <c><![CDATA[request_timer]]></c> is not properly chosen.</p>
  </section>

  <section>
    <marker id="segment_reply"></marker>
    <title>Segmentation of transaction replies</title>
    <p>In version 3 of the megaco standard the Segmentation package was
      introduced. Simply, this package defines a procedure to segment 
      megaco messages (transaction replies) when using a transport that 
      does not automatically do this (e.g. UDP). See also
      <seealso marker="megaco_encode#handling_versions">version3</seealso>.</p>
    <p>Although it would be both pointless and counterproductive to use
      segmentation on a transport that already does this (e.g. TCP), the 
      megaco application does not check this. Instead, it is up to the 
      user to configure this properly. </p>
    <list type="bulleted">
      <item>
        <p>Receiving segmented messages: </p>
        <p>This is handled automatically by the megaco application. 
          There is however one thing that need to be configured by the user, 
          the 
          <seealso marker="megaco#user_info">segment_recv_timer</seealso>
          option. </p>
        <p>Note that the segments are delivered to the user differently 
          depending on which function is used to issue the original request.
          When issuing the request using the 
          <seealso marker="megaco#cast">megaco:cast</seealso> function,
          the segments are delivered to the user via the 
          <seealso marker="megaco_user#trans_reply">handle_trans_reply</seealso>
          callback function one at a time, as they arrive. But this obviously
          doe not work for the 
          <seealso marker="megaco#call">megaco:call</seealso> function. 
          In this case, the segments are accumulated and then delivered
          all at once as the function returns.</p>
      </item>
      <item>
        <p>Sending segmented messages: </p>
        <p>This is also handled automatically by the megaco application. 
          First of all, segmentation is only attempted if so configured, see 
          the <seealso marker="megaco#user_info">segment_send</seealso> option.
          Secondly, megaco relies on the ability of the used codec to
          encode action replies, which is the smallest component the
          megaco application handles when segmenting. Thirdly, the 
          reply will be segmented only if the sum of the size of the
          action replies (plus an arbitrary message header size) are greater
          then the specified max message size (see the 
          <seealso marker="megaco#user_info">max_pdu_size</seealso> option).
          Finally, if segmentation is decided, then each action reply
          will make up its own (segment) message.</p>
      </item>
    </list>
  </section>
</chapter>

