<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter SYSTEM "chapter.dtd">

<chapter>
  <header>
    <copyright>
      <year>2003</year><year>2016</year>
      <holder>Ericsson AB. All Rights Reserved.</holder>
    </copyright>
    <legalnotice>
      Licensed under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the "License");
      you may not use this file except in compliance with the License.
      You may obtain a copy of the License at
 
          http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0

      Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
      distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,
      WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
      See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
      limitations under the License.
    
    </legalnotice>

    <title>Concurrent Programming</title>
    <prepared></prepared>
    <docno></docno>
    <date></date>
    <rev></rev>
    <file>conc_prog.xml</file>
  </header>

  <marker id="Distributed Programming"></marker>
  <section>
    <title>Processes</title>
    <p>One of the main reasons for using Erlang instead of other
      functional languages is Erlang's ability to handle concurrency
      and distributed programming. By concurrency is meant programs
      that can handle several threads of execution at the same time.
      For example, modern operating systems allow you to use a
      word processor, a spreadsheet, a mail client, and a print job all
      running at the same time. Each processor (CPU) in
      the system is probably only handling one thread (or job) at a
      time, but it swaps between the jobs at such a rate that it gives
      the illusion of running them all at the same time. It is easy to
      create parallel threads of execution in an Erlang program and
      to allow these threads to communicate with each other. In
      Erlang, each thread of execution is called a <em>process</em>.</p>
    <p>(Aside: the term "process" is usually used when the threads of
      execution share no data with each other and the term "thread"
      when they share data in some way. Threads of execution in Erlang
      share no data, that is why they are called processes).</p>
    <p>The Erlang BIF <c>spawn</c> is used to create a new process:
      <c>spawn(Module, Exported_Function, List of Arguments)</c>.
      Consider the following module:</p>
    <code type="none">
-module(tut14).

-export([start/0, say_something/2]).

say_something(What, 0) ->
    done;
say_something(What, Times) ->
    io:format("~p~n", [What]),
    say_something(What, Times - 1).

start() ->
    spawn(tut14, say_something, [hello, 3]),
    spawn(tut14, say_something, [goodbye, 3]).</code>
    <pre>
5> <input>c(tut14).</input>
{ok,tut14}
6> <input>tut14:say_something(hello, 3).</input>
hello
hello
hello
done</pre>
    <p>As shown, the function <c>say_something</c> writes its first
      argument the number of times specified by second argument.
      The function <c>start</c> starts two Erlang processes,
      one that writes "hello" three times and one that writes
      "goodbye" three times. Both processes use the function
      <c>say_something</c>. Notice that a function used in this way by
      <c>spawn</c>, to start a process, must be exported from the module
      (that is, in the <c>-export</c> at the start of the module).</p>
    <pre>
9> <input>tut14:start().</input>
hello
goodbye
&lt;0.63.0>
hello
goodbye
hello
goodbye</pre>
    <p>Notice that it did not write "hello" three times and then
      "goodbye" three times. Instead, the first process wrote a "hello",
      the second a "goodbye", the first another "hello" and so forth.
      But where did the &lt;0.63.0&gt; come from? The return value of a
      function is the return value of the last "thing" in
      the function. The last thing in the function <c>start</c> is</p>
    <code type="none">
spawn(tut14, say_something, [goodbye, 3]).</code>
    <p><c>spawn</c> returns a <em>process identifier</em>, or
      <em>pid</em>, which uniquely identifies the process. So &lt;0.63.0&gt;
      is the pid of the <c>spawn</c> function call above.
      The next example shows how to use pids.</p>
    <p>Notice also that ~p is used instead of ~w in
      <c>io:format</c>. To quote the manual: "~p Writes the data with
      standard syntax in the same way as ~w, but breaks terms whose
      printed representation is longer than one line into many lines
      and indents each line sensibly. It also tries to detect lists of
      printable characters and to output these as strings".</p>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Message Passing</title>
    <p>In the following example two processes are created and
    they send messages to each other a number of times.</p>
    <code type="none">
-module(tut15).

-export([start/0, ping/2, pong/0]).

ping(0, Pong_PID) ->
    Pong_PID ! finished,
    io:format("ping finished~n", []);

ping(N, Pong_PID) ->
    Pong_PID ! {ping, self()},
    receive
        pong ->
            io:format("Ping received pong~n", [])
    end,
    ping(N - 1, Pong_PID).

pong() ->
    receive
        finished ->
            io:format("Pong finished~n", []);
        {ping, Ping_PID} ->
            io:format("Pong received ping~n", []),
            Ping_PID ! pong,
            pong()
    end.

start() ->
    Pong_PID = spawn(tut15, pong, []),
    spawn(tut15, ping, [3, Pong_PID]).</code>
    <pre>
1> <input>c(tut15).</input>
{ok,tut15}
2> <input>tut15: start().</input>
&lt;0.36.0>
Pong received ping
Ping received pong
Pong received ping
Ping received pong
Pong received ping
Ping received pong
ping finished
Pong finished</pre>
    <p>The function <c>start</c> first creates a process,
      let us call it "pong":</p>
    <code type="none">
Pong_PID = spawn(tut15, pong, [])</code>
    <p>This process executes <c>tut15:pong()</c>. <c>Pong_PID</c> is
      the process identity of the "pong" process. The function
      <c>start</c> now creates another process "ping":</p>
    <code type="none">
spawn(tut15, ping, [3, Pong_PID]),</code>
    <p>This process executes:</p>
    <code type="none">
tut15:ping(3, Pong_PID)</code>
    <p>&lt;0.36.0&gt; is the return value from the <c>start</c> function.</p>
    <p>The process "pong" now does:</p>
    <code type="none">
receive
    finished ->
        io:format("Pong finished~n", []);
    {ping, Ping_PID} ->
        io:format("Pong received ping~n", []),
        Ping_PID ! pong,
        pong()
end.</code>
    <p>The <c>receive</c> construct is used to allow processes to wait
      for messages from other processes. It has the following format:</p>
    <code type="none">
receive
   pattern1 ->
       actions1;
   pattern2 ->
       actions2;
   ....
   patternN
       actionsN
end.</code>
    <p>Notice there is no ";" before the <c>end</c>.</p>
    <p>Messages between Erlang processes are simply valid Erlang terms.
      That is, they can be lists, tuples, integers, atoms, pids,
      and so on.</p>
    <p>Each process has its own input queue for messages it receives.
      New messages received are put at the end of the queue. When a
      process executes a <c>receive</c>, the first message in the queue
      is matched against the first pattern in the <c>receive</c>. If
      this matches, the message is removed from the queue and
      the actions corresponding to the pattern are executed.</p>
    <p>However, if the first pattern does not match, the second pattern
      is tested. If this matches, the message is removed from the queue
      and the actions corresponding to the second pattern are executed.
      If the second pattern does not match, the third is tried and so on
      until there are no more patterns to test. If there are no more
      patterns to test, the first message is kept in the queue and
      the second message is tried instead. If this matches any pattern,
      the appropriate actions are executed and the second message is
      removed from the queue (keeping the first message and any other
      messages in the queue). If the second message does not match,
      the third message is tried, and so on, until the end of
      the queue is reached. If the end of the queue is reached,
      the process blocks
      (stops execution) and waits until a new message is received and
      this procedure is repeated.</p>
    <p>The Erlang implementation is "clever" and minimizes
      the number of times each message is tested against the patterns
      in each <c>receive</c>.</p>
    <p>Now back to the ping pong example.</p>
    <p>"Pong" is waiting for messages. If the atom <c>finished</c> is
      received, "pong" writes "Pong finished" to the output and, as it
      has nothing more to do, terminates. If it receives a message with
      the format:</p>
    <code type="none">
{ping, Ping_PID}</code>
    <p>it writes "Pong received ping" to the output and sends the atom
      <c>pong</c> to the process "ping":</p>
    <code type="none">
Ping_PID ! pong</code>
    <p>Notice how the operator "!" is used to send messages. The syntax
      of "!" is:</p>
    <code type="none">
Pid ! Message</code>
    <p>That is, <c>Message</c> (any Erlang term) is sent to the process
      with identity <c>Pid</c>.</p>
    <p>After sending the message <c>pong</c> to the process "ping",
      "pong" calls the <c>pong</c> function again, which causes it to
      get back to the <c>receive</c> again and wait for another message.</p>
     <p>Now let us look at the process "ping". Recall that it was started
      by executing:</p>
    <code type="none">
tut15:ping(3, Pong_PID)</code>
    <p>Looking at the function <c>ping/2</c>, the second
      clause of <c>ping/2</c> is executed since the value of the first
      argument is 3 (not 0) (first clause head is
      <c>ping(0,Pong_PID)</c>, second clause head is
      <c>ping(N,Pong_PID)</c>, so <c>N</c> becomes 3).</p>
    <p>The second clause sends a message to "pong":</p>
    <code type="none">
Pong_PID ! {ping, self()},</code>
    <p><c>self()</c> returns the pid of the process that executes
      <c>self()</c>, in this case the pid of "ping". (Recall the code
      for "pong", this lands up in the variable <c>Ping_PID</c> in
      the <c>receive</c> previously explained.)</p>
    <p>"Ping" now waits for a reply from "pong":</p>
    <code type="none">
receive
    pong ->
        io:format("Ping received pong~n", [])
end,</code>
    <p>It writes "Ping received pong" when this reply arrives, after
      which "ping" calls the <c>ping</c> function again.</p>
    <code type="none">
ping(N - 1, Pong_PID)</code>
    <p><c>N-1</c> causes the first argument to be decremented until it
      becomes 0. When this occurs, the first clause of <c>ping/2</c>
      is executed:</p>
    <code type="none">
ping(0, Pong_PID) ->
    Pong_PID !  finished,
    io:format("ping finished~n", []);</code>
    <p>The atom <c>finished</c> is sent to "pong" (causing it to
      terminate as described above) and "ping finished" is written to
      the output. "Ping" then terminates as it has nothing left
      to do.</p>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Registered Process Names</title>
    <p>In the above example, "pong" was first created to be able
      to give the identity of "pong" when "ping" was started. That is, in
      some way "ping" must be able to know the identity of "pong" to be
      able to send a message to it. Sometimes processes
      which need to know each other's identities are started
      independently of each other. Erlang thus provides a mechanism for
      processes to be given names so that these names can be used as
      identities instead of pids. This is done by using
      the <c>register</c> BIF:</p>
    <code type="none">
register(some_atom, Pid)</code>
    <p>Let us now rewrite the ping pong example using this and give
      the name <c>pong</c> to the "pong" process:</p>
    <code type="none">
-module(tut16).

-export([start/0, ping/1, pong/0]).

ping(0) ->
    pong ! finished,
    io:format("ping finished~n", []);

ping(N) ->
    pong ! {ping, self()},
    receive
        pong ->
            io:format("Ping received pong~n", [])
    end,
    ping(N - 1).

pong() ->
    receive
        finished ->
            io:format("Pong finished~n", []);
        {ping, Ping_PID} ->
            io:format("Pong received ping~n", []),
            Ping_PID ! pong,
            pong()
    end.

start() ->
    register(pong, spawn(tut16, pong, [])),
    spawn(tut16, ping, [3]).</code>
    <pre>
2> <input>c(tut16).</input>
{ok, tut16}
3> <input>tut16:start().</input>
&lt;0.38.0>
Pong received ping
Ping received pong
Pong received ping
Ping received pong
Pong received ping
Ping received pong
ping finished
Pong finished</pre>
    <p>Here the <c>start/0</c> function,</p>
    <code type="none">
register(pong, spawn(tut16, pong, [])),</code>
    <p>both spawns the "pong" process and gives it the name <c>pong</c>.
      In the "ping" process, messages can be sent to <c>pong</c> by:</p>
    <code type="none">
pong ! {ping, self()},</code>
    <p><c>ping/2</c> now becomes <c>ping/1</c> as
      the argument <c>Pong_PID</c> is not needed.</p>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Distributed Programming</title>
    <p>Let us rewrite the ping pong program with "ping" and "pong"
      on different computers. First a few things
      are needed to set up to get this to work. The distributed Erlang
      implementation provides a basic security mechanism to prevent
      unauthorized access to an Erlang system on another computer.
      Erlang systems which talk to each other must have
      the same <em>magic cookie</em>. The easiest way to achieve this
      is by having a file called <c>.erlang.cookie</c> in your home
      directory on all machines on which you are going to run
      Erlang systems communicating with each other:
     </p>
      <list type="bulleted">
	<item>On Windows systems the home directory is the directory
	pointed out by the environment variable $HOME - you may need
        to set this.</item>
        <item> On Linux or UNIX
        you can safely ignore this and simply create a file called
        <c>.erlang.cookie</c> in the directory you get to after executing
        the command <c>cd</c> without any argument.</item>
      </list>
      <p>The <c>.erlang.cookie</c> file is to contain a line with
      the same atom. For example, on Linux or UNIX, in the OS shell:</p>
    <pre>
$ <input>cd</input>
$ <input>cat > .erlang.cookie</input>
this_is_very_secret
$ <input>chmod 400 .erlang.cookie</input></pre>
    <p>The <c>chmod</c> above makes the <c>.erlang.cookie</c> file
      accessible only by the owner of the file. This is a requirement.</p>
    <p>When you start an Erlang system that is going to talk to other
      Erlang systems, you must give it a name, for example:</p>
    <pre>
$ <input>erl -sname my_name</input></pre>
    <p>We will see more details of this later. If you want to
      experiment with distributed Erlang, but you only have one
      computer to work on, you can start two separate Erlang systems on
      the same computer but give them different names. Each Erlang
      system running on a computer is called an <em>Erlang node</em>.</p>
    <p>(Note: <c>erl -sname</c> assumes that all nodes are in the same
      IP domain and we can use only the first component of the IP
      address, if we want to use nodes in different domains we use
      <c>-name</c> instead, but then all IP address must be given in
      full.)</p>
    <p>Here is the ping pong example modified to run on two separate
      nodes:</p>
    <code type="none">
-module(tut17).

-export([start_ping/1, start_pong/0,  ping/2, pong/0]).

ping(0, Pong_Node) ->
    {pong, Pong_Node} ! finished,
    io:format("ping finished~n", []);

ping(N, Pong_Node) ->
    {pong, Pong_Node} ! {ping, self()},
    receive
        pong ->
            io:format("Ping received pong~n", [])
    end,
    ping(N - 1, Pong_Node).

pong() ->
    receive
        finished ->
            io:format("Pong finished~n", []);
        {ping, Ping_PID} ->
            io:format("Pong received ping~n", []),
            Ping_PID ! pong,
            pong()
    end.

start_pong() ->
    register(pong, spawn(tut17, pong, [])).

start_ping(Pong_Node) ->
    spawn(tut17, ping, [3, Pong_Node]).</code>
    <p>Let us assume there are two computers called gollum and kosken.
      First a node is started on kosken, called ping, and then a node on gollum,
      called pong.</p>
    <p>On kosken (on a Linux/UNIX system):</p>
    <pre>
kosken> <input>erl -sname ping</input>
Erlang (BEAM) emulator version 5.2.3.7 [hipe] [threads:0]

Eshell V5.2.3.7  (abort with ^G)
(ping@kosken)1></pre>
    <p>On gollum:</p>
    <pre>
gollum> <input>erl -sname pong</input>
Erlang (BEAM) emulator version 5.2.3.7 [hipe] [threads:0]

Eshell V5.2.3.7  (abort with ^G)
(pong@gollum)1></pre>
    <p>Now the "pong" process on gollum is started:</p>
    <pre>
(pong@gollum)1> <input>tut17:start_pong().</input>
true</pre>
    <p>And the "ping" process on kosken is started (from the code above you
      can see that a parameter of the <c>start_ping</c> function is
      the node name of the Erlang system where "pong" is running):</p>
    <pre>
(ping@kosken)1> <input>tut17:start_ping(pong@gollum).</input>
&lt;0.37.0>
Ping received pong
Ping received pong 
Ping received pong
ping finished</pre>
    <p>As shown, the ping pong program has run. On the "pong" side:</p>
    <pre>
(pong@gollum)2>
Pong received ping                 
Pong received ping                 
Pong received ping                 
Pong finished                      
(pong@gollum)2></pre>
    <p>Looking at the <c>tut17</c> code, you see that the <c>pong</c>
      function itself is unchanged, the following lines work in the same way
      irrespective of on which node the "ping" process is executes:</p>
    <code type="none">
{ping, Ping_PID} ->
    io:format("Pong received ping~n", []),
    Ping_PID ! pong,</code>
    <p>Thus, Erlang pids contain information about
      where the process executes. So if you know the pid of a process,
      the "!" operator can be used to send it a message disregarding
      if the process is on the same node or on a different node.</p>
    <p>A difference is how messages are sent to a registered process on
      another node:</p>
    <code type="none">
{pong, Pong_Node} ! {ping, self()},</code>
    <p>A tuple <c>{registered_name,node_name}</c> is used instead of
      just the <c>registered_name</c>.</p>
    <p>In the previous example, "ping" and "pong" were started from
      the shells of two separate Erlang nodes. <c>spawn</c> can also be
      used to start processes in other nodes.</p>
      <p>The next example is the ping pong program, yet again,
      but this time "ping" is started in another node:</p>
    <code type="none">
-module(tut18).

-export([start/1,  ping/2, pong/0]).

ping(0, Pong_Node) ->
    {pong, Pong_Node} ! finished,
    io:format("ping finished~n", []);

ping(N, Pong_Node) ->
    {pong, Pong_Node} ! {ping, self()},
    receive
        pong ->
            io:format("Ping received pong~n", [])
    end,
    ping(N - 1, Pong_Node).

pong() ->
    receive
        finished ->
            io:format("Pong finished~n", []);
        {ping, Ping_PID} ->
            io:format("Pong received ping~n", []),
            Ping_PID ! pong,
            pong()
    end.

start(Ping_Node) ->
    register(pong, spawn(tut18, pong, [])),
    spawn(Ping_Node, tut18, ping, [3, node()]).</code>
    <p>Assuming an Erlang system called ping (but not the "ping"
      process) has already been started on kosken, then on gollum this is done:</p>
    <pre>
(pong@gollum)1> <input>tut18:start(ping@kosken).</input>
&lt;3934.39.0>
Pong received ping
Ping received pong
Pong received ping
Ping received pong
Pong received ping
Ping received pong
Pong finished
ping finished</pre>
    <p>Notice that all the output is received on gollum. This is because
      the I/O
      system finds out where the process is spawned from and sends all
      output there.</p>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>A Larger Example</title>
    <p>Now for a larger example with a simple
      "messenger". The messenger is a program that allows users to log
      in on different nodes and send simple messages to each other.</p>
    <p>Before starting, notice the following:</p>
    <list type="bulleted">
      <item>
        <p>This example only shows the message passing logic - no
          attempt has been made to provide a nice graphical user
          interface, although this can also be done in Erlang.</p>
      </item>
      <item>
        <p>This sort of problem can be solved easier by use of
          the facilities in OTP, which also provide methods for
          updating code on the fly and so on (see
	  <seealso marker="doc/design_principles:des_princ#otp design principles">
          OTP Design Principles</seealso>).</p>
      </item>
      <item>
        <p>The first program contains some inadequacies
          regarding handling of nodes which disappear.
          These are corrected in a later version of the program.</p>
      </item>
    </list>
    <p>The messenger is set up by allowing "clients" to connect to
      a central server and say who and where they are. That is, a user
      does not need to know the name of the Erlang node where another user
      is located to send a message.</p>
    <p>File <c>messenger.erl</c>:</p>
    <marker id="ex"></marker>
    <code type="none">
%%% Message passing utility.  
%%% User interface:
%%% logon(Name)
%%%     One user at a time can log in from each Erlang node in the
%%%     system messenger: and choose a suitable Name. If the Name
%%%     is already logged in at another node or if someone else is
%%%     already logged in at the same node, login will be rejected
%%%     with a suitable error message.
%%% logoff()
%%%     Logs off anybody at that node
%%% message(ToName, Message)
%%%     sends Message to ToName. Error messages if the user of this 
%%%     function is not logged on or if ToName is not logged on at
%%%     any node.
%%%
%%% One node in the network of Erlang nodes runs a server which maintains
%%% data about the logged on users. The server is registered as "messenger"
%%% Each node where there is a user logged on runs a client process registered
%%% as "mess_client" 
%%%
%%% Protocol between the client processes and the server
%%% ----------------------------------------------------
%%% 
%%% To server: {ClientPid, logon, UserName}
%%% Reply {messenger, stop, user_exists_at_other_node} stops the client
%%% Reply {messenger, logged_on} logon was successful
%%%
%%% To server: {ClientPid, logoff}
%%% Reply: {messenger, logged_off}
%%%
%%% To server: {ClientPid, logoff}
%%% Reply: no reply
%%%
%%% To server: {ClientPid, message_to, ToName, Message} send a message
%%% Reply: {messenger, stop, you_are_not_logged_on} stops the client
%%% Reply: {messenger, receiver_not_found} no user with this name logged on
%%% Reply: {messenger, sent} Message has been sent (but no guarantee)
%%%
%%% To client: {message_from, Name, Message},
%%%
%%% Protocol between the "commands" and the client
%%% ----------------------------------------------
%%%
%%% Started: messenger:client(Server_Node, Name)
%%% To client: logoff
%%% To client: {message_to, ToName, Message}
%%%
%%% Configuration: change the server_node() function to return the
%%% name of the node where the messenger server runs

-module(messenger).
-export([start_server/0, server/1, logon/1, logoff/0, message/2, client/2]).

%%% Change the function below to return the name of the node where the
%%% messenger server runs
server_node() ->
    messenger@bill.

%%% This is the server process for the "messenger"
%%% the user list has the format [{ClientPid1, Name1},{ClientPid22, Name2},...]
server(User_List) ->
    receive
        {From, logon, Name} ->
            New_User_List = server_logon(From, Name, User_List),
            server(New_User_List);
        {From, logoff} ->
            New_User_List = server_logoff(From, User_List),
            server(New_User_List);
        {From, message_to, To, Message} ->
            server_transfer(From, To, Message, User_List),
            io:format("list is now: ~p~n", [User_List]),
            server(User_List)
    end.

%%% Start the server
start_server() ->
    register(messenger, spawn(messenger, server, [[]])).


%%% Server adds a new user to the user list
server_logon(From, Name, User_List) ->
    %% check if logged on anywhere else
    case lists:keymember(Name, 2, User_List) of
        true ->
            From ! {messenger, stop, user_exists_at_other_node},  %reject logon
            User_List;
        false ->
            From ! {messenger, logged_on},
            [{From, Name} | User_List]        %add user to the list
    end.

%%% Server deletes a user from the user list
server_logoff(From, User_List) ->
    lists:keydelete(From, 1, User_List).


%%% Server transfers a message between user
server_transfer(From, To, Message, User_List) ->
    %% check that the user is logged on and who he is
    case lists:keysearch(From, 1, User_List) of
        false ->
            From ! {messenger, stop, you_are_not_logged_on};
        {value, {From, Name}} ->
            server_transfer(From, Name, To, Message, User_List)
    end.
%%% If the user exists, send the message
server_transfer(From, Name, To, Message, User_List) ->
    %% Find the receiver and send the message
    case lists:keysearch(To, 2, User_List) of
        false ->
            From ! {messenger, receiver_not_found};
        {value, {ToPid, To}} ->
            ToPid ! {message_from, Name, Message}, 
            From ! {messenger, sent} 
    end.


%%% User Commands
logon(Name) ->
    case whereis(mess_client) of 
        undefined ->
            register(mess_client, 
                     spawn(messenger, client, [server_node(), Name]));
        _ -> already_logged_on
    end.

logoff() ->
    mess_client ! logoff.

message(ToName, Message) ->
    case whereis(mess_client) of % Test if the client is running
        undefined ->
            not_logged_on;
        _ -> mess_client ! {message_to, ToName, Message},
             ok
end.


%%% The client process which runs on each server node
client(Server_Node, Name) ->
    {messenger, Server_Node} ! {self(), logon, Name},
    await_result(),
    client(Server_Node).

client(Server_Node) ->
    receive
        logoff ->
            {messenger, Server_Node} ! {self(), logoff},
            exit(normal);
        {message_to, ToName, Message} ->
            {messenger, Server_Node} ! {self(), message_to, ToName, Message},
            await_result();
        {message_from, FromName, Message} ->
            io:format("Message from ~p: ~p~n", [FromName, Message])
    end,
    client(Server_Node).

%%% wait for a response from the server
await_result() ->
    receive
        {messenger, stop, Why} -> % Stop the client 
            io:format("~p~n", [Why]),
            exit(normal);
        {messenger, What} ->  % Normal response
            io:format("~p~n", [What])
    end.</code>
    <p>To use this program, you need to:</p>
    <list type="bulleted">
      <item>Configure the <c>server_node()</c> function.</item>
      <item>Copy the compiled code (<c>messenger.beam</c>) to
       the directory on each computer where you start Erlang.</item>
    </list>
    <p>In the following example using this program,
      nodes are started on four different computers. If you do not have that
      many machines available on your network, you can start
      several nodes on the same machine.</p>
    <p>Four Erlang nodes are started up: messenger@super, c1@bilbo,
      c2@kosken, c3@gollum.</p>
    <p>First the server at messenger@super is started up:</p>
    <pre>
(messenger@super)1> <input>messenger:start_server().</input>
true</pre>
    <p>Now Peter logs on at c1@bilbo:</p>
    <pre>
(c1@bilbo)1> <input>messenger:logon(peter).</input>
true
logged_on</pre>
    <p>James logs on at c2@kosken:</p>
    <pre>
(c2@kosken)1> <input>messenger:logon(james).</input>
true
logged_on</pre>
    <p>And Fred logs on at c3@gollum:</p>
    <pre>
(c3@gollum)1> <input>messenger:logon(fred).</input>
true
logged_on</pre>
    <p>Now Peter sends Fred a message:</p>
    <pre>
(c1@bilbo)2> <input>messenger:message(fred, "hello").</input>
ok
sent</pre>
    <p>Fred receives the message and sends a message to Peter and
      logs off:</p>
    <pre>
Message from peter: "hello"
(c3@gollum)2> <input>messenger:message(peter, "go away, I'm busy").</input>
ok
sent
(c3@gollum)3> <input>messenger:logoff().</input>
logoff</pre>
    <p>James now tries to send a message to Fred:</p>
    <pre>
(c2@kosken)2> <input>messenger:message(fred, "peter doesn't like you").</input>
ok
receiver_not_found</pre>
    <p>But this fails as Fred has already logged off.</p>
    <p>First let us look at some of the new concepts that have
       been introduced.</p>
    <p>There are two versions of the <c>server_transfer</c> function:
      one with four arguments (<c>server_transfer/4</c>) and one with
      five (<c>server_transfer/5</c>). These are regarded by Erlang as
      two separate functions.</p>
    <p>Notice how to write the <c>server</c> function so that it calls
      itself, through <c>server(User_List)</c>, and thus creates a loop.
      The Erlang compiler is "clever" and optimizes the code so that
      this really is a sort of loop and not a proper function call. But
      this only works if there is no code after the call. Otherwise,
      the compiler expects the call to return and make a proper
      function call. This would result in the process getting bigger
      and bigger for every loop.</p>
    <p>Functions in the <c>lists</c> module are used. This is a very
      useful module and a study of the manual page is recommended
      (<c>erl -man lists</c>).
      <c>lists:keymember(Key,Position,Lists)</c> looks through a list
      of tuples and looks at <c>Position</c> in each tuple to see if it
      is the same as <c>Key</c>. The first element is position 1. If it
      finds a tuple where the element at <c>Position</c> is the same as
      <c>Key</c>, it returns <c>true</c>, otherwise <c>false</c>.</p>
    <pre>
3> <input>lists:keymember(a, 2, [{x,y,z},{b,b,b},{b,a,c},{q,r,s}]).</input>
true
4> <input>lists:keymember(p, 2, [{x,y,z},{b,b,b},{b,a,c},{q,r,s}]).</input>
false</pre>
    <p><c>lists:keydelete</c> works in the same way but deletes
      the first tuple found (if any) and returns the remaining list:</p>
    <pre>
5> <input>lists:keydelete(a, 2, [{x,y,z},{b,b,b},{b,a,c},{q,r,s}]).</input>
[{x,y,z},{b,b,b},{q,r,s}]</pre>
    <p><c>lists:keysearch</c> is like <c>lists:keymember</c>, but it
      returns <c>{value,Tuple_Found}</c> or the atom <c>false</c>.</p>
    <p>There are many very useful functions in the <c>lists</c>
      module.</p>
    <p>An Erlang process (conceptually) runs until it does a
      <c>receive</c> and there is no message which it wants to receive
      in the message queue. "conceptually" is used here because the Erlang
      system shares the CPU time between the active processes in
      the system.</p>
    <p>A process terminates when there is nothing more for it to do,
      that is, the last function it calls simply returns and does not call
      another function. Another way for a process to terminate is for
      it to call <c>exit/1</c>. The argument to <c>exit/1</c> has a
      special meaning, which is discussed later. In this example,
      <c>exit(normal)</c> is done, which has the same effect as a
      process running out of functions to call.</p>
    <p>The BIF <c>whereis(RegisteredName)</c> checks if a registered
      process of name <c>RegisteredName</c> exists. If it exists, the pid of
      that process is returned. If it does not exist, the atom
      <c>undefined</c> is returned.</p>
    <p>You should by now be able to understand most of the code in the
      messenger-module. Let us study one case in detail: a message is
      sent from one user to another.</p>
    <p>The first user "sends" the message in the example above by:</p>
    <code type="none">
messenger:message(fred, "hello")</code>
    <p>After testing that the client process exists:</p>
    <code type="none">
whereis(mess_client) </code>
    <p>And a message is sent to <c>mess_client</c>:</p>
    <code type="none">
mess_client ! {message_to, fred, "hello"}</code>
    <p>The client sends the message to the server by:</p>
    <code type="none">
{messenger, messenger@super} ! {self(), message_to, fred, "hello"},</code>
    <p>And waits for a reply from the server.</p>
    <p>The server receives this message and calls:</p>
    <code type="none">
server_transfer(From, fred, "hello", User_List),</code>
    <p>This checks that the pid <c>From</c> is in the <c>User_List</c>:</p>
    <code type="none">
lists:keysearch(From, 1, User_List) </code>
    <p>If <c>keysearch</c> returns the atom <c>false</c>, some
      error has occurred and the server sends back the message:</p>
    <code type="none">
From ! {messenger, stop, you_are_not_logged_on}</code>
    <p>This is received by the client, which in turn does
      <c>exit(normal)</c> and terminates. If <c>keysearch</c> returns
      <c>{value,{From,Name}}</c> it is certain that the user is logged on and
      that his name (peter) is in variable <c>Name</c>.</p>
      <p>Let us now call:</p>
    <code type="none">
server_transfer(From, peter, fred, "hello", User_List)</code>
    <p>Notice that as this is <c>server_transfer/5</c>, it is not the same
      as the previous function <c>server_transfer/4</c>. Another
      <c>keysearch</c> is done on <c>User_List</c> to find the pid of
      the client corresponding to fred:</p>
    <code type="none">
lists:keysearch(fred, 2, User_List)</code>
    <p>This time argument 2 is used, which is the second element in
      the tuple. If this returns the atom <c>false</c>,
      fred is not logged on and the following message is sent:</p>
    <code type="none">
From ! {messenger, receiver_not_found};</code>
    <p>This is received by the client.</p>
    <p> If <c>keysearch</c> returns:</p>
    <code type="none">
{value, {ToPid, fred}}</code>
    <p>The following message is sent to fred's client:</p>
    <code type="none">
ToPid ! {message_from, peter, "hello"}, </code>
    <p>The following message is sent to peter's client:</p>
    <code type="none">
From ! {messenger, sent} </code>
    <p>Fred's client receives the message and prints it:</p>
    <code type="none">
{message_from, peter, "hello"} ->
    io:format("Message from ~p: ~p~n", [peter, "hello"])</code>
    <p>Peter's client receives the message in
      the <c>await_result</c> function.</p>
  </section>
</chapter>

