<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter SYSTEM "chapter.dtd">

<chapter>
  <header>
    <copyright>
      <year>1997</year><year>2013</year>
      <holder>Ericsson AB. All Rights Reserved.</holder>
    </copyright>
    <legalnotice>
      Licensed under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the "License");
      you may not use this file except in compliance with the License.
      You may obtain a copy of the License at
 
          http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0

      Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
      distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,
      WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
      See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
      limitations under the License.
    
    </legalnotice>

    <title>Introduction</title>
    <prepared>Ingela Anderton Andin</prepared>
    <responsible></responsible>
    <docno></docno>
    <approved></approved>
    <checked></checked>
    <date>2004-09-28</date>
    <rev>A</rev>
    <file>inets_services.xml</file>
  </header>

  <section>
    <title>Purpose</title>
    <p>Inets is a container for Internet clients and
      servers. Currently, an <term id="HTTP"></term>client and server, a
      TFPT client and server, and a FTP client has been incorporated
      into Inets. The HTTP server and client is HTTP 1.1 compliant as
      defined in <term id="RFC"></term>2616.</p>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Prerequisites</title>
    <p>It is assumed that the reader is familiar with the Erlang
      programming language, concepts of OTP and has a basic
      understanding of the HTTP, TFTP and FTP protocols.</p>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>The Service Concept</title>
    <p>Each client and server in inets is viewed as service.  Services
      may be configured to be started at application startup or
      started dynamically in runtime. If you want to run inets as an
      distributed application that should handle application failover
      and takeover, services should be configured to be started at
      application startup. When starting the inets application
      the inets top supervisor will start a number of subsupervisors
      and worker processes for handling the different services
      provided. When starting services dynamically new children will
      be added to the supervision tree, unless the service is started
      with the stand alone option, in which case the service is linked
      to the calling process and all OTP application features such as
      soft upgrade are lost.</p>
    <p>Services that should be configured for startup at application
      startup time should be put into the erlang node configuration file
      on the form: </p>
    <pre>
      [{inets, [{services, ListofConfiguredServices}]}].
    </pre>
    <p>For details of exactly what to put in the list of configured
      services see the documentation for the services that should be
      configured.</p>
  </section>
</chapter>


