<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter SYSTEM "chapter.dtd">

<chapter>
  <header>
    <copyright>
      <year>1997</year><year>2016</year>
      <holder>Ericsson AB. All Rights Reserved.</holder>
    </copyright>
    <legalnotice>
      Licensed under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the "License");
      you may not use this file except in compliance with the License.
      You may obtain a copy of the License at
 
          http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0

      Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
      distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,
      WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
      See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
      limitations under the License.
    
    </legalnotice>

    <title>Inets</title>
    <prepared>Ingela Anderton Andin</prepared>
    <responsible></responsible>
    <docno></docno>
    <approved></approved>
    <checked></checked>
    <date>2004-09-28</date>
    <rev>A</rev>
    <file>inets_services.xml</file>
  </header>

  <section>
    <title>Service Concept</title>
    <p>Each client and server in <c>Inets</c> is viewed as a service.
      Services can be configured to be started at application startup or
      dynamically in runtime. To run <c>Inets</c> as a distributed 
      application that handles application failover and takeover, 
      configure the services to be started at application startup. 
      When starting the <c>Inets</c> application, the <c>Inets</c> 
      top supervisor starts a number of subsupervisors and worker 
      processes for handling the provided services.
      When starting services dynamically, new children are added to the 
      supervision tree, unless the service is started with the standalone 
      option. In this case the service is linked to the calling process 
      and all OTP application features, such as soft upgrade, are lost.</p>
    <p>Services to be configured for startup at application startup are to 
      be put into the Erlang node configuration file
      on the following form:</p>
    <pre>
      [{inets, [{services, ListofConfiguredServices}]}].</pre>
    <p>For details of what to put in the list of configured services, 
    see the documentation for the services to be configured.</p>
  </section>
</chapter>


