<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter SYSTEM "chapter.dtd">
<!-- %EricssonCopyright% -->
<chapter>
  <header>
    <copyright>
      <year>2013</year><year>2018</year>
      <holder>Ericsson AB. All Rights Reserved.</holder>
    </copyright>
    <legalnotice>
      The program may be used and/or copied only with the written permission from
      Ericsson AB, or in accordance with the terms and conditions stipulated in
      the agreement/contract under which the program has been supplied.
    </legalnotice>
    <title>Secure Shell (SSH)</title>
    <prepared>OTP</prepared>
    <date></date>
    <rev>%VSN%</rev>
    <file>ssh_protocol.xml</file>
  </header>

  <section>
    <title>SSH Protocol Overview</title>

    <p> Conceptually the SSH protocol can be partitioned into four
    layers:</p>

    <image file="SSH_protocols.png">
      <icaption>SSH Protocol Architecture</icaption>
    </image>

    <section>
      <title>Transport Protocol</title>

      <p> The SSH Transport Protocol is a secure, low level transport.
      It provides strong encryption, cryptographic host
      authentication and integrity protection. Currently, only a
      minimum of MAC- (message authentication code, a short piece of
      information used to authenticate a message) and encryption
      algorithms are supported see <seealso marker="ssh">ssh(3)</seealso>
      </p>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Authentication Protocol</title>

      <p>The SSH authentication protocol is a general-purpose user
      authentication protocol run over the SSH transport
      protocol. Erlang SSH supports user authentication using public
      key technology (RSA and DSA, X509-certificates are currently not
      supported). It is also possible to use a so called keyboard
      interactive authentication. This method is suitable for
      interactive authentication methods that do not need any special
      software support on the client side. Instead, all authentication
      data should be entered via the keyboard. It is also possible
      to use a pure password based authentication scheme, note that in
      this case the the plain text password will be encrypted before sent
      over the network. There are several configuration options for
      authentication handling available in
      <seealso marker="ssh#connect-3">ssh:connect/[3,4]</seealso>
      and <seealso marker="ssh#daemon-2">ssh:daemon/[2,3]</seealso>
      It is also possible to customize the public key handling
      by implementing the behaviours <seealso
      marker="ssh_client_key_api">ssh_client_key_api</seealso> and
      <seealso
	  marker="ssh_server_key_api">ssh_server_key_api</seealso>
      </p>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Connection Protocol</title>

      <p>The SSH Connection Protocol provides application-support
      services over the transport pipe, such as channel multiplexing,
      flow control, remote program execution, signal propagation,
      connection forwarding, etc.  Functions for handling the SSH
      Connection Protocol can be found in the module <seealso
      marker="ssh_connection">ssh_connection</seealso>.
      </p>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Channels</title>

      <p>All terminal sessions, forwarded connections etc., are
      channels.  Multiple channels are multiplexed into a single
      connection, and all channels are flow-controlled.  Typically an
      SSH client will open a channel, send data/commands, receive
      data/"control information" and when it is done close the
      channel. The 
      <seealso marker="ssh_client_channel">ssh_client_channel</seealso> / 
      <seealso marker="ssh_server_channel">ssh_server_channel</seealso> (Replaces ssh_daemon_channel)
      behaviours makes it easy to
      write your own SSH client/server processes that use flow
      control. It handles generic parts of SSH channel management and
      lets you focus on the application logic.
      </p>

      <p>Channels comes in three flavors</p>

      <list type="bulleted">
	<item><em>Subsystem</em> - named services that can be run as
	part of an SSH server such as SFTP <seealso
	marker="ssh_sftpd">ssh_sftpd</seealso>, that is built in to the
	SSH daemon (server) by default but may be disabled. The Erlang SSH
	daemon may be configured to run any Erlang
	implemented SSH subsystem.
	</item>
	<item><em>Shell</em> - interactive shell.  By default the
	Erlang daemon will run the Erlang shell. It is
	possible to customize the shell by providing your own
	read-eval-print loop. It is also possible, but much more work,
	to provide your own CLI (Command Line Interface) implementation.
	</item>
	<item><em>Exec</em> - one-time remote execution of commands. See <seealso
	marker="ssh_connection#exec-4">ssh_connection:exec/4</seealso></item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <p>Channels are flow controlled.  No data may be sent to a channel
    peer until a message is received to indicate that window space is
    available.  The 'initial window size' specifies how many bytes of
    channel data that can be sent to the channel peer without adjusting the
    window.
    </p>

    <p>
      For more detailed information about the SSH protocol, see the
      following RFCs:
    </p>

    <list type="bulleted">
      <item><url href="http://www.ietf.org/rfc/rfc4250.txt">RFC 4250</url> -
      Protocol Assigned Numbers.</item>
      <item><url href="http://www.ietf.org/rfc/rfc4251.txt">RFC 4251</url> -
      Protocol Architecture.</item>
      <item><url href="http://www.ietf.org/rfc/rfc4252.txt">RFC 4252</url> -
      Authentication Protocol.</item>
      <item><url href="http://www.ietf.org/rfc/rfc4253.txt">RFC 4253</url> -
      Transport Layer Protocol.</item>
      <item><url href="http://www.ietf.org/rfc/rfc4254.txt">RFC 4254</url> -
      Connection Protocol.</item>
      <item><url href="http://www.ietf.org/rfc/rfc4344.txt">RFC 4344</url> -
      Transport Layer Encryption Modes.</item>
      <item><url href="http://www.ietf.org/rfc/rfc4716.txt">RFC 4716</url> -
      Public Key File Format.</item>
    </list>
  </section>
</chapter>
