<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<!DOCTYPE erlref SYSTEM "erlref.dtd">

<erlref>
  <header>
    <copyright>
      <year>2009</year>
      <year>2018</year>
      <holder>Ericsson AB, All Rights Reserved</holder>
    </copyright>
    <legalnotice>
      Licensed under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the "License");
      you may not use this file except in compliance with the License.
      You may obtain a copy of the License at
 
          http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0

      Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
      distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,
      WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
      See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
      limitations under the License.

      The Initial Developer of the Original Code is Ericsson AB.
    </legalnotice>
    <title>ssh_server_channel</title>
    <prepared></prepared>
    <docno></docno>
    <date></date>
    <rev></rev>
  </header>
  <module since="OTP 21.0">ssh_server_channel</module>
  <modulesummary>-behaviour(ssh_server_channel). (Replaces ssh_daemon_channel)
  </modulesummary>
  <description>
    <note>
      <p>This module replaces ssh_daemon_channel.</p>
      <p>The old module is still available for compatibility, but should not be used for new programs.
      The old module will not be maintained except for some error corrections
      </p>
    </note>

    <p>SSH services (clients and servers) are implemented as channels
    that are multiplexed over an SSH connection and communicates over
    the <url href="http://www.ietf.org/rfc/rfc4254.txt"> SSH
    Connection Protocol</url>. This module provides a callback API
    that takes care of generic channel aspects for daemons, such as flow control
    and close messages. It lets the callback functions take care of
    the service (application) specific parts. This behavior also ensures
    that the channel process honors the principal of an OTP-process so
    that it can be part of a supervisor tree. This is a requirement of
    channel processes implementing a subsystem that will be added to
    the <c>ssh</c> applications supervisor tree.
    </p>

    <note><p>When implementing a client subsystem handler, use
    <seealso marker="ssh_client_channel">-behaviour(ssh_client_channel)</seealso> instead.
    </p>
    </note>

  </description>

  <section>
    <title>Callback Functions</title>
    <p>
      The following functions are to be exported from a
      <c>ssh_server_channel</c> callback module.
    </p>
  </section>

  <funcs>
    <func>
      <name since="OTP 21.0">Module:init(Args) -> {ok, State} | {ok, State, timeout()} |
      {stop, Reason}</name>
      <fsummary>Makes necessary initializations and returns the
      initial channel state if the initializations succeed.</fsummary>
      <type>
	<v>Args = term()</v>
	<d>Last argument to <c>start_link/4</c>.</d>
	<v>State = term()</v>
	<v>Reason = term()</v>
      </type>
      <desc>
	<p>Makes necessary initializations and returns the initial channel
	state if the initializations succeed.
	</p>
	<p>The time-out values that can be returned
	have the same semantics as in a <seealso marker="stdlib:gen_server">gen_server</seealso>.
	If the time-out occurs, <seealso marker="#Module:handle_msg-2">handle_msg/2</seealso>
	is called as <c>handle_msg(timeout, State)</c>.
	</p>
      </desc>
    </func>
   
    <func>
      <name since="OTP 21.0">Module:handle_msg(Msg, State) -> {ok, State} |
      {stop, ChannelId, State}</name>

      <fsummary>Handles other messages than SSH connection protocol,
      call, or cast messages sent to the channel.</fsummary>
      <type>
	<v>Msg = timeout | term()</v>
	<v>ChannelId = <seealso marker="ssh#type-channel_id">ssh:channel_id()</seealso></v>
	<v>State = term() </v>
      </type>
      <desc>
	<p>Handles other messages than SSH Connection Protocol, call, or
	cast messages sent to the channel. 
	</p>

	<p>Possible Erlang 'EXIT' messages is to be handled by this
	function and all channels are to handle the following message.</p>
	
	<taglist>
	  <tag><c>{ssh_channel_up, </c><seealso marker="ssh:ssh#type-channel_id">ssh:channel_id()</seealso><c>, </c><seealso marker="ssh:ssh#type-connection_ref">ssh:connection_ref()</seealso><c>}</c></tag>
	  <item><p>This is the first message that the channel receives.
	  This is especially useful if the
	  server wants to send a message to the client without first
	  receiving a message from it. If the message is not
	  useful for your particular scenario, ignore it by
	  immediately returning <c>{ok, State}</c>.
	  </p></item>
	</taglist>
      </desc>
    </func>

    <func>
      <name since="OTP 21.0">Module:handle_ssh_msg(Msg, State) -> {ok, State} | {stop,
      ChannelId, State}</name>
      <fsummary>Handles <c>ssh</c> connection protocol messages.</fsummary>
      <type>
	<v>Msg = <seealso marker="ssh_connection#type-event">ssh_connection:event()</seealso></v>
	<v>ChannelId = <seealso marker="ssh#type-channel_id">ssh:channel_id()</seealso></v>
	<v>State = term()</v>
      </type>
      <desc>
	<p>Handles SSH Connection Protocol messages that may need
	service-specific attention. For details,
	see <seealso marker="ssh_connection#type-event">ssh_connection:event()</seealso>.
	</p>
	
	<p>The following message is taken care of by the
	<c>ssh_server_channel</c> behavior.</p>
	
	<taglist>
	  <tag><c>{closed, </c><seealso marker="ssh:ssh#type-channel_id">ssh:channel_id()</seealso><c>}</c></tag>
	  <item><p>The channel behavior sends a close message to the
	  other side, if such a message has not already been sent.
	  Then it terminates the channel with reason <c>normal</c>.</p></item>
	</taglist>
      </desc>
    </func>

    <func>
      <name since="OTP 21.0">Module:terminate(Reason, State) -> _</name>
      <fsummary>Does cleaning up before channel process termination.
      </fsummary>
      <type>
	<v>Reason = term()</v>
	<v>State = term()</v>
      </type>
      <desc>
	<p>This function is called by a channel process when it is
	about to terminate. Before this function is called, <seealso
	marker="ssh_connection#close-2"> ssh_connection:close/2
	</seealso> is called, if it has not been called earlier.
	This function does any necessary cleaning
	up. When it returns, the channel process terminates with
	reason <c>Reason</c>. The return value is ignored.
	</p>
      </desc>
    </func>
    
  </funcs>
  
</erlref>
