<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter SYSTEM "chapter.dtd">

<chapter>
  <header>
    <copyright>
      <year>2009</year>
      <year>2016</year>
      <holder>Ericsson AB, All Rights Reserved</holder>
    </copyright>
    <legalnotice>
  Licensed under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the "License");
  you may not use this file except in compliance with the License.
  You may obtain a copy of the License at
 
      http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0

  Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
  distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,
  WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
  See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
  limitations under the License.

  The Initial Developer of the Original Code is Ericsson AB.
      </legalnotice>

    <title>Reltool Release Notes</title>
    <prepared>H&aring;kan Mattsson</prepared>
    <docno></docno>
    <date></date>
    <rev></rev>
    <file>notes.xml</file>
  </header>
  <p>This document describes the changes made to the Reltool system
    from version to version. The intention of this document is to
    list all incompatibilities as well as all enhancements and
    bugfixes for every release of Reltool. Each release of Reltool
    thus constitutes one section in this document. The title of each
    section is the version number of Reltool.</p>

  <section><title>Reltool 0.7.1</title>

    <section><title>Improvements and New Features</title>
      <list>
        <item>
	    <p> Modify the code as motivated by a change of the
	    Erlang Parser (<c>undefined</c> is no longer
	    automatically inserted to the type of record fields
	    without an initializer). </p>
          <p>
	    Own Id: OTP-13033 Aux Id: OTP-12719 </p>
        </item>
      </list>
    </section>

</section>

<section><title>Reltool 0.7</title>

    <section><title>Improvements and New Features</title>
      <list>
        <item>
          <p>
	    Change license text from Erlang Public License to Apache
	    Public License v2</p>
          <p>
	    Own Id: OTP-12845</p>
        </item>
      </list>
    </section>

</section>

<section><title>Reltool 0.6.6</title>

    <section><title>Fixed Bugs and Malfunctions</title>
      <list>
        <item>
          <p>
	    Fixed a minor typo in an error message from
	    reltool_server.</p>
          <p>
	    Own Id: OTP-11977</p>
        </item>
      </list>
    </section>

</section>

<section><title>Reltool 0.6.5</title>

    <section><title>Fixed Bugs and Malfunctions</title>
      <list>
        <item>
          <p>
	    When adding a regexp to a filter in reltool using
	    {add,Regexp}, and the existing regexp was undefined,
	    reltool would crash since it got an improper list. This
	    has been corrected. (Thanks to Håkan Mattsson)</p>
          <p>
	    Own Id: OTP-11591</p>
        </item>
        <item>
          <p>
	    Adapted reltool test server to common test usage of
	    tc_status. (Note that this code is not used by OTP daily
	    test runs.) (Thanks to Håkan Mattsson)</p>
          <p>
	    Own Id: OTP-11592</p>
        </item>
        <item>
          <p>
	    Application upgrade (appup) files are corrected for the
	    following applications: </p>
          <p>
	    <c>asn1, common_test, compiler, crypto, debugger,
	    dialyzer, edoc, eldap, erl_docgen, et, eunit, gs, hipe,
	    inets, observer, odbc, os_mon, otp_mibs, parsetools,
	    percept, public_key, reltool, runtime_tools, ssh,
	    syntax_tools, test_server, tools, typer, webtool, wx,
	    xmerl</c></p>
          <p>
	    A new test utility for testing appup files is added to
	    test_server. This is now used by most applications in
	    OTP.</p>
          <p>
	    (Thanks to Tobias Schlager)</p>
          <p>
	    Own Id: OTP-11744</p>
        </item>
      </list>
    </section>

</section>

<section><title>Reltool 0.6.4.1</title>

    <section><title>Improvements and New Features</title>
      <list>
        <item>
          <p>
	    The encoding of the <c>notes.xml</c> file has been
	    changed from latin1 to utf-8 to avoid future merge
	    problems.</p>
          <p>
	    Own Id: OTP-11310</p>
        </item>
      </list>
    </section>

</section>

<section><title>Reltool 0.6.4</title>

    <section><title>Fixed Bugs and Malfunctions</title>
      <list>
        <item>
          <p>
	    Fix receive support in erl_eval with a BEAM module.
	    Thanks to Anthony Ramine.</p>
          <p>
	    Own Id: OTP-11137</p>
        </item>
      </list>
    </section>


    <section><title>Improvements and New Features</title>
      <list>
        <item>
          <p>
	    Reltool used to fail if an application was mentioned in
	    the config file which was not found in the file system,
	    even if the application was explicitly excluded in the
	    config. This has been changed and will only produce a
	    warning. If the application is not explicitly excluded it
	    will still cause reltool to fail. Thanks to Håkan
	    Mattsson!</p>
          <p>
	    Own Id: OTP-10988</p>
        </item>
        <item>
          <p>
	    Fix possibly "not owner" error while file copy with
	    reltool. Thanks to Alexey Saltanov.</p>
          <p>
	    Own Id: OTP-11099</p>
        </item>
      </list>
    </section>

</section>

<section><title>Reltool 0.6.3</title>

    <section><title>Improvements and New Features</title>
      <list>
        <item>
          <p>
	    Some updates are made to reltool for handling unicode.</p>
          <p>
	    Own Id: OTP-10781</p>
        </item>
      </list>
    </section>

</section>

<section><title>Reltool 0.6.2</title>

    <section><title>Fixed Bugs and Malfunctions</title>
      <list>
        <item>
	    <list> <item> If <c>incl_cond</c> was set to
	    <c>derived</c> on module level, then reltool_server would
	    crash with a <c>case_clause</c>. This has been corrected.
	    <c>incl_cond</c> on module level now overwrites
	    <c>mod_cond</c> on app or sys level as described in the
	    documentation. </item> <item> If a <c>rel</c> spec in the
	    reltool config does not contain all applications that are
	    listed as <c>{applications,Applications}</c> in a
	    <c>.app</c> file, then these applications are
	    autmatically added when creating the <c>.rel</c> file.
	    For 'included_applications', the behaviour was not the
	    same. I.e. if a <c>rel</c> spec in the reltool config did
	    not contain all applications that are listed as
	    <c>{included_applications,InclApplications}</c> in a
	    <c>.app</c> file, then reltool would fail with reason
	    "Undefined applications" when creating the <c>.rel</c>
	    file. This has been corrected, so both
	    <c>applications</c> and <c>included_applications</c> are
	    now automatically added if not already in the <c>rel</c>
	    spec. </item> <item> The <c>rel</c> specification now
	    dictates the order in which included and used
	    applications (specified in the <c>.app</c> file as
	    <c>included_applications</c> and <c>applications</c>
	    respectively) are loaded/started by the boot file. If the
	    applications are not specified in the <c>rel</c> spec,
	    then the order from the <c>.app</c> file is used. This
	    was a bug earlier reported on systools, and is now also
	    implemented in reltool. </item> <item> Instead of only
	    looking at the directory name, reltool now first looks
	    for a <c>.app</c> file in order to figure out the name of
	    an application. </item> </list>
          <p>
	    Own Id: OTP-10012 Aux Id: kunagi-171 [82] </p>
        </item>
      </list>
    </section>


    <section><title>Improvements and New Features</title>
      <list>
        <item>
	    <p> Some examples overflowing the width of PDF pages have
	    been corrected. </p>
          <p>
	    Own Id: OTP-10665</p>
        </item>
      </list>
    </section>

</section>

<section><title>Reltool 0.6.1</title>

    <section><title>Improvements and New Features</title>
      <list>
        <item>
          <p>
	    A new sys level configuration parameter
	    <c>{excl_lib,otp_root}</c> is added. When this is set,
	    the target system will not contain anything from
	    <c>$OTP_ROOT</c>. It will only contain a releases
	    directory with rel, script and boot files, and a lib
	    directory with applications found outside of
	    <c>$OTP_ROOT</c> (i.e. "your own" applications).</p>
          <p>
	    Own Id: OTP-9743</p>
        </item>
      </list>
    </section>

</section>

<section><title>Reltool 0.6</title>

    <section><title>Fixed Bugs and Malfunctions</title>
      <list>
        <item>
	    Miscellaneous corrections: <list> <item> Start of reltool
	    GUI would sometimes crash with a badmatch in
	    reltool_sys_win:do_init. This has been corrected. </item>
	    <item> Minor corrections of documentation and type
	    specifications of app() and mod() are done. </item>
	    <item> If a module name is duplicated in an app file
	    reltool would return an error. This is now changed to a
	    warning. </item> <item> Reltool would earlier not
	    necessarily keep the order of applications as listed in
	    the rel specification in the configuration. This has been
	    corrected. </item> <item> Reltool would earlier set the
	    default for included applications to an empty list if it
	    was not set in the rel specification in the
	    configuration. This was correct according to
	    sasl/systools documentation, but not according to
	    sasl/systools implementation. We decided to change the
	    documentation and reltool to use the value of
	    included_applications from the .app file as default
	    instead of the empty list, since this seems more
	    intuitive and since systools always has done the same.
	    </item> <item> The value of included applications in the
	    rel specification in the configuration did not overwrite
	    included_applications in the .app file if it was set to
	    an empty list. This has been corrected. </item> <item>
	    Reltool would earlier add load instructions in the
	    script/boot files for ALL modules in the ebin directory
	    of an application even if mod_cond was set to app
	    (include only modules listed in the .app file). This has
	    been corrected. </item> <item> Reltool would earlier add
	    start instructions in the script/boot file for included
	    applications. This has been corrected - included
	    applications shall only be loaded since the including
	    application is responsible for starting them. </item>
	    <item> Status bar now indicates that reltool is working
	    (Processing libraries...) for all configuration changes,
	    and when generating target system. </item> <item> Title
	    of dependecies column in app and mod window is changed
	    from "Modules used by others" to "Modules using this".
	    </item> </list>
          <p>
	    Own Id: OTP-9792</p>
        </item>
        <item>
          <p>
	    Configuration changes via the GUI had a few bugs related
	    to error handling, rollback and undo. A major re-write of
	    the reltool_server has been done in order to align the
	    way reltool_server updates and uses its state and tables
	    for all different kinds of configuration change. </p>
          <p>
	    All configuration changes (except undo) now cause a
	    re-read of the file system, meaning that if something has
	    changed in the file system it will be reflected in the
	    result of the configuration change.</p>
          <p>
	    When loading a new configuration file via the GUI, the
	    old configuration is now completely scratched, and only
	    the new is valid.</p>
          <p>
	    *** POTENTIAL INCOMPATIBILITY ***</p>
          <p>
	    Own Id: OTP-9794</p>
        </item>
        <item>
          <p>
	    Some bug fixes related to the handling of escripts:</p>
	    <list> <item> Reltool could not handle escripts with
	    inlined applications. This has been corrected. Inlined
	    applications will be visible in the GUI, but not possible
	    to include/exclude separately. </item> <item> Loading a
	    config which contains an escript via the GUI menu did not
	    produce the same result as when using the same
	    configuration at reltool start. Paths, version and label
	    could differ. This has been corrected. </item> <item>
	    Loading config with same escript (source) twice caused
	    reltool to add same module twice. This has been
	    corrected. </item> <item> Loading config with same
	    escript (inlined beam) twice caused reltool to fail
	    saying module is included by two different applications.
	    This has been corrected. </item> <item> Loading config
	    which in addition to an existing escript also adds
	    another escript, for which the name sorts before the
	    existing one, would cause reltool to fail saying
	    "Application name clash". This has been corrected.
	    </item> </list>
          <p>
	    Own Id: OTP-9968</p>
        </item>
        <item>
          <p>
	    Reltool would sometimes generate a .app file containing
	    <c>{start_phases,undefined}</c>, which would cause an
	    exception in systools at parse time. This has been
	    corrected so reltool now omits the <c>start_phases</c>
	    entry if the value is <c>undefined</c>. (Thanks to Juan
	    Jose Comellas)</p>
          <p>
	    In order to align with reltool, sasl will also omit
	    <c>start_phases</c> entries with value <c>undefined</c>
	    in .script files.</p>
          <p>
	    Own Id: OTP-10003</p>
        </item>
      </list>
    </section>


    <section><title>Improvements and New Features</title>
      <list>
        <item>
          <p>
	    A warning list is added to the sys window of the reltool
	    GUI. This list will continuously show all warnings
	    produced by the current configuration.</p>
          <p>
	    Own Id: OTP-9967</p>
        </item>
        <item>
          <p>
	    As a way of specifying one specific version of an
	    application, the following configuration parameter is
	    added on application level:</p>
          <p>
	    {lib_dir,Dir}, Dir = string()</p>
          <p>
	    This can be useful if the parent directory of the
	    application directory is not suitable to use as a lib dir
	    on system level.</p>
          <p>
	    Own Id: OTP-9977</p>
        </item>
      </list>
    </section>

</section>

<section><title>Reltool 0.5.7.1</title>

    <section><title>Improvements and New Features</title>
      <list>
        <item>
          <p>
	    Added recommendation about <c>RootDir</c> parameter to
	    <c>reltool:eval_target_spec/3</c>.</p>
          <p>
	    Own Id: OTP-9742</p>
        </item>
      </list>
    </section>

</section>

<section><title>Reltool 0.5.7</title>

    <section><title>Fixed Bugs and Malfunctions</title>
      <list>
        <item>
          <p>
	    If a module was duplicated in the library directories
	    visible to reltool, and the configuration did not point
	    out which file to use, then reltool:start would always
	    fail. A pop-up is added which asks if you want to
	    continue with a safe and minimal configuration.</p>
          <p>
	    Own Id: OTP-9383</p>
        </item>
        <item>
          <p>
	    wx would sometimes crash due to an empty radiobox on the
	    'releases' tab of the system window. This radiobox is
	    removed, and replaced by a listbox which will always
	    contain at least kernel and stdlib applications.</p>
          <p>
	    Own Id: OTP-9384</p>
        </item>
      </list>
    </section>

</section>

<section><title>Reltool 0.5.6</title>

    <section><title>Fixed Bugs and Malfunctions</title>
      <list>
        <item>
          <p>
	    The system level option <c>app_files</c> is documented to
	    allow the values <c>keep | strip | all</c>, but it only
	    allowed <c>keep</c>. This is corrected.</p>
          <p>
	    Own Id: OTP-9135</p>
        </item>
        <item>
          <p>
	    Allow the same module name in multiple applications
	    visible to reltool, as long as all but one of the
	    applications/modules are explicitely excluded. (Thanks to
	    Andrew Gopienko and Jay Nelson)</p>
          <p>
	    Own Id: OTP-9229</p>
        </item>
      </list>
    </section>

</section>

<section><title>Reltool 0.5.5</title>

    <section><title>Fixed Bugs and Malfunctions</title>
      <list>
        <item>
          <p>
	    The reltool module contained two seriously erroneous
	    specs which caused bogus warnings when dialyzing reltool
	    and some correct code of users. These were fixed (specs
	    for start_link/1 and eval_server/3)</p>
          <p>
	    - Code cleanups and simplifications - Fix a bug in the
	    calculation of circular dependencies - Eliminate two
	    dialyzer warnings - Put files alphabetically</p>
          <p>
	    Own Id: OTP-9120</p>
        </item>
      </list>
    </section>

</section>

<section><title>Reltool 0.5.4</title>

    <section><title>Improvements and New Features</title>
      <list>
        <item>
          <p>
            Added function <c>zip:foldl/3</c> to iterate over zip
            archives.</p>
          <p>
            Added functions to create and extract escripts. See
            <c>escript:create/2</c> and <c>escript:extract/2</c>.</p>
          <p>
            The undocumented function <c>escript:foldl/3</c> has been
            removed. The same functionality can be achieved with the
            more flexible functions <c>escript:extract/2</c> and
            <c>zip:foldl/3</c>.</p>
          <p>
            Record fields has been annotated with type info. Source
            files as been adapted to fit within 80 chars and trailing
            whitespace has been removed.</p>
          <p>
            Own Id: OTP-8521</p>
        </item>
        <item>
            <p>A new escript, called <c>reltool</c>, has been
            introduced in order to simplify the usage of the reltool
            application from makefiles.</p>
            <p>The handling of applications included in releases has
            been improved. Applications that are required to be
            started before other applications in a release are now
            automatically included in the release. The <c>kernel</c>
            and <c>stdlib</c> applications are always included as
            they are mandatory.</p>
            <p>Applications that are (explicitly or implicitly)
            included in a release are now automatically included as
            if they were explicitly included with the incl_cond
            flag.</p>
            <p>A new <c>embedded_app_type</c> option has been
            introduced. It is intended to be used for embedded
            systems where all included applications must be loaded
            from the boot script, as these systems does not utilize
            dynamic code loading. If <c>embedded_app_type </c> is set
            to something else than <c>undefined</c>, all included
            applications will be included in both the release as well
            as in the boot script. If the <c>profile</c> is
            <c>embedded</c> the <c>embedded_app_type</c> option
            defaults to <c>load</c>.</p>
            <p>A new function called <c>reltool:get_status/1</c> has
            been introduced. It returns status about the
            configuration in the server.</p>
            <p>The API functions that may take <c>PidOrOptions</c> as
            input and actually gets <c>Options</c> does now print out
            warnings.</p>
            <p>The internal error handling has been improved. For
            example <c>{error,Reason}</c> is always returned in case
            of errors even when the server dies.</p>
            <p><c>app</c> and <c>appup</c> files has been added as
            well as a corresponding test suite.</p>
            <p>Various cleanups has been made in the code and in the
            documentation.</p>
          <p>
            Own Id: OTP-8590</p>
        </item>
      </list>
    </section>

  </section>

    <section><title>Reltool 0.5.3</title>

        <section><title>Improvements and New Features</title>
          <list>
            <item>
              <p>
                Removed spurious documentation files.</p>
              <p>
                Own Id: OTP-8057</p>
            </item>
          </list>
        </section>

    </section>

    <section><title>Reltool 0.5.2</title>

        <section><title>Improvements and New Features</title>
          <list>
            <item>
              <p>
                The documentation is now built with open source tools
                (xsltproc and fop) that exists on most platforms. One
                visible change is that the HTML frames are removed.</p>
              <p>
                Own Id: OTP-8254</p>
            </item>
          </list>
        </section>

    </section>

    <section><title>Reltool 0.5.1</title>

	<section><title>Fixed Bugs and Malfunctions</title>
          <list>
            <item>
              <p>
                In the new release of Reltool (0.5) there is a severe bug
                that may cause your source files to be deleted. The bug
                is triggered when you generate a target system WITH
                archive files AND your library directories are given with
                absolute paths. (Library directories are given with the
                ERL_LIBS environment variable or with the lib_dirs
                configuration parameter.)</p>
              <p>
                Own Id: OTP-8199</p>
            </item>
          </list>
        </section>

    </section>

    <section><title>Reltool 0.5</title>

        <section><title>Improvements and New Features</title>
          <list>
            <item>
              <p>
                The tool is still experimental. Feedback is appreciated. </p>
              <p>
                Major improvements of the target system generation has
                been performed. Now it is possible to generate a
                relocatable target system that does not need to be
                re-installed if it is moved to a new location. Archive
                files are automatically generated. A detailed
                specification of the target system can be generated
                without actually creating the target system. Relocatable
                escripts are put in the bin directory of the target
                system. etc. etc.</p>
              <p>
                Some new functions has been introduced in the
                <c>reltool</c> module: <c>start/1, start_link/1,
                get_config/3, get_target_spec/1 and
                eval_target_spec/3</c>.</p>
              <p>
                Some new configuration parameters has been introduced:
                <c>profile, incl_sys_filters, excl_sys_filters,
                incl_app_filters, excl_app_filters, incl_archive_filters,
                excl_archive_filters, archive_opts, escript and
                relocatable</c>.</p>
              <p>
                Some parameters have been obsoleted and given new
                semantics: <c>incl_erts_dirs (incl_sys_filters),
                excl_erts_dirs (excl_sys_filters), incl_app_dirs
                (incl_app_filters), excl_app_dirs (excl_app_filters) and
                escripts (escript).</c></p>
              <p>
                *** POTENTIAL INCOMPATIBILITY ***</p>
              <p>
                Own Id: OTP-7949</p>
            </item>
          </list>
        </section>

     <section>
      <title>Known Bugs and Problems</title>
      <list>
        <item>
          <p>
            The application is experimental. Feedback is appreciated.</p>
        </item>
      </list>
    </section>

    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Reltool 0.2.2</title>
      
      <section>
	<title>Fixed Bugs and Malfunctions</title>
	<list>
	  <item>
	    <p>
	      The tool crashed when rel, script and boot files were
	    generated via the GUI. This has been fixed.</p>
	    <p>
	    Own Id: OTP-7999</p>
	  </item>
	</list>
      </section>
      
    </section>

  <section>
    <title>Reltool 0.2.1</title>

    <section>
      <title>Improvements and New Features</title>

      <list>
	<item>
	  <p>
	  Minor GUI fixes</p>
	  <p>
	  Own Id: OTP-7840</p>
	</item>
      </list>
    </section>
  
  </section>
  
  <section>
    <title>Reltool 0.2</title>
    <section>
      <title>Improvements and new features</title>
      <p>This is the first (experimental) release of Reltool.</p>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Known Bugs and Problems</title>
      <list>
        <item>
          <p>
            The application is experimental.</p>
        </item>
      </list>
    </section>
  </section>
</chapter>
