<?xml version="1.0" encoding="latin1" ?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter SYSTEM "chapter.dtd">

<chapter>
  <header>
    <copyright>
      <year>2009</year>
      <year>2009</year>
      <holder>Ericsson AB, All Rights Reserved</holder>
    </copyright>
    <legalnotice>
  The contents of this file are subject to the Erlang Public License,
  Version 1.1, (the "License"); you may not use this file except in
  compliance with the License. You should have received a copy of the
  Erlang Public License along with this software. If not, it can be
  retrieved online at http://www.erlang.org/.

  Software distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS"
  basis, WITHOUT WARRANTY OF ANY KIND, either express or implied. See
  the License for the specific language governing rights and limitations
  under the License.

  The Initial Developer of the Original Code is Ericsson AB.
      </legalnotice>

    <title>Reltool Release Notes</title>
    <prepared>H&aring;kan Mattsson</prepared>
    <docno></docno>
    <date></date>
    <rev></rev>
    <file>notes.xml</file>
  </header>
  <p>This document describes the changes made to the Reltool system
    from version to version. The intention of this document is to
    list all incompatibilities as well as all enhancements and
    bugfixes for every release of Reltool. Each release of Reltool
    thus constitutes one section in this document. The title of each
    section is the version number of Reltool.</p>


    <section><title>Reltool 0.5.2</title>

        <section><title>Improvements and New Features</title>
          <list>
            <item>
              <p>
                The documentation is now built with open source tools
                (xsltproc and fop) that exists on most platforms. One
                visible change is that the HTML frames are removed.</p>
              <p>
                Own Id: OTP-8254</p>
            </item>
          </list>
        </section>

    </section>

    <section><title>Reltool 0.5.1</title>

	<section><title>Fixed Bugs and Malfunctions</title>
          <list>
            <item>
              <p>
                In the new release of Reltool (0.5) there is a severe bug
                that may cause your source files to be deleted. The bug
                is triggered when you generate a target system WITH
                archive files AND your library directories are given with
                absolute paths. (Library directories are given with the
                ERL_LIBS environment variable or with the lib_dirs
                configuration parameter.)</p>
              <p>
                Own Id: OTP-8199</p>
            </item>
          </list>
        </section>

    </section>

    <section><title>Reltool 0.5</title>

        <section><title>Improvements and New Features</title>
          <list>
            <item>
              <p>
                The tool is still experimental. Feedback is appreciated. </p>
              <p>
                Major improvements of the target system generation has
                been performed. Now it is possible to generate a
                relocatable target system that does not need to be
                re-installed if it is moved to a new location. Archive
                files are automatically generated. A detailed
                specification of the target system can be generated
                without actually creating the target system. Relocatable
                escripts are put in the bin directory of the target
                system. etc. etc.</p>
              <p>
                Some new functions has been introduced in the
                <c>reltool</c> module: <c>start/1, start_link/1,
                get_config/3, get_target_spec/1 and
                eval_target_spec/3</c>.</p>
              <p>
                Some new configuration parameters has been introduced:
                <c>profile, incl_sys_filters, excl_sys_filters,
                incl_app_filters, excl_app_filters, incl_archive_filters,
                excl_archive_filters, archive_opts, escript and
                relocatable</c>.</p>
              <p>
                Some parameters have been obsoleted and given new
                semantics: <c>incl_erts_dirs (incl_sys_filters),
                excl_erts_dirs (excl_sys_filters), incl_app_dirs
                (incl_app_filters), excl_app_dirs (excl_app_filters) and
                escripts (escript).</c></p>
              <p>
                *** POTENTIAL INCOMPATIBILITY ***</p>
              <p>
                Own Id: OTP-7949</p>
            </item>
          </list>
        </section>

     <section>
      <title>Known Bugs and Problems</title>
      <list>
        <item>
          <p>
            The application is experimental. Feedback is appreciated.</p>
        </item>
      </list>
    </section>

    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Reltool 0.2.2</title>
      
      <section>
	<title>Fixed Bugs and Malfunctions</title>
	<list>
	  <item>
	    <p>
	      The tool crashed when rel, script and boot files were
	    generated via the GUI. This has been fixed.</p>
	    <p>
	    Own Id: OTP-7999</p>
	  </item>
	</list>
      </section>
      
    </section>

  <section>
    <title>Reltool 0.2.1</title>

    <section>
      <title>Improvements and New Features</title>

      <list>
	<item>
	  <p>
	  Minor GUI fixes</p>
	  <p>
	  Own Id: OTP-7840</p>
	</item>
      </list>
    </section>
  
  </section>
  
  <section>
    <title>Reltool 0.2</title>
    <section>
      <title>Improvements and new features</title>
      <p>This is the first (experimental) release of Reltool.</p>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Known Bugs and Problems</title>
      <list>
        <item>
          <p>
            The application is experimental.</p>
        </item>
      </list>
    </section>
  </section>
</chapter>
