<?xml version="1.0" encoding="latin1" ?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter SYSTEM "chapter.dtd">

<chapter>
  <header>
    <copyright>
      <year>2006</year><year>2009</year>
      <holder>Ericsson AB. All Rights Reserved.</holder>
    </copyright>
    <legalnotice>
      The contents of this file are subject to the Erlang Public License,
      Version 1.1, (the "License"); you may not use this file except in
      compliance with the License. You should have received a copy of the
      Erlang Public License along with this software. If not, it can be
      retrieved online at http://www.erlang.org/.
    
      Software distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS"
      basis, WITHOUT WARRANTY OF ANY KIND, either express or implied. See
      the License for the specific language governing rights and limitations
      under the License.
    
    </legalnotice>

    <title>Inviso Release Notes</title>
    <prepared></prepared>
    <docno></docno>
    <date></date>
    <rev></rev>
    <file>notes.xml</file>
  </header>
  <p>This document describes the changes made to the Inviso application.</p>


  <section><title>Inviso 0.6.1</title>

    <section><title>Improvements and New Features</title>
      <list>
        <item>
          <p>
	    The documentation is now built with open source tools
	    (xsltproc and fop) that exists on most platforms. One
	    visible change is that the frames are removed.</p>
          <p>
	    Own Id: OTP-8201</p>
        </item>
      </list>
    </section>

</section>

<section><title>Inviso 0.6</title>
      <section><title>Fixed Bugs and Malfunctions</title>
      <list>
        <item>
          <p>
            In this release the following has been fixed and
            enhanced: Autostart: It is now possible to configure
            modules that shall be loaded by the autostart mechanism.
            This because it is not certain that all application
            systems make use of the OTP boot script to set up paths
            to all Erlang modules. Runtime_tools/Inviso: A bug in the
            fetch_log functionality has been fixed. Further a bug
            that was (supposedly) fixed in a previous patch
            concerning meta-tracer write_ti has been fixed (again) in
            this patch. A bug in inviso_as_lib making remote
            autostart config file updates fail has been fixed.
            Inviso: inviso_tool has been given a flush API.</p>
          <p>
            Own Id: OTP-6918</p>
        </item>
      </list>
   </section>
  
</section>
<section><title>Inviso 0.5</title>

    <section><title>Improvements and New Features</title>
      <list>
        <item>
          <p>
            The following bugs/improvements have been done: Internal
            interworking between inviso_rt and inviso_rt_meta. The
            call function used by inviso_rt to call inviso_rt_meta is
            now protected with a monitor. Inviso_rt_meta now includes
            the timestamp of the incoming meta trace message when
            calling the call-callback. (Makes it possible to add a
            "better" timestamp to the ti-file.) Bug in inviso_tool
            making it not remove trace patterns when terminating. Bug
            in internal function h_start_session making inviso_tool
            crash if there were no active nodes to start the session
            on. The user-inviso_tool and inviso API-inviso control
            component request/response gen_server protocols had
            default time-out. Since many trace operations can be time
            consuming, a longer time-out is necessary. Improved
            overload protection. It is now possible to let the
            overload protection renew itself (e.g after an exit from
            an external overload protector). Inviso_rt_meta now fully
            uses the exception_trace match spec action term. Run
            Trace Case API (as in contrast to activate and deactivate
            trace case APIs) in inviso_tool. Flush trace-port API
            added to inviso. Get_session_data API added to
            inviso_tool. Improved inviso_tool:stop making it possible
            to name nodes which shall not have their trace patterns
            removed when inviso_tool terminates. Bug in handling of
            writing multiple ti-entries if returned from a
            call/return_from call-back in inviso_rt_meta Process
            trace flags are no longer explicitly removed by the
            inviso_tool when it terminates. Not necessary.
            Inviso_tool get_autostart_data adopted to standard
            autostarter.</p>
          <p>
            *** INCOMPATIBILITY with Meta trace call-backs are called
            with different arguments now. ***</p>
          <p>
            Own Id: OTP-6881</p>
        </item>
      </list>
    </section>

</section>
<section><title>Inviso 0.4</title>

    <section><title>Fixed Bugs and Malfunctions</title>
      <list>
        <item>
          <p>
	    A bug in inviso_rt_meta caused an ETS table containing
	    information on initiated (init_tpm) functions to be lost
	    when suspending tracing. Further an enhancement to
	    inviso_rt has been introduced making it possible to
	    activate process trace flags based on globally registered
	    names. It is then not an error to activate a global name
	    on a node where the name does not reside. The process
	    count in the return value will simply be set to zero
	    (hence exactly one node in the NodeResult part of the
	    return value will indicate one matching process found). A
	    bug was found in fetch_log API. At the same time the
	    fetch_log functionality was enhanced to also offer flow
	    control making fetcher processes send chunks of
	    transferred file data at a slower pace.</p>
          <p>
	    Own Id: OTP-6703</p>
        </item>
      </list>
    </section>


    <section><title>Improvements and New Features</title>
      <list>
        <item>
          <p>
	    Minor Makefile changes.</p>
          <p>
	    Own Id: OTP-6689 Aux Id: OTP-6742 </p>
        </item>
      </list>
    </section>

</section>


<section><title>Inviso 0.3</title>

    <section><title>Improvements and New Features</title>
      <list>
        <item>
          <p>
            In this release the first working version of the
            inviso_tool is included. Updates and small bugfixes in
            the inviso application.</p>
          <p>
            Own Id: OTP-6677</p>
        </item>
      </list>
    </section>

</section>
<section><title>Inviso 0.2.1</title>

    <section><title>Improvements and New Features</title>
      <list>
        <item>
          <p>
            Misc improvements.</p>
          <p>
            Own Id: OTP-6576</p>
        </item>
      </list>
    </section>

</section>

<section><title>Inviso 0.2</title>

    <section><title>Fixed Bugs and Malfunctions</title>
      <list>
        <item>
          <p>
            This ticket includes several improvements and bugfixes to
            both runtime_tools and inviso. The overload mechanism can
            now also react to incoming messages. This is useful if
            an external overload watch-dog is used. Some improvements
            of variable bindings has been done to the default
            autostart mechanism - inviso_autostart_server. Autostart
            "jobs" can now be done in parallel, allowing for some
            jobs to hang waiting for some parts of the traced system
            to become ready before proceeding. Previously when using
            named meta-match-specs (tpm_ms) ending up with zero
            match-specs still kept the meta trace pattern active.
            This caused zero match-specs to be equal to unlimited
            meta tracing on that particular function. If the internal
            database becomes empty of meta match specs, meta trace
            pattern is removed for that function. Standard public
            loop data in the inviso runtime meta tracer process is
            now extended to a 2-tuple. The functions ctp/1 and ctpl/1
            are added making it possible to remove trace patterns for
            a list of functions rather than one by one.
            Inviso_rt_meta will now accept a list of binaries to be
            output into the trace information file, in additions to a
            single binary. Further it is also possible to make own
            output to the trace information file using the write_ti/1
            function. An error was discovered in inviso_rt making the
            inviso_rt_meta remain rather than terminate if the
            inviso_rt terminated due to "running alone" (not allowed
            to run without a control component). A new tool,
            inviso_tool, has been added to the inviso application.</p>
          <p>
            Own Id: OTP-6426</p>
        </item>
      </list>
    </section>
    
</section>

  <section>
    <title>Inviso 0.1</title>
    <p>First version.</p>
  </section>

</chapter>

