<?xml version="1.0" encoding="latin1" ?>
<!DOCTYPE fileref SYSTEM "fileref.dtd">

<fileref>
  <header>
    <copyright>
      <year>1997</year>
      <year>2012</year>
      <holder>Ericsson AB, All Rights Reserved</holder>
    </copyright>
    <legalnotice>
  The contents of this file are subject to the Erlang Public License,
  Version 1.1, (the "License"); you may not use this file except in
  compliance with the License. You should have received a copy of the
  Erlang Public License along with this software. If not, it can be
  retrieved online at http://www.erlang.org/.

  Software distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS"
  basis, WITHOUT WARRANTY OF ANY KIND, either express or implied. See
  the License for the specific language governing rights and limitations
  under the License.

  The Initial Developer of the Original Code is Ericsson AB.
    </legalnotice>

    <title>rel</title>
    <prepared></prepared>
    <docno></docno>
    <date></date>
    <rev></rev>
  </header>
  <file>rel</file>
  <filesummary>Release resource file</filesummary>
  <description>
    <p>The <em>release resource file</em> specifies which applications are
      are included in a release (system) based on Erlang/OTP.</p>
    <p>This file is used by the functions in <c>systools</c> when generating
      start scripts (<c>.script</c>, <c>.boot</c>) and release upgrade
      files (<c>relup</c>).</p>
  </description>

  <section>
    <title>FILE SYNTAX</title>
    <p>The release resource file should be called <c>Name.rel</c>.</p>
    <p>The <c>.rel</c> file contains one single Erlang term, which is
      called a <em>release specification</em>.  The file has the
      following syntax:</p>
    <code type="none">
{release, {RelName,Vsn}, {erts, EVsn},
  [{Application, AppVsn} |
   {Application, AppVsn, Type} |
   {Application, AppVsn, IncApps} |
   {Application, AppVsn, Type, IncApps}]}.
    </code>
    <list type="bulleted">
      <item>
        <p><c>RelName = string()</c> is the name of the release.</p>
      </item>
      <item>
        <p><c>Vsn = string()</c> is the version of the release.</p>
      </item>
      <item>
        <p><c>EVsn = string()</c> is the version of ERTS the release is
          intended for.</p>
      </item>
      <item>
        <p><c>Application = atom()</c> is the name of an application
          included in the release.</p>
      </item>
      <item>
        <p><c>AppVsn = string()</c> is the version of an application
          included in the release.</p>
      </item>
      <item>
        <p><c>Type = permanent | transient | temporary | load | none</c>
          is the start type of an application included in the release.</p>
        <p>If <c>Type = permanent | transient | temporary</c>,
          the application will be loaded and started in the corresponding
          way, see <c>application(3)</c>. If <c>Type = load</c>,
          the application will only be loaded. If <c>Type = none</c>,
          the application will be neither loaded nor started, although
          the code for its modules will be loaded.
          Defaults to <c>permanent</c></p>
      </item>
      <item>
        <p><c>IncApps = [atom()]</c> is a list of applications that are
          included by an application included in the release.</p>
        <p>The list must be a subset of the included applications
          specified in the application resource file
          (<c>Application.app</c>) and overrides this value. Defaults
          to the same value as in the application resource file.</p>
      </item>
    </list>
    <note>
      <p>The list of applications must contain the <c>kernel</c> and
        <c>stdlib</c> applications.</p>
    </note>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>SEE ALSO</title>
    <p>application(3), relup(4), systools(3)</p>
  </section>
</fileref>

