<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<!DOCTYPE erlref SYSTEM "erlref.dtd">

<erlref>
  <header>
    <copyright>
      <year>1996</year><year>2016</year>
      <holder>Ericsson AB. All Rights Reserved.</holder>
    </copyright>
    <legalnotice>
      Licensed under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the "License");
      you may not use this file except in compliance with the License.
      You may obtain a copy of the License at
 
          http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0

      Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
      distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,
      WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
      See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
      limitations under the License.
    
    </legalnotice>

    <title>erl_boot_server</title>
    <prepared></prepared>
    <docno></docno>
    <date></date>
    <rev></rev>
  </header>
  <module>erl_boot_server</module>
  <modulesummary>Boot server for other Erlang machines.</modulesummary>
  <description>
    <p>This server is used to assist diskless Erlang nodes that fetch
      all Erlang code from another machine.</p>
    <p>This server is used to fetch all code, including the start
      script, if an Erlang runtime system is started with
      command-line flag <c>-loader inet</c>. All hosts specified
      with command-line flag <c>-hosts Host</c> must have one
      instance of this server running.</p>
    <p>This server can be started with the <c>Kernel</c> configuration
      parameter <c>start_boot_server</c>.</p>
    <p>The <c>erl_boot_server</c> can read regular files and
      files in archives. See <seealso marker="code"><c>code(3)</c></seealso>
      and
    <seealso marker="erts:erl_prim_loader"><c>erl_prim_loader(3)</c></seealso>
    in <c>ERTS</c>.</p>
    <warning><p>The support for loading code from archive files is
     experimental. It is released before it is ready
     to obtain early feedback. The file format, semantics,
     interfaces, and so on, can be changed in a future release.</p></warning>
  </description>
  <funcs>
    <func>
      <name name="add_slave" arity="1"/>
      <fsummary>Add a slave to the list of allowed slaves.</fsummary>
      <desc>
        <p>Adds a <c><anno>Slave</anno></c> node to the list of allowed slave hosts.</p>
      </desc>
    </func>
    <func>
      <name name="delete_slave" arity="1"/>
      <fsummary>Delete a slave from the list of allowed slaves.</fsummary>
      <desc>
        <p>Deletes a <c><anno>Slave</anno></c> node from the list of allowed slave
          hosts.</p>
      </desc>
    </func>
    <func>
      <name name="start" arity="1"/>
      <fsummary>Start the boot server.</fsummary>
      <desc>
        <p>Starts the boot server. <c><anno>Slaves</anno></c> is a list of
          IP addresses for hosts, which are allowed to use this server as a
          boot server.</p>
      </desc>
    </func>
    <func>
      <name name="start_link" arity="1"/>
      <fsummary>Start the boot server and link to the the caller.</fsummary>
      <desc>
        <p>Starts the boot server and links to the caller. This function
          is used to start the server if it is included in a supervision
          tree.</p>
      </desc>
    </func>
    <func>
      <name name="which_slaves" arity="0"/>
      <fsummary>Return the current list of allowed slave hosts.</fsummary>
      <desc>
        <p>Returns the current list of allowed slave hosts.</p>
      </desc>
    </func>
  </funcs>
  <section>
    <title>SEE ALSO</title>
    <p><seealso marker="erts:init"><c>erts:init(3)</c></seealso>,
      <seealso marker="erts:erl_prim_loader"><c>erts:erl_prim_loader(3)</c></seealso></p>
  </section>
</erlref>


