<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<!DOCTYPE erlref SYSTEM "erlref.dtd">

<!-- %ExternalCopyright% -->

<erlref>
  <header>
    <copyright>
      <year>2020</year><year>2020</year>
      <holder>Maxim Fedorov, WhatsApp Inc.</holder>
    </copyright>
    <legalnotice>
      Licensed under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the "License");
      you may not use this file except in compliance with the License.
      You may obtain a copy of the License at

          http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0

      Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
      distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,
      WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
      See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
      limitations under the License.

    </legalnotice>

    <title>pg</title>
    <prepared>maximfca@gmail.com</prepared>
    <responsible></responsible>
    <docno></docno>
    <approved></approved>
    <checked></checked>
    <date></date>
    <rev>A</rev>
    <file>pg.xml</file>
  </header>
  <module since="OTP 23.0">pg</module>
  <modulesummary>Distributed named process groups.</modulesummary>
  <description>
    <p>This module implements process groups. A message can be sent
      to one, some, or all group members.</p>

    <p>Up until OTP 17 there used to exist an experimental <c>pg</c>
      module in <c>stdlib</c>. This <c>pg</c> module is not the same
      module as that experimental <c>pg</c> module, and only share
      the same module name.</p>

    <p>A group of processes can be accessed by a common name. For
      example, if there is a group named <c>foobar</c>, there can be a
      set of processes (which can be located on different nodes) that
      are all members of the group <c>foobar</c>. There are no special
      functions for sending a message to the group. Instead, client
      functions are to be written with the functions
      <seealso marker="#get_members/1"><c>get_members/1</c></seealso> and
      <seealso marker="#get_local_members/1"><c>get_local_members/1</c></seealso>
      to determine which processes are members of the group.
      Then the message can be sent to one or more group members.</p>
    <p>If a member terminates, it is automatically removed from the group.</p>

    <p>A process may join multiple groups. It may join the same group multiple times.
      It is only allowed to join processes running on local node.
    </p>

    <p>Process Groups implement strong eventual consistency.
      Unlike <seealso marker="pg2"><c>pg2</c></seealso>, that provides
      strong ordering guarantees, Process Groups membership view may temporarily
      diverge. For example, when processes on <c>node1</c> and <c>node2</c>
      join concurrently, <c>node3</c> and <c>node4</c> may receive updates in
      a different order.</p>

    <p> Membership view is not transitive. If <c>node1</c> is not directly
      connected to <c>node2</c>, they will not see each other groups. But if
      both are connected to <c>node3</c>, <c>node3</c> will have the full view. </p>

    <p>Groups are automatically created when any process joins,
      and are removed when all processes leave the group. Non-existing group is
      considered empty (containing no processes).</p>

    <p>Process groups can be organised into multiple scopes. Scopes are
      completely independent of each other. A process may join any
      number of groups in any number of scopes. Scopes are designed to
      decouple single mesh into a set of overlay networks, reducing
      amount of traffic required to propagate group membership
      information. Default scope <c>pg</c> is started automatically
      when <seealso marker="kernel_app#start_pg"><c>kernel(6)</c></seealso>
      is configured to do so.
    </p>

    <note><p>
      Scope name is used to register process locally, and to name an ETS table.
      If there is another process registered under this name, or another ETS table
      exists, scope fails to start.</p>
      <p>Local membership is not preserved if scope process exits and
        restarts. This behaviour is different from
        <seealso marker="pg2"><c>pg2</c></seealso>, that recovers
        local membership from remote nodes.
    </p></note>

  </description>

  <datatypes>
    <datatype>
      <name name="group"/>
      <desc><p>The identifier of a process group.</p></desc>
    </datatype>
  </datatypes>

  <funcs>

    <func>
      <name name="start_link" arity="0" since="OTP 23.0"/>
      <fsummary>Start the default <c>pg</c> scope.</fsummary>
      <desc>
        <p>Starts the default <c>pg</c> scope within supervision tree.
          Kernel may be configured to do it automatically, see
          <seealso marker="kernel_app#start_pg"><c>kernel(6)</c></seealso>
          configuration manual.</p>
      </desc>
    </func>

    <func>
      <name name="start" arity="1" since="OTP 23.0"/>
      <name name="start_link" arity="1" since="OTP 23.0"/>
      <fsummary>Start additional scope.</fsummary>
      <desc>
        <p>Starts additional scope.</p>
      </desc>
    </func>

    <func>
      <name name="join" arity="2" since="OTP 23.0"/>
      <name name="join" arity="3" since="OTP 23.0"/>
      <fsummary>Join a process or a list of processes to a group.</fsummary>
      <desc>
        <p>Joins single process or multiple processes to the
          group <c>Name</c>. A process can join a group many times and
          must then leave the group the same number of times.</p>
        <p><c>PidOrPids</c> may contain the same process multiple times.</p>
      </desc>
    </func>

    <func>
      <name name="leave" arity="2" since="OTP 23.0"/>
      <name name="leave" arity="3" since="OTP 23.0"/>
      <fsummary>Make a process leave a group.</fsummary>
      <desc>
        <p>Makes the process <c>PidOrPids</c> leave the group <c>Name</c>.
	  If the process is not a member of the group, <c>not_joined</c> is
	  returned.</p>
        <p>When list of processes is passed as <c>PidOrPids</c>, function
        returns <c>not_joined</c> only when all processes of the list
        are not joined.</p>
      </desc>
    </func>

    <func>
      <name name="get_local_members" arity="1" since="OTP 23.0"/>
      <name name="get_local_members" arity="2" since="OTP 23.0"/>
      <fsummary>Return all local processes in a group.</fsummary>
      <desc>
        <p>Returns all processes running on the local node in the
          group <c>Name</c>. Processes are returned in no specific order.
          This function is optimised for speed.
        </p>
      </desc>
    </func>

    <func>
      <name name="get_members" arity="1" since="OTP 23.0"/>
      <name name="get_members" arity="2" since="OTP 23.0"/>
      <fsummary>Return all processes in a group.</fsummary>
      <desc>
        <p>Returns all processes in the group <c>Name</c>.
          Processes are returned in no specific order.
          This function is optimised for speed.</p>
      </desc>
    </func>

    <func>
      <name name="which_groups" arity="0" since="OTP 23.0"/>
      <name name="which_groups" arity="1" since="OTP 23.0"/>
      <fsummary>Return a list of all known groups.</fsummary>
      <desc>
        <p>Returns a list of all known groups.</p>
      </desc>
    </func>

  </funcs>

  <section>
    <title>See Also</title>
    <p><seealso marker="kernel_app"><c>kernel(6)</c></seealso></p>
  </section>
</erlref>

