<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<!DOCTYPE erlref SYSTEM "erlref.dtd">

<erlref>
  <header>
    <copyright>
      <year>2003</year><year>2016</year>
      <holder>Ericsson AB. All Rights Reserved.</holder>
    </copyright>
    <legalnotice>
      Licensed under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the "License");
      you may not use this file except in compliance with the License.
      You may obtain a copy of the License at
 
          http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0

      Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
      distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,
      WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
      See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
      limitations under the License.
    
    </legalnotice>

    <title>Erlang mode for Emacs</title>
    <prepared>Ingela Anderton</prepared>
    <responsible></responsible>
    <docno></docno>
    <date></date>
    <rev></rev>
  </header>
  <module>erlang.el</module>
  <modulesummary>Erlang mode for Emacs </modulesummary>
  <description>
    <p>Possibly the most important feature of an editor designed for
      programmers is the ability to indent a line of code in accordance
      with the structure of the programming language. The Erlang mode
      does, of course, provide this feature.  The layout used is based
      on the common use of the language. The mode also provides things as
      syntax highlighting, electric commands, module name verification,
      comment support including paragraph filling, skeletons, tags
      support etc.</p>
    <p>In the following descriptions the use of the word <em>Point</em> means: "Point can be seen as the position of the
      cursor. More precisely, the point is the position between two
      characters while the cursor is drawn over the character
      following the point".</p>
  </description>

  <section>
    <title>Indent</title>
    <p>The following command are directly available for indentation.</p>
    <list type="bulleted">
      <item><em><c>TAB</c></em> (<c>erlang-indent-command</c>) -
       Indents the current line of code. </item>
      <item><em><c>M-C-\</c></em> (<c>indent-region</c>) - Indents all
       lines in the region. </item>
      <item><em><c>M-l</c></em> (<c>indent-for-comment</c>) - Insert a
       comment character to the right of the code on the line (if
       any).</item>
    </list>
    <p>Lines containing comment are indented differently depending on
      the number of %-characters used: </p>
    <list type="bulleted">
      <item>Lines with one %-character is indented to the right of
       the code. The column is specified by the variable
      <c>comment-column</c>, by default column 48 is used.</item>
      <item>Lines with two %-characters will be indented to the same
       depth as code would have been in the same situation. </item>
      <item>Lines with three of more %-characters are indented to the
       left margin.</item>
      <item><em><c>C-c C-q</c></em> (<c>erlang-indent-function</c>) -
       Indents the current Erlang function. </item>
      <item><em><c>M-x erlang-indent-clause RET</c></em>      <br></br>
 -Indent the
       current Erlang clause.</item>
      <item><em><c>M-x erlang-indent-current-buffer RET</c></em> -
       Indent the entire buffer. </item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Edit - Fill Comment </title>
    <p>When editing normal text in text mode you can let Emacs reformat the
      text by the <c>fill-paragraph</c> command.  This command will not work
      for comments since it will treat the comment characters as words.</p>
    <p>The Erlang editing mode provides a command that knows about the
      Erlang comment structure and can be used to fill text paragraphs
      in comments. Ex:</p>
    <code type="none">
      %% This is   just a very simple test to show
      %% how the Erlang fill
      %% paragraph   command works.</code>
    <p>Clearly, the text is badly formatted.  Instead of formatting this
      paragraph line by line, let's try <c>erlang-fill-paragraph</c> by
      pressing <em><c>M-q</c></em>. The result is:</p>
    <code type="none">
      %% This is just a very simple test to show how the Erlang fill
      %% paragraph command works.</code>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Edit - Comment/Uncomment Region </title>
    <p><em><c>C-c C-c</c></em> will put comment characters at the
      beginning of all lines in a marked region. If you want to have
      two comment characters instead of one you can do <em><c>C-u 2 C-c C-c</c></em></p>
    <p><em><c>C-c C-u</c></em> will undo a comment-region command. </p>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Edit - Moving the marker </title>
    <list type="bulleted">
      <item><em><c>C-a M-a </c></em>
       (<c>erlang-beginning-of-function</c>) - Move the point to the
       beginning of the current or preceding Erlang function.  With an
       numeric argument (ex <em><c>C-u 2 C-a M-a</c></em>) the function
       skips backwards over this many Erlang functions. Should the
       argument be negative the point is moved to the beginning of a
       function below the current function. </item>
      <item><em><c>M-C-a </c></em> (<c>erlang-beginning-of-clause</c>) - As
       above but move point to the beginning of the current or
       preceding Erlang clause.</item>
      <item><em><c>C-a M-e </c></em> (<c>erlang-end-of-function</c>)
       - Move to the end of the current or following Erlang function.  With
       an numeric argument (ex <em><c>C-u 2 C-a M-e</c></em>) the function
       skips backwards over this many Erlang functions. Should the argument
       be negative the point is moved to the end of a function below
       the current function.</item>
      <item><em><c>M-C-e </c></em> (<c>erlang-end-of-clause</c>) - As above
       but move point to the end of the current or following Erlang
       clause.</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Edit - Marking </title>
    <list type="bulleted">
      <item><em><c>C-c M-h</c></em> (<c>erlang-mark-function</c>) - Put the
       region around the current Erlang function.  The point is
       placed in the beginning and the mark at the end of the
       function.</item>
      <item><em><c>M-C-h </c></em> (<c>erlang-mark-clause</c>) Put the region
       around the current Erlang clause.  The point is placed in the
       beginning and the mark at the end of the function. </item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Edit - Function Header Commands </title>
    <list type="bulleted">
      <item><em><c>C-c C-j</c></em> (<c>erlang-generate-new-clause</c>) -
       Create a new clause in the current Erlang function. The point is
       placed between the parentheses of the argument list.</item>
      <item><em><c>C-c C-y</c></em> (<c>erlang-clone-arguments</c>) -
       Copy the function arguments of the preceding Erlang clause. This
       command is useful when defining a new clause with almost the same
       argument as the preceding.</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Edit - Arrows</title>
    <list type="bulleted">
      <item>
        <p><em><c>C-c C-a</c></em> (<c>erlang-align-arrows</c>) -
          aligns arrows after clauses inside a region.</p>
        <code type="none">
        Example:
        
        sum(L) -> sum(L, 0).
        sum([H|T], Sum) -> sum(T, Sum + H);
        sum([], Sum) -> Sum.
        
        becomes:
        
        sum(L)          -> sum(L, 0).
        sum([H|T], Sum) -> sum(T, Sum + H);
        sum([], Sum)    -> Sum.</code>
      </item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Syntax highlighting</title>
    <p>The syntax highlighting can be activated from the Erlang menu. There
      are four different alternatives:</p>
    <list type="bulleted">
      <item>Off: Normal black and white display.
      </item>
      <item>Level 1: Function headers, reserved words, comments,
       strings, quoted atoms, and character constants will be
       colored. </item>
      <item>Level 2: The above, attributes, Erlang bif:s, guards, and
       words in comments enclosed in single quotes will be colored.</item>
      <item>Level 3: The above, variables, records, and macros will
       be colored. (This level is also known as the Christmas tree
       level.) </item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Tags</title>
    <p>For the tag commands to work it requires that you have
      generated a tag file. See <seealso marker="erlang_mode_chapter#tags">Erlang mode users guide</seealso></p>
    <p></p>
    <list type="bulleted">
      <item><em><c>M-. </c></em> (<c>find-tag</c>) -
       Find a function definition. The default value is the function name
       under the point.  </item>
      <item>Find Tag (<c>erlang-find-tag</c>) - Like the Elisp-function
       `find-tag'. Capable of retrieving Erlang modules. Tags can be
       given on the forms `tag', `module:', `module:tag'.</item>
      <item><em><c>M-+</c></em> (<c>erlang-find-next-tag</c>) - Find the
       next occurrence of tag.</item>
      <item><em><c>M-TAB</c></em> (<c>erlang-complete-tag</c>) -
       Perform completion on the tag entered in a tag search.
       Completes to the set of names listed in the current tags table.</item>
      <item>Tags aprops (<c>tags-apropos</c>) - Display list of all tags in
       tags table REGEXP matches. </item>
      <item><em><c>C-x t s</c></em> (<c>tags-search</c>) - Search
       through all files listed in tags table for match for REGEXP.
       Stops when a match is found.</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Skeletons</title>
    <p>A skeleton is a piece of pre-written code that can be inserted into
      the buffer. Erlang mode comes with a set of predefined skeletons.
      The skeletons can be accessed either from the Erlang menu of
      from commands named <c>tempo-template-erlang-*</c>, as the
      skeletons is defined using the standard Emacs package "tempo".
      Here follows a brief description of the available skeletons:</p>
    <list type="bulleted">
      <item>Simple skeletons: If, Case, Receive, Receive After,
       Receive Loop - Basic code constructs.
      </item>
      <item>Header elements: Module, Author - These commands insert
       lines on the form <c>-module(</c>xxx<c>).  </c> and
      <c>-author('my@home').</c>. They can be used directly, but are
       also used as part of the full headers described below.</item>
      <item>Full Headers: Small (minimum requirement), Medium (with
       fields for basic information about the module), and Large
       Header (medium header with some extra layout structure).</item>
      <item>Small Server - skeleton for a simple server not using
       OTP.</item>
      <item>Application - skeletons for the OTP application
       behavior</item>
      <item>Supervisor - skeleton for the OTP supervisor behavior</item>
      <item>Supervisor Bridge - skeleton for the OTP supervisor bridge
       behavior </item>
      <item>gen_server - skeleton for the OTP gen_server
       behavior</item>
      <item>gen_event - skeleton for the OTP gen_event behavior</item>
      <item>gen_fsm - skeleton for the OTP gen_fsm behavior</item>
      <item>gen_statem - skeleton for the OTP gen_statem behavior</item>
      <item>Library module - skeleton for a module that does not
       implement a process.</item>
      <item>Corba callback - skeleton for a Corba callback module.</item>
      <item>Erlang test suite - skeleton for a callback module
       for the erlang test server.</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Shell</title>
    <list type="bulleted">
      <item>New shell (<c>erlang-shell</c>) - Starts a new Erlang shell.</item>
      <item><em><c>C-c C-z,</c></em> (<c>erlang-shell-display </c>) -
       Displays an Erlang shell, or starts a new one if there is no shell
       started.</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Compile</title>
    <list type="bulleted">
      <item><em><c>C-c C-k,</c></em> (<c>erlang-compile</c>) -
       Compiles the Erlang module in the current buffer.
       You can also use <em><c>C-u C-c C-k</c></em>
       to debug compile the module with the debug options
      <c>debug_info</c> and <c>export_all</c>.</item>
      <item><em><c>C-c C-l,</c></em> (<c>erlang-compile-display</c>) -
       Display compilation output.</item>
      <item><em><c>C-u C-x`</c></em> Start parsing the compiler output from the
       beginning. This command will place the point on the line where
       the first error was found.</item>
      <item><em><c>C-x`</c></em> (<c>erlang-next-error</c>) - Move the
       point on to the next error. The buffer displaying the
       compilation errors will be updated so that the current error
       will be visible.</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Man</title>
    <p>On unix you can view the manual pages in emacs.
      In order to find the manual pages, the variable `erlang-root-dir'
      should be bound to the name of the directory containing the Erlang
      installation.  The name should not include the final slash.
      Practically, you should add a line on the following form to
      your ~/.emacs,</p>
    <code type="none">
      (setq erlang-root-dir "/the/erlang/root/dir/goes/here")</code>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Starting IMenu</title>
    <list type="bulleted">
      <item><em><c>M-x imenu-add-to-menubar RET</c></em> - This
       command will create the IMenu menu containing all the functions
       in the current buffer.The command will ask you for a suitable
       name for the menu. Not supported by Xemacs.</item>
    </list>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Version</title>
    <list type="bulleted">
      <item><em><c>M-x erlang-version RET</c></em> -
       This command displays the version number of the Erlang editing mode.
       Remember to always supply the version number when asking questions
       about the Erlang mode.</item>
    </list>
  </section>
</erlref>

