<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter SYSTEM "chapter.dtd">

<chapter>
  <header>
    <copyright>
      <year>2006</year><year>2016</year>
      <holder>Ericsson AB. All Rights Reserved.</holder>
    </copyright>
    <legalnotice>
      Licensed under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the "License");
      you may not use this file except in compliance with the License.
      You may obtain a copy of the License at
 
          http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0

      Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
      distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,
      WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
      See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
      limitations under the License.
    
    </legalnotice>

    <title>Tools Release Notes</title>
    <prepared></prepared>
    <docno></docno>
    <date></date>
    <rev></rev>
  </header>

  <section>
    <title>Tools 2.4</title>

    <section>
      <title>Fixed Bugs and Malfunctions</title>
      <list type="bulleted">
        <item>
          <p>The Erlang Emacs mode now properly handles strings that
            have $ or ^ as the last character.</p>
          <p>Own Id: OTP-4697</p>
        </item>
        <item>
          <p><c>xref</c>: The unresolved arity (-1) is now recognized
            in analyses and queries.</p>
          <p>Own Id: OTP-4778</p>
        </item>
        <item>
          <p><c>cover</c> does no longer hang if an interface function
            is called on a remote node - it returns
            <c>{error,not_main_node}</c>.</p>
          <p>Own Id: OTP-5031</p>
        </item>
        <item>
          <p><c>fprof</c>: Time spent in the last function in a chain,
            i.e. a function which did not call another function, and
            the time when a process was scheduled out, was charged on
            the above function. This resulted in own time in many
            cases being bigger than acc time since the time a process
            was scheduled out was charged on the function from which
            the process was scheduled out. This is now corrected.</p>
          <p>Own Id: OTP-5073</p>
        </item>
        <item>
          <p>Previous patch from open source messed up \M-q so part of
            that patch was backed out.</p>
          <p>Own Id: OTP-5074</p>
        </item>
        <item>
          <p><c>cover</c>: Added "Exclude Included Functions". If
            "real code" is included in a modules which is cover
            compiled, there will be no bumps for lines in the
            included file. Earlier this would cause faulty bumps for
            lines in the module, i.e. if the code was on line 4 in
            the included file it would produce a bump for line 4 in
            the module. Lines in included files are now just
            disregarded.</p>
          <p>Own Id: OTP-5122</p>
        </item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Improvements and New Features</title>
      <list type="bulleted">
        <item>
          <p>Added support for try-catch to the Erlang mode for Emacs.
            However there are still some known problems with some of
            the more advanced variants especially including separate
            of-clauses.</p>
          <p>Own Id: OTP-4594</p>
        </item>
        <item>
          <p>Improvments for support of Emacs 21 contributed by Dave
            Love. The bulk of the changes are actually cosmetic
            commentary/doc fixes. The significant ones make it play
            better with Emacs 21 with up-to-date facilities. In
            particular, support for compilation error messages from
            an inferior erl (as opposed to batch compilation) works
            in the released Emacs 21, and currently with the
            development Emacs.</p>
          <p>Own Id: OTP-5019</p>
        </item>
        <item>
          <p>Added a skeletons for an Erlang test-suite for both the
            ts-frontend and the ct-frontend (this frontend is
            Ericsson internal). Also altered some of the old
            skeletons to get a uniform look and feel.</p>
          <p>Own Id: OTP-5058</p>
        </item>
        <item>
          <p>The Erlang mode for Emacs now supports the new guard
            <c>is_boolean</c>.</p>
          <p>Own Id: OTP-5059</p>
        </item>
        <item>
          <p><c>cover</c>: Adjustments to handle new syntax of
            try-catch.</p>
          <p>Own Id: OTP-5154</p>
        </item>
      </list>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Tools 2.3</title>

    <section>
      <title>Fixed Bugs and Malfunctions</title>
      <list type="bulleted">
        <item>
          <p>Totally rewritten the interface for WebCover. Can now
            compile both <c>.erl</c> and <c>.beam</c> files and
            export/import cover data.</p>
          <p>Own Id: OTP-4706</p>
        </item>
        <item>
          <p><c>cover</c> does no longer report coverage on lines which
            are not executed.</p>
          <p>Own Id: OTP-4734</p>
        </item>
        <item>
          <p>Erlang mode for Emacs: Fixed so that the generation of new
            function clauses works also for guarded functions.</p>
          <p>Own Id: OTP-3697</p>
        </item>
        <item>
          <p>Erlang mode for Emacs: Fixed so that you do not get
            the error message "unbalanced parenthesis" when indenting
            correct code including bit syntax.</p>
          <p>Own Id: OTP-4526</p>
        </item>
        <item>
          <p>Erlang mode for Emacs: The guard <c>function</c> is now
            colored.</p>
          <p>Own Id: OTP-4533</p>
        </item>
        <item>
          <p>Erlang mode for Emacs: Indentation of macros is handled
            correctly in all cases.</p>
          <p>Own Id: OTP-4561, OTP-4687</p>
        </item>
        <item>
          <p><c>is_*</c> guards are now colored.</p>
          <p>Own Id: OTP-4562</p>
        </item>
        <item>
          <p>Erlang mode for Emacs: Now handles the fact that a function
            argument may be a guard expression. (That is useful when
            writing test case code.)</p>
          <p>Own Id: OTP-4579</p>
        </item>
        <item>
          <p>Erlang mode for Emacs: Keywords <c>andalso</c> and
            <c>orelse</c> are now colored.</p>
          <p>Own Id: OTP-4580</p>
        </item>
        <item>
          <p>Erlang mode for Emacs: Fixed bug in function that calculates
            the arity of an Erlang function.</p>
          <p>Own Id: OTP-4581</p>
        </item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Improvements and New Features</title>
      <list type="bulleted">
        <item>
          <p>Added functions <c>cover:start(Nodes)</c> and
            <c>cover:stop(Nodes)</c>. Cover compiled modules will be
            loaded on all nodes added with <c>cover:start(Nodes)</c>.
            <c>cover:stop(Nodes)</c> will collect coverage data from
            the stopped nodes and merge it with data collected on
            the main (controller) node.</p>
          <p><c>cover:analyse/1,2,3</c> and
            <c>cover:analyse_to_file/1,2,3</c> will also collect data
            from all nodes before analysing.</p>
          <p>Own Id: OTP-4177</p>
        </item>
        <item>
          <p>The module attribute tag <c>deprecated</c> is used by
            <c>xref</c> to find calls to deprecated functions.
            The <c>m/1</c>, <c>d/1</c>, and <c>analyze/2,3</c> functions
            have been updated to return calls to deprecated functions.
            See also <c>xref(3)</c> for more details.</p>
          <p>Own Id: OTP-4695</p>
        </item>
        <item>
          <p>Added functions <c>cover:compile_beam/1</c> and
            <c>cover:compile_beam_directory/0,1</c>. These functions use
            abstract code from existing beam files when cover compiling.</p>
          <p>Added option <c>html</c> to
            <c>cover:analyse_to_file/1,2,3</c>. Instead of plain text,
            a HTML file is generated with all uncovered lines colored
            red.</p>
          <p>Added functions <c>cover:export/1,2</c> and
            <c>cover:import/1</c>. These functions can be used to export
            current coverage data to a file, and then import the data
            in a later session. Data can be exported for one single
            module or for all currently cover compiled modules.</p>
          <p>Own Id: OTP-4702</p>
        </item>
        <item>
          <p>Erlang mode for Emacs: Added function
            <c>erlang-align-arrows</c>.</p>
          <p>Own Id: OTP-4737</p>
        </item>
        <item>
          <p>The interface for the <c>instrument</c> module has been
            slightly changed. Also some new functionality has been
            added. See <c>instrument(3)</c> for more information.</p>
          <p>(*** POTENTIAL INCOMPATIBILITY ***)</p>
          <p>Own Id: OTP-4761            <br></br>

            Aux Id: OTP-4534</p>
        </item>
      </list>
    </section>
  </section>
</chapter>

