<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<!DOCTYPE part SYSTEM "part.dtd">

<part xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <header>
    <copyright>
      <year>1996</year><year>2016</year>
      <holder>Ericsson AB. All Rights Reserved.</holder>
    </copyright>
    <legalnotice>
      Licensed under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the "License");
      you may not use this file except in compliance with the License.
      You may obtain a copy of the License at
 
          http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0

      Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
      distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,
      WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
      See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
      limitations under the License.

    </legalnotice>

    <title>Tools User's Guide</title>
    <prepared></prepared>
    <docno></docno>
    <date></date>
    <rev></rev>
  </header>
  <description>
    <p>The <em>Tools</em> application contains a number of stand-alone
      tools, which are useful when developing Erlang programs.</p>
    <taglist>
      <tag><em>cover</em></tag>
      <item>A coverage analysis tool for Erlang.</item>
      <tag><em>cprof</em></tag>
      <item>A profiling tool that shows how many
       times each function is called. Uses a kind of local call trace
       breakpoints containing counters to achieve very low runtime
       performance degradation.</item>
      <tag><em>emacs - (erlang.el and erlang-start.el)</em></tag>
      <item>This package provides support
       for the programming language Erlang in Emacs. The package provides an
       editing mode with lots of bells and whistles, compilation
       support, and it makes it possible for the user to start Erlang
       shells that run inside Emacs.</item>
      <tag><em>eprof</em></tag>
      <item>A time profiling tool; measure how time is used in Erlang
       programs. Erlang programs. Predecessor of <em>fprof</em> (see below).</item>
      <tag><em>fprof</em></tag>
      <item>Another Erlang profiler; measure how time is used in your
       Erlang programs. Uses trace to file to minimize runtime
       performance impact, and displays time for calling and called 
       functions.</item>
      <tag><em>instrument</em></tag>
      <item>Utility functions for obtaining and analysing resource usage
       in an instrumented Erlang runtime system.</item>
      <tag><em>lcnt</em></tag>
      <item>A lock profiling tool for the Erlang runtime system.</item>
      <tag><em>make</em></tag>
      <item>A make utility for Erlang similar to UNIX make.</item>
      <tag><em>tags</em></tag>
      <item>A tool for generating Emacs TAGS files from Erlang source
       files.</item>
      <tag><em>xref</em></tag>
      <item>A cross reference tool. Can be used to check dependencies 
       between functions, modules, applications and releases.</item>
    </taglist>
  </description>
  <xi:include href="cover_chapter.xml"/>
  <xi:include href="cprof_chapter.xml"/>
  <xi:include href="erlang_mode_chapter.xml"/>
  <xi:include href="fprof_chapter.xml"/>
  <xi:include href="lcnt_chapter.xml"/>
  <xi:include href="xref_chapter.xml"/>
</part>

