<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<!DOCTYPE erlref SYSTEM "erlref.dtd">

<!-- THIS FILE IS GENERATED DO NOT EDIT -->


<erlref>
<header>
  <copyright>
    <year>2020</year>
    <holder>wxWidgets team.</holder></copyright>
  <legalnotice>Licensed under the wxWindows Free Documentation Licence, Version 3
  </legalnotice>
  <title>wxClipboardTextEvent</title>
</header>
<module>wxClipboardTextEvent</module>
<modulesummary>Functions for wxClipboardTextEvent class</modulesummary>
<description><p>This class represents the events generated by a control (typically a <seeerl marker="wxTextCtrl"><c>wxTextCtrl</c></seeerl> but other windows can generate these events as well) when its content gets copied or cut to, or pasted from the clipboard.
      </p><p>There are three types of corresponding events <c>wxEVT_TEXT_COPY</c>, <c>wxEVT_TEXT_CUT</c> and <c>wxEVT_TEXT_PASTE</c>.
      </p><p>If any of these events is processed (without being skipped) by an event handler, the corresponding operation doesn't take place which allows preventing the text from being copied from or pasted to a control. It is also possible to examine the clipboard contents in the PASTE event handler and transform it in some way before inserting in a control - for example, changing its case or removing invalid characters.
      </p><p>Finally notice that a CUT event is always preceded by the COPY event which makes it possible to only process the latter if it doesn't matter if the text was copied or cut.
      </p><p>Note: These events are currently only generated by <seeerl marker="wxTextCtrl"><c>wxTextCtrl</c></seeerl> in wxGTK and wxOSX but are also generated by <seeerl marker="wxComboBox"><c>wxComboBox</c></seeerl> without wxCB_READONLY style in wxMSW.
      </p><p>See: <seeerl marker="wxClipboard"><c>wxClipboard</c></seeerl>
      </p>
  <p>This class is derived (and can use functions) from: 
    <seeerl marker="wxCommandEvent"><c>wxCommandEvent</c></seeerl> <seeerl marker="wxEvent"><c>wxEvent</c></seeerl></p>
  
  <p>wxWidgets docs: <url href="https://docs.wxwidgets.org/3.1/classwx_clipboard_text_event.html">wxClipboardTextEvent</url></p>
  </description><section><title>Events</title><p>Use <seemfa marker="wxEvtHandler#connect/3"><c>wxEvtHandler:connect/3</c></seemfa> with <seetype marker="#wxClipboardTextEventType"><c>wxClipboardTextEventType</c></seetype> to subscribe to events of this type.</p></section>
<datatypes>
    <datatype><name name="wxClipboardTextEvent"/></datatype>
    <datatype><name name="wxClipboardText"/></datatype>
    <datatype><name name="wxClipboardTextEventType"/></datatype></datatypes>

</erlref>
