<?xml version="1.0" encoding="latin1" ?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter SYSTEM "chapter.dtd">

<chapter>
  <header>
    <copyright>
      <year>2000</year><year>2009</year>
      <holder>Ericsson AB. All Rights Reserved.</holder>
    </copyright>
    <legalnotice>
      The contents of this file are subject to the Erlang Public License,
      Version 1.1, (the "License"); you may not use this file except in
      compliance with the License. You should have received a copy of the
      Erlang Public License along with this software. If not, it can be
      retrieved online at http://www.erlang.org/.
    
      Software distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS"
      basis, WITHOUT WARRANTY OF ANY KIND, either express or implied. See
      the License for the specific language governing rights and limitations
      under the License.
    
    </legalnotice>

    <title>Introduction to cosTime</title>
    <prepared>Niclas Eklund</prepared>
    <docno></docno>
    <date>2000-01-31</date>
    <rev></rev>
    <file>ch_introduction.xml</file>
  </header>

  <section>
    <title>Overview</title>
    <p>The cosTime application is Time and TimerEvent Services compliant with the <url href="http://www.omg.org">OMG</url> 
      Services CosTime and CosTimerEvent.
      </p>

    <section>
      <title>Purpose and Dependencies</title>
      <p>This application use <c>calender:now_to_universal_time(Now)</c> to create a 
        UTC. Hence, the underlying OS must deliver a correct result when calling 
        <c>erlang:now()</c>.</p>
      <p><em>cosTime</em> is dependent on  <em>Orber</em>, which provides CORBA functionality in an Erlang environment.</p>
      <p><em>cosTimerEvent</em> is dependent on  <em>Orber</em> and <em>cosNotification</em>, 
        which provides CORBA functionality and Event handling in an Erlang environment.</p>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Prerequisites</title>
      <p>To fully understand the concepts presented in the
        documentation, it is recommended that the user is familiar
        with distributed programming, CORBA, the Orber and cosNotification applications.
        </p>
      <p>Recommended reading includes <em>CORBA, Fundamentals and Programming - Jon Siegel</em> and <em>Open Telecom Platform Documentation Set</em>. It is also helpful to  have read <em>Concurrent Programming in Erlang</em>.</p>
    </section>
  </section>
</chapter>

