<?xml version="1.0" encoding="latin1" ?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter SYSTEM "chapter.dtd">

<chapter>
  <header>
    <copyright>
      <year>2004</year><year>2013</year>
      <holder>Ericsson AB. All Rights Reserved.</holder>
    </copyright>
    <legalnotice>
      The contents of this file are subject to the Erlang Public License,
      Version 1.1, (the "License"); you may not use this file except in
      compliance with the License. You should have received a copy of the
      Erlang Public License along with this software. If not, it can be
      retrieved online at http://www.erlang.org/.
    
      Software distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS"
      basis, WITHOUT WARRANTY OF ANY KIND, either express or implied. See
      the License for the specific language governing rights and limitations
      under the License.
    
    </legalnotice>

    <title>Ports and Port Drivers</title>
    <prepared></prepared>
    <docno></docno>
    <date></date>
    <rev></rev>
    <file>ports.xml</file>
  </header>
  <p>Examples of how to use ports and port drivers can be found in
    <em>Interoperability Tutorial</em>. The BIFs mentioned are as usual
    documented in <c>erlang(3)</c>.</p>

  <section>
    <title>Ports</title>
    <p><em>Ports</em> provide the basic mechanism for communication
      with the external world, from Erlang's point of view. They
      provide a byte-oriented interface to an external program. When a
      port has been created, Erlang can communicate with it by sending
      and receiving lists of bytes, including binaries.</p>
    <p>The Erlang process which creates a port is said to be
      the <em>port owner</em>, or the <em>connected process</em> of
      the port. All communication to and from the port should go via
      the port owner. If the port owner terminates, so will the port
      (and the external program, if it is written correctly).</p>
    <p>The external program resides in another OS process. By default,
      it should read from standard input (file descriptor 0) and write
      to standard output (file descriptor 1). The external program
      should terminate when the port is closed.</p>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Port Drivers</title>
    <p>It is also possible to write a driver in C according to certain
      principles and dynamically link it to the Erlang runtime system.
      The linked-in driver looks like a port from the Erlang
      programmer's point of view and is called a <em>port driver</em>.</p>
    <warning>
      <p>An erroneous port driver will cause the entire Erlang runtime
        system to leak memory, hang or crash.</p>
    </warning>
    <p>Port drivers are documented in <c>erl_driver(4)</c>,
      <c>driver_entry(1)</c> and <c>erl_ddll(3)</c>.</p>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Port BIFs</title>
    <p>To create a port:</p>
    <table>
      <row>
        <cell align="left" valign="middle"><c>open_port(PortName, PortSettings</c></cell>
        <cell align="left" valign="middle">Returns a port identifier <c>Port</c>as the result of opening a new Erlang port. Messages can be sent to and received from a port identifier, just like a pid. Port identifiers can also be linked to or registered under a name using <c>link/1</c>and <c>register/2</c>.</cell>
      </row>
      <tcaption>Port Creation BIF.</tcaption>
    </table>
    <p><c>PortName</c> is usually a tuple <c>{spawn,Command}</c>, where
      the string <c>Command</c> is the name of the external program.
      The external program runs outside the Erlang workspace unless a
      port driver with the name <c>Command</c> is found. If found, that
      driver is started.</p>
    <p><c>PortSettings</c> is a list of settings (options) for the port.
      The list typically contains at least a tuple <c>{packet,N}</c>
      which specifies that data sent between the port and the external
      program are preceded by an N-byte length indicator. Valid values
      for N are 1, 2 or 4. If binaries should be used instead of lists
      of bytes, the option <c>binary</c> must be included.</p>
    <p>The port owner <c>Pid</c> can communicate with the port
      <c>Port</c> by sending and receiving messages. (In fact, any
      process can send the messages to the port, but the port owner must
      be identified in the message).</p>
    <p>As of OTP-R16 messages sent to ports are delivered truly
      asynchronously. The underlying implementation previously
      delivered messages to ports synchronously. Message passing has
      however always been documented as an asynchronous operation, so
      this should not be an issue for an Erlang program communicating
      with ports, unless false assumptions about ports has been made.</p>
    <p>Below, <c>Data</c> must be an I/O list. An I/O list is a binary
      or a (possibly deep) list of binaries or integers in the range
      0..255.</p>
    <table>
      <row>
        <cell align="left" valign="middle"><c>{Pid,{command,Data}}</c></cell>
        <cell align="left" valign="middle">Sends <c>Data</c>to the port.</cell>
      </row>
      <row>
        <cell align="left" valign="middle"><c>{Pid,close}</c></cell>
        <cell align="left" valign="middle">Closes the port. Unless the port is already closed, the port replies with <c>{Port,closed}</c>when all buffers have been flushed and the port really closes.</cell>
      </row>
      <row>
        <cell align="left" valign="middle"><c>{Pid,{connect,NewPid}}</c></cell>
        <cell align="left" valign="middle">Sets the port owner of <c>Port</c>to <c>NewPid</c>. Unless the port is already closed, the port replies with<c>{Port,connected}</c>to the old port owner. Note that the old port owner is still linked to the port, but the new port owner is not.</cell>
      </row>
      <tcaption>Messages Sent To a Port.</tcaption>
    </table>
    <table>
      <row>
        <cell align="left" valign="middle"><c>{Port,{data,Data}}</c></cell>
        <cell align="left" valign="middle"><c>Data</c>is received from the external program.</cell>
      </row>
      <row>
        <cell align="left" valign="middle"><c>{Port,closed}</c></cell>
        <cell align="left" valign="middle">Reply to <c>Port ! {Pid,close}</c>.</cell>
      </row>
      <row>
        <cell align="left" valign="middle"><c>{Port,connected}</c></cell>
        <cell align="left" valign="middle">Reply to <c>Port ! {Pid,{connect,NewPid}}</c></cell>
      </row>
      <row>
        <cell align="left" valign="middle"><c>{'EXIT',Port,Reason}</c></cell>
        <cell align="left" valign="middle">If the port has terminated for some reason.</cell>
      </row>
      <tcaption>Messages Received From a Port.</tcaption>
    </table>
    <p>Instead of sending and receiving messages, there are also a
      number of BIFs that can be used.</p>
    <table>
      <row>
        <cell align="left" valign="middle"><c>port_command(Port,Data)</c></cell>
        <cell align="left" valign="middle">Sends <c>Data</c>to the port.</cell>
      </row>
      <row>
        <cell align="left" valign="middle"><c>port_close(Port)</c></cell>
        <cell align="left" valign="middle">Closes the port.</cell>
      </row>
      <row>
        <cell align="left" valign="middle"><c>port_connect(Port,NewPid)</c></cell>
        <cell align="left" valign="middle">Sets the port owner of <c>Port</c>to <c>NewPid</c>. The old port owner <c>Pid</c>stays linked to the port and have to call <c>unlink(Port)</c>if this is not desired.</cell>
      </row>
      <row>
        <cell align="left" valign="middle"><c>erlang:port_info(Port,Item)</c></cell>
        <cell align="left" valign="middle">Returns information as specified by <c>Item</c>.</cell>
      </row>
      <row>
        <cell align="left" valign="middle"><c>erlang:ports()</c></cell>
        <cell align="left" valign="middle">Returns a list of all ports on the current node.</cell>
      </row>
      <tcaption>Port BIFs.</tcaption>
    </table>
    <p>There are some additional BIFs that only apply to port drivers:
      <c>port_control/3</c> and <c>erlang:port_call/3</c>.</p>
  </section>
</chapter>

