<?xml version="1.0" encoding="latin1" ?>
<!DOCTYPE erlref SYSTEM "erlref.dtd">

<erlref>
  <header>
    <copyright>
      <year>2002</year>
      <year>2011</year>
      <holder>Ericsson AB, All Rights Reserved</holder>
    </copyright>
    <legalnotice>
  The contents of this file are subject to the Erlang Public License,
  Version 1.1, (the "License"); you may not use this file except in
  compliance with the License. You should have received a copy of the
  Erlang Public License along with this software. If not, it can be
  retrieved online at http://www.erlang.org/.

  Software distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS"
  basis, WITHOUT WARRANTY OF ANY KIND, either express or implied. See
  the License for the specific language governing rights and limitations
  under the License.

  The Initial Developer of the Original Code is Ericsson AB.
    </legalnotice>

    <title>CosEventDomainAdmin</title>
    <prepared>Niclas Eklund</prepared>
    <responsible>Niclas Eklund</responsible>
    <docno></docno>
    <approved>Niclas Eklund</approved>
    <checked></checked>
    <date>2001-08-20</date>
    <rev>PA1</rev>
  </header>
  <module>CosEventDomainAdmin</module>
  <modulesummary>This module export functions which return QoS and Admin Properties constants.</modulesummary>
  <description>
    <p>To get access to all definitions include necessary <c><![CDATA[hrl]]></c> files by using:<br></br><c><![CDATA[-include_lib("cosEventDomain/include/*.hrl").]]></c></p>
  </description>
  <funcs>
    <func>
      <name>'CycleDetection'() -> string()</name>
      <fsummary>Return the CycleDetection identifier required when defining QoS Properties</fsummary>
      <desc>
        <p>This function returns the CycleDetection identifier; required when 
          defining QoS Properties.</p>
      </desc>
    </func>
    <func>
      <name>'AuthorizeCycles'() -> short()</name>
      <fsummary>Return the AuthorizeCycles value; required when defining QoS Properties</fsummary>
      <desc>
        <p>This function returns the AuthorizeCycles value; required when 
          defining QoS Properties.</p>
      </desc>
    </func>
    <func>
      <name>'ForbidCycles'() -> short()</name>
      <fsummary>Return the ForbidCycles value; required when defining QoS Properties</fsummary>
      <desc>
        <p>This function returns the ForbidCycles value; required when 
          defining QoS Properties.</p>
      </desc>
    </func>
    <func>
      <name>'DiamondDetection'() -> string()</name>
      <fsummary>Return the DiamondDetection identifier required when defining QoS Properties</fsummary>
      <desc>
        <p>This function returns the DiamondDetection identifier; required when 
          defining QoS Properties.</p>
      </desc>
    </func>
    <func>
      <name>'AuthorizeDiamonds'() -> short()</name>
      <fsummary>Return the AuthorizeDiamonds value; required when defining QoS Properties</fsummary>
      <desc>
        <p>This function returns the AuthorizeDiamonds value; required when 
          defining QoS Properties.</p>
      </desc>
    </func>
    <func>
      <name>'ForbidDiamonds'() -> short()</name>
      <fsummary>Return the ForbidDiamonds value; required when defining QoS Properties</fsummary>
      <desc>
        <p>This function returns the ForbidDiamonds value; required when 
          defining QoS Properties.</p>
      </desc>
    </func>
  </funcs>
  
</erlref>

