<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<!DOCTYPE erlref SYSTEM "erlref.dtd">

<erlref>
  <header>
    <copyright>
      <year>2002</year>
      <year>2016</year>
      <holder>Ericsson AB, All Rights Reserved</holder>
    </copyright>
    <legalnotice>
  Licensed under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the "License");
  you may not use this file except in compliance with the License.
  You may obtain a copy of the License at
 
      http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0

  Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
  distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,
  WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
  See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
  limitations under the License.

  The Initial Developer of the Original Code is Ericsson AB.
    </legalnotice>

    <title>CosEventDomainAdmin</title>
    <prepared>Niclas Eklund</prepared>
    <responsible>Niclas Eklund</responsible>
    <docno></docno>
    <approved>Niclas Eklund</approved>
    <checked></checked>
    <date>2001-08-20</date>
    <rev>PA1</rev>
  </header>
  <module>CosEventDomainAdmin</module>
  <modulesummary>This module export functions which return QoS and Admin Properties constants.</modulesummary>
  <description>
    <p>To get access to all definitions include necessary <c><![CDATA[hrl]]></c> files by using:<br></br><c><![CDATA[-include_lib("cosEventDomain/include/*.hrl").]]></c></p>
  </description>
  <funcs>
    <func>
      <name>'CycleDetection'() -> string()</name>
      <fsummary>Return the CycleDetection identifier required when defining QoS Properties</fsummary>
      <desc>
        <p>This function returns the CycleDetection identifier; required when 
          defining QoS Properties.</p>
      </desc>
    </func>
    <func>
      <name>'AuthorizeCycles'() -> short()</name>
      <fsummary>Return the AuthorizeCycles value; required when defining QoS Properties</fsummary>
      <desc>
        <p>This function returns the AuthorizeCycles value; required when 
          defining QoS Properties.</p>
      </desc>
    </func>
    <func>
      <name>'ForbidCycles'() -> short()</name>
      <fsummary>Return the ForbidCycles value; required when defining QoS Properties</fsummary>
      <desc>
        <p>This function returns the ForbidCycles value; required when 
          defining QoS Properties.</p>
      </desc>
    </func>
    <func>
      <name>'DiamondDetection'() -> string()</name>
      <fsummary>Return the DiamondDetection identifier required when defining QoS Properties</fsummary>
      <desc>
        <p>This function returns the DiamondDetection identifier; required when 
          defining QoS Properties.</p>
      </desc>
    </func>
    <func>
      <name>'AuthorizeDiamonds'() -> short()</name>
      <fsummary>Return the AuthorizeDiamonds value; required when defining QoS Properties</fsummary>
      <desc>
        <p>This function returns the AuthorizeDiamonds value; required when 
          defining QoS Properties.</p>
      </desc>
    </func>
    <func>
      <name>'ForbidDiamonds'() -> short()</name>
      <fsummary>Return the ForbidDiamonds value; required when defining QoS Properties</fsummary>
      <desc>
        <p>This function returns the ForbidDiamonds value; required when 
          defining QoS Properties.</p>
      </desc>
    </func>
  </funcs>
  
</erlref>

