<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<!DOCTYPE erlref SYSTEM "erlref.dtd">

<erlref>
  <header>
    <copyright>
      <year>2002</year><year>2013</year>
      <holder>Ericsson AB. All Rights Reserved.</holder>
    </copyright>
    <legalnotice>
      Licensed under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the "License");
      you may not use this file except in compliance with the License.
      You may obtain a copy of the License at
 
          http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0

      Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
      distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,
      WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
      See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
      limitations under the License.

    </legalnotice>

    <title>ms_transform</title>
    <prepared>Patrik Nyblom</prepared>
    <responsible>Bjarne Dacker</responsible>
    <docno>1</docno>
    <approved>Bjarne D&auml;cker</approved>
    <checked></checked>
    <date>99-02-09</date>
    <rev>C</rev>
    <file>ms_transform.sgml</file>
  </header>
  <module>ms_transform</module>
  <modulesummary>Parse_transform that translates fun syntax into match specifications. </modulesummary>
  <description>
    <marker id="top"></marker>
    <p>This module implements the parse_transform that makes calls to
      <c>ets</c> and <c>dbg</c>:<c>fun2ms/1</c> translate into literal
      match specifications. It also implements the back end for the same
      functions when called from the Erlang shell.</p>
    <p>The translations from fun's to match_specs 
      is accessed through the two "pseudo
      functions" <c>ets:fun2ms/1</c> and <c>dbg:fun2ms/1</c>.</p>
    <p>Actually this introduction is more or less an introduction to the
      whole concept of match specifications. Since everyone trying to use
      <c>ets:select</c> or <c>dbg</c> seems to end up reading
      this page, it seems in good place to explain a little more than
      just what this module does.</p>
    <p>There are some caveats one should be aware of, please read through
      the whole manual page if it's the first time you're using the
      transformations. </p>
    <p>Match specifications are used more or less as filters. 
      They resemble usual Erlang matching in a list comprehension or in
      a <c>fun</c> used in conjunction with <c>lists:foldl</c> etc. The
      syntax of pure match specifications is somewhat awkward though, as
      they are made up purely by Erlang terms and there is no syntax in the
      language to make the match specifications more readable.</p>
    <p>As the match specifications execution and structure is quite like
      that of a fun, it would for most programmers be more straight forward
      to simply write it using the familiar fun syntax and having that
      translated into a match specification automatically. Of course a real
      fun is more powerful than the match specifications allow, but bearing
      the match specifications in mind, and what they can do, it's still
      more convenient to write it all as a fun. This module contains the
      code that simply translates the fun syntax into match_spec terms.</p>
    <p>Let's start with an ets example. Using <c>ets:select</c> and
      a match specification, one can filter out rows of a table and construct
      a list of tuples containing relevant parts of the data in these
      rows. Of course one could use <c>ets:foldl</c> instead, but the
      select call is far more efficient. Without the translation, one has to
      struggle with writing match specifications terms to accommodate this,
      or one has to resort to the less powerful
      <c>ets:match(_object)</c> calls, or simply give up and use
      the more inefficient method of <c>ets:foldl</c>. Using the
      <c>ets:fun2ms</c> transformation, a <c>ets:select</c> call
      is at least as easy to write as any of the alternatives.</p>
    <p>As an example, consider a simple table of employees:</p>
    <code type="none">
-record(emp, {empno,     %Employee number as a string, the key
              surname,   %Surname of the employee
              givenname, %Given name of employee
              dept,      %Department one of {dev,sales,prod,adm}
              empyear}). %Year the employee was employed    </code>
    <p>We create the table using:</p>
    <code type="none">
ets:new(emp_tab,[{keypos,#emp.empno},named_table,ordered_set]).    </code>
    <p>Let's also fill it with some randomly chosen data for the examples:</p>
    <code type="none">
[{emp,"011103","Black","Alfred",sales,2000},
 {emp,"041231","Doe","John",prod,2001},
 {emp,"052341","Smith","John",dev,1997},
 {emp,"076324","Smith","Ella",sales,1995},
 {emp,"122334","Weston","Anna",prod,2002},
 {emp,"535216","Chalker","Samuel",adm,1998},
 {emp,"789789","Harrysson","Joe",adm,1996},
 {emp,"963721","Scott","Juliana",dev,2003},
 {emp,"989891","Brown","Gabriel",prod,1999}]    </code>
    <p>Now, the amount of data in the table is of course to small to justify
      complicated ets searches, but on real tables, using <c>select</c> to get
      exactly the data you want will increase efficiency remarkably.</p>
    <p>Lets say for example that we'd want the employee numbers of
      everyone in the sales department. One might use <c>ets:match</c>
      in such a situation:</p>
    <pre>
1> <input>ets:match(emp_tab, {'_', '$1', '_', '_', sales, '_'}).</input>
[["011103"],["076324"]]    </pre>
    <p>Even though <c>ets:match</c> does not require a full match
      specification, but a simpler type, it's still somewhat unreadable, and
      one has little control over the returned result, it's always a list of
      lists. OK, one might use <c>ets:foldl</c> or
      <c>ets:foldr</c> instead:</p>
    <code type="none">
ets:foldr(fun(#emp{empno = E, dept = sales},Acc) -> [E | Acc];
             (_,Acc) -> Acc
          end,
          [],
          emp_tab).    </code>
    <p>Running that would result in <c>["011103","076324"]</c>
      , which at least gets rid of the extra lists. The fun is also quite
      straightforward, so the only problem is that all the data from the
      table has to be transferred from the table to the calling process for
      filtering. That's inefficient compared to the <c>ets:match</c>
      call where the filtering can be done "inside" the emulator and only
      the result is transferred to the process. Remember that ets tables are
      all about efficiency, if it wasn't for efficiency all of ets could be
      implemented in Erlang, as a process receiving requests and sending
      answers back. One uses ets because one wants performance, and
      therefore one wouldn't want all of the table transferred to the
      process for filtering. OK, let's look at a pure
      <c>ets:select</c> call that does what the <c>ets:foldr</c>
      does:</p>
    <code type="none">
ets:select(emp_tab,[{#emp{empno = '$1', dept = sales, _='_'},[],['$1']}]).    </code>
    <p>Even though the record syntax is used, it's still somewhat hard to
      read and even harder to write. The first element of the tuple,
      <c>#emp{empno = '$1', dept = sales, _='_'}</c> tells what to
      match, elements not matching this will not be returned at all, as in
      the <c>ets:match</c> example. The second element, the empty list
      is a list of guard expressions, which we need none, and the third
      element is the list of expressions constructing the return value (in
      ets this almost always is a list containing one single term). In our
      case <c>'$1'</c> is bound to the employee number in the head
      (first element of tuple), and hence it is the employee number that is
      returned. The result is <c>["011103","076324"]</c>, just as in
      the <c>ets:foldr</c> example, but the result is retrieved much
      more efficiently in terms of execution speed and memory consumption.</p>
    <p>We have one efficient but hardly readable way of doing it and one
      inefficient but fairly readable (at least to the skilled Erlang
      programmer) way of doing it. With the use of <c>ets:fun2ms</c>,
      one could have something that is as efficient as possible but still is
      written as a filter using the fun syntax:</p>
    <code type="none">
-include_lib("stdlib/include/ms_transform.hrl").

% ...

ets:select(emp_tab, ets:fun2ms(
                      fun(#emp{empno = E, dept = sales}) ->
                              E
                      end)).    </code>
    <p>This may not be the shortest of the expressions, but it requires no
      special knowledge of match specifications to read. The fun's head
      should simply match what you want to filter out and the body returns
      what you want returned. As long as the fun can be kept within the
      limits of the match specifications, there is no need to transfer all
      data of the table to the process for filtering as in the
      <c>ets:foldr</c> example. In fact it's even easier to read then
      the <c>ets:foldr</c> example, as the select call in itself
      discards anything that doesn't match, while the fun of the
      <c>foldr</c> call needs to handle both the elements matching and
      the ones not matching.</p>
    <p>It's worth noting in the above <c>ets:fun2ms</c> example that one
      needs to include <c>ms_transform.hrl</c> in the source code, as this is
      what triggers the parse transformation of the <c>ets:fun2ms</c> call
      to a valid match specification. This also implies that the
      transformation is done at compile time (except when called from the
      shell of course) and therefore will take no resources at all in
      runtime. So although you use the more intuitive fun syntax, it gets as
      efficient in runtime as writing match specifications by hand.</p>
    <p>Let's look at some more <c>ets</c> examples. Let's say one
      wants to get all the employee numbers of any employee hired before the
      year 2000. Using <c>ets:match</c> isn't an alternative here as
      relational operators cannot be expressed there. Once again, an
      <c>ets:foldr</c> could do it (slowly, but correct):</p>
    <code type="none"><![CDATA[
ets:foldr(fun(#emp{empno = E, empyear = Y},Acc) when Y < 2000 -> [E | Acc];
                  (_,Acc) -> Acc
          end,
          [],
          emp_tab).    ]]></code>
    <p>The result will be
      <c>["052341","076324","535216","789789","989891"]</c>, as
      expected. Now the equivalent expression using a handwritten match
      specification would look something like this:</p>
    <code type="none"><![CDATA[
ets:select(emp_tab,[{#emp{empno = '$1', empyear = '$2', _='_'},
                     [{'<', '$2', 2000}],
                     ['$1']}]).    ]]></code>
    <p>This gives the same result, the <c><![CDATA[[{'<', '$2', 2000}]]]></c> is in
      the guard part and therefore discards anything that does not have a
      empyear (bound to '$2' in the head) less than 2000, just as the guard
      in the <c>foldl</c> example. Lets jump on to writing it using 
      <c>ets:fun2ms</c></p>
    <code type="none"><![CDATA[
-include_lib("stdlib/include/ms_transform.hrl").

% ...

ets:select(emp_tab, ets:fun2ms(
                      fun(#emp{empno = E, empyear = Y}) when Y < 2000 ->
                              E
                      end)).    ]]></code>
    <p>Obviously readability is gained by using the parse transformation.</p>
    <p>I'll show some more examples without the tiresome
      comparing-to-alternatives stuff. Let's say we'd want the whole object
      matching instead of only one element. We could of course assign a
      variable to every part of the record and build it up once again in the
      body of the <c>fun</c>, but it's easier to do like this:</p>
    <code type="none"><![CDATA[
ets:select(emp_tab, ets:fun2ms(
                      fun(Obj = #emp{empno = E, empyear = Y}) 
                         when Y < 2000 ->
                              Obj
                      end)).    ]]></code>
    <p>Just as in ordinary Erlang matching, you can bind a variable to the
      whole matched object using a "match in then match", i.e. a
      <c>=</c>. Unfortunately this is not general in <c>fun's</c> translated
      to match specifications, only on the "top level", i.e. matching the
      <em>whole</em> object arriving to be matched into a separate variable,
      is it allowed. For the one's used to writing match specifications by
      hand, I'll have to mention that the variable A will simply be
      translated into '$_'. It's not general, but it has very common usage,
      why it is handled as a special, but useful, case. If this bothers you,
      the pseudo function <c>object</c> also returns the whole matched
      object, see the part about caveats and limitations below.</p>
    <p>Let's do something in the <c>fun</c>'s body too: Let's say
      that someone realizes that there are a few people having an employee
      number beginning with a zero (<c>0</c>), which shouldn't be
      allowed. All those should have their numbers changed to begin with a
      one (<c>1</c>) instead  and one wants the
      list <c><![CDATA[[{<Old empno>,<New empno>}]]]></c> created:</p>
    <code type="none">
ets:select(emp_tab, ets:fun2ms(
                      fun(#emp{empno = [$0 | Rest] }) ->
                              {[$0|Rest],[$1|Rest]}
                      end)).    </code>
    <p>As a matter of fact, this query hits the feature of partially bound
      keys in the table type <c>ordered_set</c>, so that not the whole
      table need be searched, only the part of the table containing keys
      beginning with <c>0</c> is in fact looked into. </p>
    <p>The fun of course can have several clauses, so that if one could do
      the following: For each employee, if he or she is hired prior to 1997,
      return the tuple <c><![CDATA[{inventory, <employee number>}]]></c>, for each hired 1997
      or later, but before 2001, return <c><![CDATA[{rookie, <employee number>}]]></c>, for all others return <c><![CDATA[{newbie, <employee number>}]]></c>. All except for the ones named <c>Smith</c> as
      they would be affronted by anything other than the tag
      <c>guru</c> and that is also what's returned for their numbers; 
      <c><![CDATA[{guru, <employee number>}]]></c>:</p>
    <code type="none"><![CDATA[
ets:select(emp_tab, ets:fun2ms(
                      fun(#emp{empno = E, surname = "Smith" }) ->
                              {guru,E};
                         (#emp{empno = E, empyear = Y}) when Y < 1997  ->
                              {inventory, E};
                         (#emp{empno = E, empyear = Y}) when Y > 2001  ->
                              {newbie, E};
                         (#emp{empno = E, empyear = Y}) -> % 1997 -- 2001
                              {rookie, E}
                      end)).    ]]></code>
    <p>The result will be:</p>
    <code type="none">
[{rookie,"011103"},
 {rookie,"041231"},
 {guru,"052341"},
 {guru,"076324"},
 {newbie,"122334"},
 {rookie,"535216"},
 {inventory,"789789"},
 {newbie,"963721"},
 {rookie,"989891"}]    </code>
    <p>and so the Smith's will be happy...</p>
    <p>So, what more can you do? Well, the simple answer would be; look
      in the documentation of match specifications in ERTS users
      guide. However let's briefly go through the most useful "built in
      functions" that you can use when the <c>fun</c> is to be
      translated into a match specification by <c>ets:fun2ms</c> (it's
      worth mentioning, although it might be obvious to some, that calling
      other functions than the one's allowed in match specifications cannot
      be done. No "usual" Erlang code can be executed by the <c>fun</c> being
      translated by <c>fun2ms</c>, the <c>fun</c> is after all limited
      exactly to the power of the match specifications, which is
      unfortunate, but the price one has to pay for the execution speed of
      an <c>ets:select</c> compared to <c>ets:foldl/foldr</c>).</p>
    <p>The head of the <c>fun</c> is obviously a head matching (or mismatching) 
      <em>one</em> parameter, one object of the table we <c>select</c>
      from. The object is always a single variable (can be <c>_</c>) or
      a tuple, as that's what's in <c>ets, dets</c> and
      <c>mnesia</c> tables (the match specification returned by
      <c>ets:fun2ms</c> can of course be used with
      <c>dets:select</c> and <c>mnesia:select</c> as well as
      with <c>ets:select</c>). The use of <c>=</c> in the head
      is allowed (and encouraged) on the top level.</p>
    <p>The guard section can contain any guard expression of Erlang.
      Even the "old" type test are allowed on the toplevel of the guard 
      (<c>integer(X)</c> instead of <c>is_integer(X)</c>). As the new type tests (the
      <c>is_</c> tests) are in practice just guard bif's they can also
      be called from within the body of the fun, but so they can in ordinary
      Erlang code. Also arithmetics is allowed, as well as ordinary guard
      bif's. Here's a list of bif's and expressions:</p>
    <list type="bulleted">
      <item>The type tests: is_atom, is_float, is_integer,
       is_list, is_number, is_pid, is_port, is_reference, is_tuple,
       is_binary, is_function, is_record</item>
      <item>The boolean operators: not, and, or, andalso, orelse </item>
      <item>The relational operators: >, >=, &lt;, =&lt;, =:=, ==, =/=, /=</item>
      <item>Arithmetics: +, -, *, div, rem</item>
      <item>Bitwise operators: band, bor, bxor, bnot, bsl, bsr</item>
      <item>The guard bif's: abs, element, hd, length, node, round, size, tl, 
       trunc, self</item>
      <item>The obsolete type test (only in guards):
       atom, float, integer,
       list, number, pid, port, reference, tuple,
       binary, function, record</item>
    </list>
    <p>Contrary to the fact with "handwritten" match specifications, the
      <c>is_record</c> guard works as in ordinary Erlang code.</p>
    <p>Semicolons (<c>;</c>) in guards are allowed, the result will be (as
      expected) one "match_spec-clause" for each semicolon-separated
      part of the guard. The semantics being identical to the Erlang
      semantics.</p>
    <p>The body of the <c>fun</c> is used to construct the
      resulting value. When selecting from tables one usually just construct
      a suiting term here, using ordinary Erlang term construction, like
      tuple parentheses, list brackets and variables matched out in the
      head, possibly in conjunction with the occasional constant. Whatever
      expressions are allowed in guards are also allowed here, but there are
      no special functions except <c>object</c> and
      <c>bindings</c> (see further down), which returns the whole
      matched object and all known variable bindings respectively.</p>
    <p>The <c>dbg</c> variants of match specifications have an
      imperative approach to the match specification body, the ets dialect
      hasn't. The fun body for <c>ets:fun2ms</c> returns the result
      without side effects, and as matching (<c>=</c>) in the body of
      the match specifications is not allowed (for performance reasons) the
      only thing left, more or less, is term construction...</p>
    <p>Let's move on to the <c>dbg</c> dialect, the slightly
      different match specifications translated by <c>dbg:fun2ms</c>. </p>
    <p>The same reasons for using the parse transformation applies to
      <c>dbg</c>, maybe even more so as filtering using Erlang code is
      simply not a good idea when tracing (except afterwards, if you trace
      to file). The concept is similar to that of <c>ets:fun2ms</c>
      except that you usually use it directly from the shell (which can also
      be done with <c>ets:fun2ms</c>). </p>
    <p>Let's manufacture a toy module to trace on  </p>
    <code type="none">
-module(toy).

-export([start/1, store/2, retrieve/1]).

start(Args) ->
    toy_table = ets:new(toy_table,Args).

store(Key, Value) ->
    ets:insert(toy_table,{Key,Value}).

retrieve(Key) ->
    [{Key, Value}] = ets:lookup(toy_table,Key),
    Value.    </code>
    <p>During model testing, the first test bails out with a
      <c>{badmatch,16}</c> in <c>{toy,start,1}</c>, why?</p>
    <p>We suspect the ets call, as we match hard on the return value, but
      want only the particular <c>new</c> call with
      <c>toy_table</c> as first parameter.
      So we start a default tracer on the node:</p>
    <pre>
1> <input>dbg:tracer().</input>
{ok,&lt;0.88.0>}</pre>
    <p>And so we turn on call tracing for all processes, we are going to
      make a pretty restrictive trace pattern, so there's no need to call
      trace only a few processes (it usually isn't):</p>
    <pre>
2> <input>dbg:p(all,call).</input>
{ok,[{matched,nonode@nohost,25}]}    </pre>
    <p>It's time to specify the filter. We want to view calls that resemble
      <c><![CDATA[ets:new(toy_table,<something>)]]></c>:</p>
    <pre>
3> <input>dbg:tp(ets,new,dbg:fun2ms(fun([toy_table,_]) -> true end)).</input>
{ok,[{matched,nonode@nohost,1},{saved,1}]}    </pre>
    <p>As can be seen, the <c>fun</c>'s used with
      <c>dbg:fun2ms</c> takes a single list as parameter instead of a
      single tuple. The list matches a list of the parameters to the traced
      function.  A single variable may also be used of course. The body
      of the fun expresses in a more imperative way actions to be taken if
      the fun head (and the guards) matches. I return <c>true</c> here, but it's
      only because the body of a fun cannot be empty, the return value will
      be discarded. </p>
    <p>When we run the test of our module now, we get the following trace
      output:</p>
    <code type="none"><![CDATA[
(<0.86.0>) call ets:new(toy_table,[ordered_set])    ]]></code>
    <p>Let's play we haven't spotted the problem yet, and want to see what 
      <c>ets:new</c> returns. We do a slightly different trace
      pattern:</p>
    <pre>
4> <input>dbg:tp(ets,new,dbg:fun2ms(fun([toy_table,_]) -> return_trace() end)).</input></pre>
    <p>Resulting in the following trace output when we run the test:</p>
    <code type="none"><![CDATA[
(<0.86.0>) call ets:new(toy_table,[ordered_set])
(<0.86.0>) returned from ets:new/2 -> 24    ]]></code>
    <p>The call to <c>return_trace</c>, makes a trace message appear
      when the function returns. It applies only to the specific function call
      triggering the match specification (and matching the head/guards of
      the match specification). This is the by far the most common call in the
      body of a <c>dbg</c> match specification.</p>
    <p>As the test now fails with <c>{badmatch,24}</c>, it's obvious 
      that the badmatch is because the atom <c>toy_table</c> does not
      match the number returned for an unnamed table. So we spotted the
      problem, the table should be named and the arguments supplied by our
      test program does not include <c>named_table</c>. We rewrite the
      start function to:</p>
    <code type="none">
start(Args) ->
    toy_table = ets:new(toy_table,[named_table |Args]).    </code>
    <p>And with the same tracing turned on, we get the following trace
      output:</p>
    <code type="none"><![CDATA[
(<0.86.0>) call ets:new(toy_table,[named_table,ordered_set])
(<0.86.0>) returned from ets:new/2 -> toy_table    ]]></code>
    <p>Very well. Let's say the module now passes all testing and goes into
      the system. After a while someone realizes that the table
      <c>toy_table</c> grows while the system is running and that for some
      reason there are a lot of elements with atom's as keys. You had
      expected only integer keys and so does the rest of the system. Well,
      obviously not all of the system. You turn on call tracing and try to
      see calls to your module with an atom as the key:</p>
    <pre>
1> <input>dbg:tracer().</input>
{ok,&lt;0.88.0>}
2> <input>dbg:p(all,call).</input>
{ok,[{matched,nonode@nohost,25}]}
3> <input>dbg:tpl(toy,store,dbg:fun2ms(fun([A,_]) when is_atom(A) -> true end)).</input>
{ok,[{matched,nonode@nohost,1},{saved,1}]}</pre>
    <p>We use <c>dbg:tpl</c> here to make sure to catch local calls
      (let's say the module has grown since the smaller version and we're
      not sure this inserting of atoms is not done locally...). When in
      doubt always use local call tracing.</p>
    <p>Let's say nothing happens when we trace in this way. Our function
      is never called with these parameters. We make the conclusion that
      someone else (some other module) is doing it and we realize that we
      must trace on ets:insert and want to see the calling function. The
      calling function may be retrieved using the match specification
      function <c>caller</c> and to get it into the trace message, one
      has to use the match spec function <c>message</c>. The filter
      call looks like this (looking for calls to <c>ets:insert</c>):</p>
    <pre>
4> <input>dbg:tpl(ets,insert,dbg:fun2ms(fun([toy_table,{A,_}]) when is_atom(A) -> </input>
<input>                                    message(caller()) </input>
<input>                                  end)). </input>
{ok,[{matched,nonode@nohost,1},{saved,2}]}    </pre>
    <p>The caller will now appear in the "additional message" part of the
      trace output, and so after a while, the following output comes:</p>
    <code type="none"><![CDATA[
(<0.86.0>) call ets:insert(toy_table,{garbage,can}) ({evil_mod,evil_fun,2})    ]]></code>
    <p>You have found out that the function <c>evil_fun</c> of the
      module <c>evil_mod</c>, with arity <c>2</c>, is the one
      causing all this trouble.</p>
    <p>This was just a toy example, but it illustrated the most used
      calls in match specifications for <c>dbg</c> The other, more
      esotheric calls are listed and explained in the <em>Users guide of the ERTS application</em>, they really are beyond the scope of this
      document.</p>
    <p>To end this chatty introduction with something more precise, here
      follows some parts about caveats and restrictions concerning the fun's
      used in conjunction with <c>ets:fun2ms</c> and
      <c>dbg:fun2ms</c>:</p>
    <warning>
      <p>To use the pseudo functions triggering the translation, one
        <em>has to</em> include the header file <c>ms_transform.hrl</c>
        in the source code. Failure to do so will possibly result in
        runtime errors rather than compile time, as the expression may
        be valid as a plain Erlang program without translation.</p>
    </warning>
    <warning>
      <p>The <c>fun</c> has to be literally constructed inside the
        parameter list to the pseudo functions. The <c>fun</c> cannot
        be bound to a variable first and then passed to
        <c>ets:fun2ms</c> or <c>dbg:fun2ms</c>, i.e this
        will work: <c>ets:fun2ms(fun(A) -> A end)</c> but not this:
        <c>F = fun(A) -> A end, ets:fun2ms(F)</c>. The later will result
        in a compile time error if the header is included, otherwise a
        runtime error. Even if the later construction would ever
        appear to work, it really doesn't, so don't ever use it.</p>
    </warning>
    <p>Several restrictions apply to the fun that is being translated
      into a match_spec. To put it simple you cannot use anything in
      the fun that you cannot use in a match_spec. This means that,
      among others, the following restrictions apply to the fun itself:</p>
    <list type="bulleted">
      <item>Functions written in Erlang cannot be called, neither
       local functions, global functions or real fun's</item>
      <item>Everything that is written as a function call will be
       translated into a match_spec call to a builtin function, so that
       the call <c>is_list(X)</c> will be translated to <c>{'is_list', '$1'}</c> (<c>'$1'</c> is just an example, the numbering may
       vary). If one tries to call a function that is not a match_spec
       builtin, it will cause an error.</item>
      <item>Variables occurring in the head of the <c>fun</c> will be
       replaced by match_spec variables in the order of occurrence, so
       that the fragment <c>fun({A,B,C})</c> will be replaced by
      <c>{'$1', '$2', '$3'}</c> etc. Every occurrence of such a
       variable later in the match_spec will be replaced by a
       match_spec variable in the same way, so that the fun
      <c>fun({A,B}) when is_atom(A) -> B end</c> will be translated into
      <c>[{{'$1','$2'},[{is_atom,'$1'}],['$2']}]</c>.</item>
      <item>
        <p>Variables that are not appearing in the head are imported 
          from the environment and made into
          match_spec <c>const</c> expressions. Example from the shell:</p>
        <pre>
1> <input>X = 25.</input>
25
2> <input>ets:fun2ms(fun({A,B}) when A > X -> B end).</input>
[{{'$1','$2'},[{'>','$1',{const,25}}],['$2']}]</pre>
      </item>
      <item>
        <p>Matching with <c>=</c> cannot be used in the body. It can only
          be used on the top level in the head of the fun. 
          Example from the shell again:</p>
        <pre>
1> <input>ets:fun2ms(fun({A,[B|C]} = D) when A > B -> D end).</input>
[{{'$1',['$2'|'$3']},[{'>','$1','$2'}],['$_']}]
2> <input>ets:fun2ms(fun({A,[B|C]=D}) when A > B -> D end).</input>
Error: fun with head matching ('=' in head) cannot be translated into 
match_spec 
{error,transform_error}
3> <input>ets:fun2ms(fun({A,[B|C]}) when A > B -> D = [B|C], D end).</input>
Error: fun with body matching ('=' in body) is illegal as match_spec
{error,transform_error}        </pre>
        <p>All variables are bound in the head of a match_spec, so the 
          translator can not allow multiple bindings. The special case
          when matching is done on the top level makes the variable bind
          to <c>'$_'</c> in the resulting match_spec, it is to allow a more
          natural access to the whole matched object. The pseudo
          function <c>object()</c> could be used instead, see below. 
          The following expressions are translated equally: </p>
        <code type="none">
ets:fun2ms(fun({a,_} = A) -> A end).
ets:fun2ms(fun({a,_}) -> object() end).</code>
      </item>
      <item>
        <p>The special match_spec variables <c>'$_'</c> and <c>'$*'</c>
          can be accessed through the pseudo functions <c>object()</c>
          (for <c>'$_'</c>) and <c>bindings()</c> (for <c>'$*'</c>).
          as an example, one could translate the following
          <c>ets:match_object/2</c> call to a <c>ets:select</c> call:</p>
        <code type="none">
ets:match_object(Table, {'$1',test,'$2'}). </code>
        <p>...is the same as...</p>
        <code type="none">
ets:select(Table, ets:fun2ms(fun({A,test,B}) -> object() end)).</code>
        <p>(This was just an example, in this simple case the former
          expression is probably preferable in terms of readability).
          The <c>ets:select/2</c> call will conceptually look like this
          in the resulting code:</p>
        <code type="none">
ets:select(Table, [{{'$1',test,'$2'},[],['$_']}]).</code>
        <p>Matching on the top level of the fun head might feel like a
          more natural way to access <c>'$_'</c>, see above.</p>
      </item>
      <item>Term constructions/literals are translated as much as is
       needed to get them into valid match_specs, so that tuples are
       made into match_spec tuple constructions (a one element tuple
       containing the tuple) and constant expressions are used when
       importing variables from the environment. Records are also
       translated into plain tuple constructions, calls to element
       etc. The guard test <c>is_record/2</c> is translated into
       match_spec code using the three parameter version that's built
       into match_specs, so that <c>is_record(A,t)</c> is translated
       into <c>{is_record,'$1',t,5}</c> given that the record size of
       record type <c>t</c> is 5.</item>
      <item>Language constructions like <c>case</c>, <c>if</c>,
      <c>catch</c> etc that are not present in match_specs are not
       allowed.</item>
      <item>If the header file <c>ms_transform.hrl</c> is not included,
       the fun won't be translated, which may result in a
      <em>runtime error</em> (depending on if the fun is valid in a
       pure Erlang context). Be absolutely sure that the header is
       included when using <c>ets</c> and <c>dbg:fun2ms/1</c> in
       compiled code.</item>
      <item>If the pseudo function triggering the translation is
      <c>ets:fun2ms/1</c>, the fun's head must contain a single
       variable or a single tuple. If the pseudo function is
      <c>dbg:fun2ms/1</c> the fun's head must contain a single
       variable or a single list.</item>
    </list>
    <p>The translation from fun's to match_specs is done at compile
      time, so runtime performance is not affected by using these pseudo
      functions. The compile time might be somewhat longer though. </p>
    <p>For more information about match_specs, please read about them
      in <em>ERTS users guide</em>.</p>
  </description>
  <funcs>
    <func>
      <name name="parse_transform" arity="2"/>
      <fsummary>Transforms Erlang abstract format containing calls to ets/dbg:fun2ms into literal match specifications.</fsummary>
      <type_desc variable="Options">Option list, required but not used.</type_desc>
      <desc>
        <p>Implements the actual transformation at compile time. This
          function is called by the compiler to do the source code
          transformation if and when the <c>ms_transform.hrl</c> header
          file is included in your source code. See the <c>ets</c> and
          <c>dbg</c>:<c>fun2ms/1</c> function manual pages for
          documentation on how to use this parse_transform, see the
          <c>match_spec</c> chapter in <c>ERTS</c> users guide for a
          description of match specifications. </p>
      </desc>
    </func>
    <func>
      <name name="transform_from_shell" arity="3"/>
      <fsummary>Used when transforming fun's created in the shell into match_specifications.</fsummary>
      <type_desc variable="BoundEnvironment">List of variable bindings in the shell environment.</type_desc>
      <desc>
        <p>Implements the actual transformation when the <c>fun2ms</c>
          functions are called from the shell. In this case the abstract
          form is for one single fun (parsed by the Erlang shell), and
          all imported variables should be in the key-value list passed
          as <c><anno>BoundEnvironment</anno></c>. The result is a term, normalized,
          i.e. not in abstract format.</p>
      </desc>
    </func>
    <func>
      <name name="format_error" arity="1"/>
      <fsummary>Error formatting function as required by the parse_transform interface.</fsummary>
      <desc>
        <p>Takes an error code returned by one of the other functions
          in the module and creates a textual description of the
          error. Fairly uninteresting function actually.</p>
      </desc>
    </func>
  </funcs>
</erlref>

