<?xml version="1.0" encoding="latin1" ?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter SYSTEM "chapter.dtd">

<chapter>
  <header>
    <copyright>
      <year>1997</year><year>2009</year>
      <holder>Ericsson AB. All Rights Reserved.</holder>
    </copyright>
    <legalnotice>
      The contents of this file are subject to the Erlang Public License,
      Version 1.1, (the "License"); you may not use this file except in
      compliance with the License. You should have received a copy of the
      Erlang Public License along with this software. If not, it can be
      retrieved online at http://www.erlang.org/.
    
      Software distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS"
      basis, WITHOUT WARRANTY OF ANY KIND, either express or implied. See
      the License for the specific language governing rights and limitations
      under the License.
    
    </legalnotice>

    <title>Windows NT</title>
    <prepared>Kenneth Lundin</prepared>
    <responsible>Kenneth Lundin</responsible>
    <docno></docno>
    <approved></approved>
    <checked></checked>
    <date>1997-11-25</date>
    <rev>PA2</rev>
    <file>embedded_nt.xml</file>
  </header>
  <p>This chapter describes the OS specific parts of OTP which relate
    to Windows NT.
    </p>

  <section>
    <title>Introduction</title>
    <p>A normal installation of NT 4.0, with service pack 4 or later, 
      is required for an embedded Windows NT running OTP.</p>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Memory Usage</title>
    <p>RAM memory of 96 MBytes is recommended to run OTP on NT.
      A system with less than 64 Mbytes of RAM is not recommended.</p>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Disk Space Usage</title>
    <p>A minimum NT installation with networking needs 250 MB, and 
      an additional 130 MB for the swap file. </p>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Installation</title>
    <p>Normal NT installation is performed. No additional application   
      programs are needed, such as Internet explorer or web server. Networking
      with TCP/IP is required.      <br></br>

      Service pack 4 or later must be installed.</p>

    <section>
      <title>Hardware Watchdog</title>
      <p>For Windows NT running on standard PCs with ISA and/or PCI bus
        there is a possibility to install an extension card with a hardware
        watchdog.
        </p>
      <p>See also the <c>heart(3)</c> reference manual page in
        <em>Kernel</em>.
        </p>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Starting Erlang</title>
    <p>On an embedded system, the <c>erlsrv</c> module should be used, 
      to install the erlang process as a Windows system service. 
      This service can start
      after NT has booted. See documentation for <c>erlsrv</c>.</p>
  </section>
</chapter>

