<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter SYSTEM "chapter.dtd">

<chapter>
  <header>
    <copyright>
      <year>1997</year><year>2016</year>
      <holder>Ericsson AB. All Rights Reserved.</holder>
    </copyright>
    <legalnotice>
      Licensed under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the "License");
      you may not use this file except in compliance with the License.
      You may obtain a copy of the License at
 
          http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0

      Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
      distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,
      WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
      See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
      limitations under the License.
    
    </legalnotice>

    <title>Windows NT</title>
    <prepared>Kenneth Lundin</prepared>
    <responsible>Kenneth Lundin</responsible>
    <docno></docno>
    <approved></approved>
    <checked></checked>
    <date>1997-11-25</date>
    <rev>PA2</rev>
    <file>embedded_nt.xml</file>
  </header>
  <marker id="windows nt"></marker>
  <p>This section describes the operating system-specific parts of OTP
    that relate to Windows NT.</p>
  <p>A normal installation of Windows NT 4.0, with Service Pack 4 or
    later, is required for an embedded Windows NT running OTP.</p>

  <section>
    <title>Memory Use</title>
    <p>RAM memory of 96 MB is recommended to run OTP on Windows NT.
      A system with less than 64 MB of RAM is not recommended.</p>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Disk Space Use</title>
    <p>A minimum Windows NT installation with networking needs 250 MB,
      and an extra 130 MB for the swap file.</p>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Installing an Embedded System</title>
    <p>Normal Windows NT installation is performed. No additional
      application programs are needed, such as Internet Explorer or
      web server. Networking with TCP/IP is required.</p>
    <p>Service Pack 4 or later must be installed.</p>

    <section>
      <title>Hardware Watchdog</title>
      <p>For Windows NT running on standard PCs with ISA and/or PCI bus,
        an extension card with a hardware watchdog can be installed.</p>
      <p>For more information, see the <c>heart(3)</c> manual page in
        <c>kernel</c>.</p>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Starting Erlang</title>
    <p>On an embedded system, the <c>erlsrv</c> module is to be used
      to install the Erlang process as a Windows system service.
      This service can start after Windows NT has booted.</p>
    <p>For more information, see the <c>erlsrv</c> manual page
      in <c>erts</c>.</p>
  </section>
</chapter>

