<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter SYSTEM "chapter.dtd">

<chapter>
  <header>
    <copyright>
      <year>1997</year>
      <year>2016</year>
      <holder>Ericsson AB, All Rights Reserved</holder>
    </copyright>
    <legalnotice>
  Licensed under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the "License");
  you may not use this file except in compliance with the License.
  You may obtain a copy of the License at
 
      http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0

  Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
  distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,
  WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
  See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
  limitations under the License.

  The Initial Developer of the Original Code is Ericsson AB.
    </legalnotice>

    <title>XNTP (Network Time Protocol)</title>
    <prepared>ETX/B/SFP Kenneth Lundin</prepared>
    <responsible></responsible>
    <docno>1</docno>
    <approved>ETX/B/SFP (Kenneth Lundin)</approved>
    <checked></checked>
    <date>1996-11-20</date>
    <rev>A</rev>
    <file>xntp.sgml</file>
  </header>
  <p>This chapter describes the OS specific part of OTP that relates
    to the Network Time Protocol (XNTP).
    </p>

  <section>
    <title>XNTP for Sunos5</title>
    <p>XNTP maintains a Unix system time-of-day which conforms with
      the Internet standard time servers. XNTP is a complete
      implementation of the Network Time Protocol, version 3
      specification as defined in RFC 1305.
      </p>
    <p>XNTP for use in an <em>embedded system running Sunos5</em> is
      delivered with OTP. The XNTP is delivered as a separate
      <c>tar</c> file which also includes extensive documentation and
      installation instructions.
      </p>
    <p>The following section of the introductory documentation is
      included in the distribution:
      </p>
    <quote>
      <p>The Network Time Protocol (NTP) is used to synchronize the
        time of a computer client or server to another server or
        reference time source, such as a radio or satellite receiver
        or modem. It provides client accuracies typically within a
        millisecond on LANs and up to a few tens of milliseconds on
        WANs relative to a primary server synchronized to Coordinated
        Universal Time (UTC) via a Global Positioning Service (GPS)
        receiver, for example. Typical NTP configurations utilize
        multiple redundant servers and diverse network paths, in order
        to achieve high accuracy and reliability. ...</p>
    </quote>
    <p>The XNTP software is supplied without charge under the
      conditions set forth in the Copyright Notice provided within the
      distribution.
      </p>
    <p>(&copy; David L. Mills 1992, 1993, 1994, 1995, 1996)
      </p>
  </section>
</chapter>

