<?xml version="1.0" encoding="latin1" ?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter SYSTEM "chapter.dtd">

<chapter>
  <header>
    <copyright>
      <year>2000</year><year>2010</year>
      <holder>Ericsson AB. All Rights Reserved.</holder>
    </copyright>
    <legalnotice>
      The contents of this file are subject to the Erlang Public License,
      Version 1.1, (the "License"); you may not use this file except in
      compliance with the License. You should have received a copy of the
      Erlang Public License along with this software. If not, it can be
      retrieved online at http://www.erlang.org/.

      Software distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS"
      basis, WITHOUT WARRANTY OF ANY KIND, either express or implied. See
      the License for the specific language governing rights and limitations
      under the License.

    </legalnotice>

    <title>Installing the Binary Release</title>
    <prepared>Peter H&ouml;gfeldt</prepared>
    <responsible>Peter H&ouml;gfeldt</responsible>
    <docno></docno>
    <approved>(Peter H&ouml;gfeldt</approved>
    <checked></checked>
    <date>1997-05-26</date>
    <rev>C</rev>
    <file>install-binary.xml</file>
  </header>

  <section>
    <title>UNIX</title>

    <section>
      <title>Introduction</title>
      <p>The system is delivered as a single compressed tar file.</p>
      <p>To browse the on-line HTML documentation, Netscape or an equivalent
        browser supporting frames is needed.</p>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Installation Procedure</title>
      <p>When installed, the entire system, except for a small start-up
        script, resides in a single directory tree. The location of this
        directory tree can be chosen arbitrarily by the installer, and it
        does not need to be in the user's <c>$PATH</c>. The only requirements
        are that the file system where it is placed has enough free space,
        and that the users who run Erlang/OTP have read access to it. In the
        example below, the directory tree is assumed to be located at
        <c>/usr/local/erlang</c>, which is here called the <em>top-level directory</em>.</p>
      <p>It is assumed that you have the compressed tar file, the name of
        which is <c><![CDATA[<PREFIX>.tar.gz]]></c>, where <c><![CDATA[<PREFIX>]]></c> is a string
        denoting the particular Erlang/OTP release, e.g.
        <c>otp_LXA_11930_sunos5_R9B</c>.</p>
      <p>Wherever the string <c><![CDATA[<PREFIX>]]></c> is used below, it should
        be replaced by the actual name prefix of the compressed tar file.</p>
      <p>The tape archive file does not have one single directory in which
        all other files are rooted. Therefore the tape archive file must be
        extracted into an empty (newly created) directory.</p>
      <list type="ordered">
        <item>
          <p>If the <em>top-level directory</em> does not already exist,
            create it:</p>
          <pre>
mkdir /usr/local/erlang</pre>
        </item>
        <item>
          <p>Change the current directory to the <em>top level directory</em>:</p>
          <pre>
cd /usr/local/erlang</pre>
        </item>
        <item>
          <p>Create the <em>installation directory</em> with an appropriate
            name. For example:</p>
          <pre>
mkdir otp_r7b</pre>
        </item>
        <item>
          <p>Change to the <em>installation directory</em>, e.g.</p>
          <pre>
cd otp_r7b</pre>
        </item>
        <item>
          <p>Assuming the compressed tar file resides in the directory
            <c><![CDATA[<SOME-DIR>]]></c>,. extract the compressed tar file into the
            current directory:</p>
          <pre>
gunzip -c &lt;SOME-DIR&gt;/&lt;PREFIX&gt;.tar.gz | tar xfp -</pre>
        </item>
        <item>
          <p>Read the <c>README</c> file in the installation directory for
            last minute updates, before proceeding.</p>
        </item>
        <item>
          <p>Run the <c>Install</c> script in the installation directory,
            with the absolute path of the installation directory as argument,</p>
          <pre>
./Install /usr/local/erlang/otp_r7b</pre>
          <p>and supply answers to the prompts.</p>
          <p>In most cases, there is a default answer in square brackets
            (<c>[]</c>). If the default is satisfactory, just press
            <c><![CDATA[<Return>]]></c>. In general you are only prompted for one thing:</p>
          <list type="bulleted">
            <item>
              <p>"Do you want to use a minimal system startup instead of the
                SASL startup?"                <br></br>

                In a minimal system, only the Kernel and STDLIB applications
                are loaded and started. If the SASL startup is used, the SASL
                application is included as well. Normally, the minimal system
                is enough.</p>
            </item>
          </list>
        </item>
        <item>
          <p>Make Erlang/OTP available for users, either by putting the path
            <c>/usr/local/erlang/otp_r7b/bin</c> in users <c>$PATH</c>
            variable, or link the executable
            <c>/usr/local/erlang/otp_r7b/bin/erl</c> accordingly, e.g.:</p>
          <pre>
ln -s /usr/local/erlang/otp_r7b/bin/erl /usr/local/bin/erl </pre>
        </item>
      </list>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Windows</title>

    <section>
      <title>Introduction</title>
      <p>The system is delivered as a single <c>.exe</c> file.</p>
      <p>To browse the on-line HTML documentation, Netscape or an equivalent
        browser supporting frames is needed.</p>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Installation Procedure</title>
      <p>The installation procedure is is automated. Double-click the
        <c>.exe</c> file icon and follow the instructions.</p>
    </section>
  </section>
</chapter>
