<?xml version="1.0" encoding="latin1" ?>
<!DOCTYPE appref SYSTEM "appref.dtd">

<appref>
  <header>
    <copyright>
      <year>1999</year><year>2009</year>
      <holder>Ericsson AB. All Rights Reserved.</holder>
    </copyright>
    <legalnotice>
      The contents of this file are subject to the Erlang Public License,
      Version 1.1, (the "License"); you may not use this file except in
      compliance with the License. You should have received a copy of the
      Erlang Public License along with this software. If not, it can be
      retrieved online at http://www.erlang.org/.
    
      Software distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS"
      basis, WITHOUT WARRANTY OF ANY KIND, either express or implied. See
      the License for the specific language governing rights and limitations
      under the License.
    
    </legalnotice>

    <title>ssl</title>
    <prepared>Peter H&ouml;gfeldt</prepared>
    <responsible>Peter H&ouml;gfeldt</responsible>
    <docno></docno>
    <approved>Peter H&ouml;gfeldt</approved>
    <checked>Peter H&ouml;gfeldt</checked>
    <date>2005-03-10</date>
    <rev>E</rev>
    <file>ssl_app.sgml</file>
  </header>
  <app>ssl</app>
  <appsummary>The SSL Application</appsummary>
  <description>
    <p>The Secure Socket Layer (SSL) application provides secure
      socket communication over TCP/IP.
      </p>
  </description>

  <section>
    <title>Warning</title>
    <p>In previous versions of Erlang/OTP SSL it was advised, as a
      work-around, to set the operating system environment variable
      <c>SSL_CERT_FILE</c> to point at a file containing CA
      certificates. That variable is no longer needed, and is not
      recognised by Erlang/OTP SSL any more.
      </p>
    <p>However, the OpenSSL package does interpret that environment
      variable. Hence a setting of that variable might have
      unpredictable effects on the Erlang/OTP SSL application. It is
      therefore adviced to not used that environment variable at all.</p>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Environment</title>
    <p>The following application environment configuration parameters
      are defined for the SSL application. Refer to application(3) for
      more information about configuration parameters.
      </p>
    <p>Note that the environment parameters can be set on the command line,
      for instance,</p>
    <p><c>erl ... -ssl protocol_version '[sslv2,sslv3]' ...</c>.
      </p>
    <taglist>
      <tag><c><![CDATA[ephemeral_rsa = true | false <optional>]]></c></tag>
      <item>
        <p>Enables all SSL servers (those that listen and accept)
          to use ephemeral RSA key generation when a clients connect with
          weak handshake cipher specifications, that need equally weak
          ciphers from the server (i.e. obsolete restrictions on export
          ciphers).  Default is <c>false</c>.
          </p>
      </item>
      <tag><c><![CDATA[debug = true | false <optional>]]></c></tag>
      <item>
        <p>Causes debug information to be written to standard
          output. Default is <c>false</c>.
          </p>
      </item>
      <tag><c><![CDATA[debugdir = path() | false <optional>]]></c></tag>
      <item>
        <p>Causes debug information output controlled by <c>debug</c>
          and <c>msgdebug</c> to be printed to a file named 
          <c><![CDATA[ssl_esock.<pid>.log]]></c> in the directory specified by
          <c>debugdir</c>, where <c><![CDATA[<pid>]]></c> is the operating system
          specific textual representation of the process identifier 
          of the external port program of the SSL application. Default
          is <c>false</c>, i.e. no log file is produced.
          </p>
      </item>
      <tag><c><![CDATA[msgdebug = true | false <optional>]]></c></tag>
      <item>
        <p>Sets <c>debug = true</c> and causes also the contents
          of low level messages to be printed to standard output.
          Default is <c>false</c>.
          </p>
      </item>
      <tag><c><![CDATA[port_program = string() | false <optional>]]></c></tag>
      <item>
        <p>Name of port program. The default is <c>ssl_esock</c>.
          </p>
      </item>
      <tag><c><![CDATA[protocol_version = [sslv2|sslv3|tlsv1] <optional>]]></c>.</tag>
      <item>
        <p>Name of protocols to use. If this option is not set, 
          all protocols are assumed, i.e. the default value is
          <c>[sslv2, sslv3, tlsv1]</c>.
          </p>
      </item>
      <tag><c><![CDATA[proxylsport = integer() | false <optional>]]></c></tag>
      <item>
        <p>Define the port number of the listen port of the 
          SSL port program. Almost never is this option needed.
          </p>
      </item>
      <tag><c><![CDATA[proxylsbacklog = integer() | false <optional>]]></c></tag>
      <item>
        <p>Set the listen queue size of the listen port of the
          SSL port program. The default is 128.
          </p>
      </item>
    </taglist>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>OpenSSL libraries</title>
    <p>The current implementation of the Erlang SSL application is
      based on the <em>OpenSSL</em> package version 0.9.7 or higher.
      There are source and binary releases on the web.
      </p>
    <p>Source releases of OpenSSL can be downloaded from the <url href="http://www.openssl.org">OpenSSL</url> project home page,
      or mirror sites listed there.
      </p>
    <p>The same URL also contains links to some compiled binaries and
      libraries of OpenSSL (see the <c>Related/Binaries</c> menu) of
      which the <url href="http://www.shininglightpro.com/search.php?searchname=Win32+OpenSSL">Shining Light Productions Win32 and OpenSSL</url> pages are of
      interest for the Win32 user.
      </p>
    <p>For some Unix flavours there are binary packages available
      on the net. 
      </p>
    <p>If you cannot find a suitable binary OpenSSL package, you 
      have to fetch an OpenSSL source release and compile it. 
      </p>
    <p>You then have to compile and install the libraries
      <c>libcrypto.so</c> and <c>libssl.so</c> (Unix), or the
      libraries <c>libeay32.dll</c> and <c>ssleay32.dll</c> (Win32).
      </p>
    <p>For Unix The <c>ssl_esock</c> port program is delivered linked
      to OpenSSL libraries in <c>/usr/local/lib</c>, but the default
      dynamic linking will also accept libraries in <c>/lib</c> and
      <c>/usr/lib</c>.
      </p>
    <p>If that is not applicable to the particular Unix operating
      system used, the example <c>Makefile</c> in the SSL
      <c>priv/obj</c> directory, should be used as a guide to
      relinking the final version of the port program.
      </p>
    <p>For <c>Win32</c> it is only required that the libraries can be
      found from the <c>PATH</c> environment variable, or that they
      reside in the appropriate <c>SYSTEM32</c> directory; hence no
      particular relinking is need. Hence no example <c>Makefile</c>
      for Win32 is provided.</p>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Restrictions</title>
    <p>Users must be aware of export restrictions and patent rights
      concerning cryptographic software.
      </p>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>SEE ALSO</title>
    <p>application(3)</p>
  </section>
  
</appref>


