<?xml version="1.0" encoding="latin1" ?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter SYSTEM "chapter.dtd">

<chapter>
  <header>
    <copyright>
      <year>2000</year><year>2009</year>
      <holder>Ericsson AB. All Rights Reserved.</holder>
    </copyright>
    <legalnotice>
      The contents of this file are subject to the Erlang Public License,
      Version 1.1, (the "License"); you may not use this file except in
      compliance with the License. You should have received a copy of the
      Erlang Public License along with this software. If not, it can be
      retrieved online at http://www.erlang.org/.
    
      Software distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS"
      basis, WITHOUT WARRANTY OF ANY KIND, either express or implied. See
      the License for the specific language governing rights and limitations
      under the License.
    
    </legalnotice>

    <title>Using SSL for Erlang Distribution</title>
    <prepared>P Nyblom</prepared>
    <responsible></responsible>
    <docno></docno>
    <approved></approved>
    <checked></checked>
    <date>2003-04-01</date>
    <rev>B</rev>
    <file>ssl_distribution.xml</file>
  </header>
  <p>This chapter describes how the Erlang distribution can use 
    SSL to get additional verification and security.</p>

  <section>
    <title>Introduction</title>
    <p>The Erlang distribution can in theory use almost any connection
      based protocol as bearer. A module that implements the protocol
      specific parts of connection setup is however needed. The
      default distribution module is <c>inet_tcp_dist</c> which is
      included in the Kernel application. When starting an
      Erlang node distributed, <c>net_kernel</c> uses this module to
      setup listen ports and connections. </p>
    <p>In the SSL application there is an additional distribution
      module, <c>inet_ssl_dist</c> which can be used as an
      alternative. All distribution connections will be using SSL and
      all participating Erlang nodes in a distributed system must use
      this distribution module.</p>
    <p>The security depends on how the connections are set up, one can
      use key files or certificates to just get a crypted
      connection. One can also make the SSL package verify the
      certificates of other nodes to get additional security. 
      Cookies are however always used as they can be used to
      differentiate between two different Erlang networks.</p>
    <p>Setting up Erlang distribution over SSL involves some simple but
      necessary steps:</p>
    <list type="bulleted">
      <item>Building boot scripts including the SSL application</item>
      <item>Specifying the distribution module for net_kernel</item>
      <item>Specifying security options and other SSL options</item>
    </list>
    <p>The rest of this chapter describes the above mentioned steps in
      more detail.</p>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Building boot scripts including the SSL application</title>
    <p>Boot scripts are built using the <c>systools</c> utility in the
      SASL application. Refer to the SASL documentations
      for more information on systools. This is only an example of
      what can be done.</p>
    <p>The simplest boot script possible includes only the Kernel
      and STDLIB applications. Such a script is located in the
      Erlang distributions bin directory. The source for the script
      can be found under the Erlang installation top directory under
      <c><![CDATA[releases/<OTP version>start_clean.rel]]></c>. Copy that
      script to another location (and preferably another name) 
      and add the SSL application with its current version number
      after the STDLIB application.</p>
    <p>An example .rel file with SSL added may look like this:</p>
    <code type="none">
{release, {"OTP  APN 181 01","P7A"}, {erts, "5.0"},
 [{kernel,"2.5"},
  {stdlib,"1.8.1"},
  {ssl,"2.2.1"}]}.    </code>
    <p>Note that the version numbers surely will differ in your system.
      Whenever one of the applications included in the script is
      upgraded, the script has to be changed.</p>
    <p>Assuming the above .rel file is stored in a file
      <c>start_ssl.rel</c> in the current directory, a boot script 
      can be built like this:</p>
    <code type="none">
1> systools:make_script("start_ssl",[]).    </code>
    <p>There will now be a file <c>start_ssl.boot</c> in the current
      directory. To test the boot script, start Erlang with the
      <c>-boot</c> command line parameter specifying this boot script
      (with its full path but without the <c>.boot</c> suffix), in
      Unix it could look like this:</p>
    <p></p>
    <code type="none"><![CDATA[
$ erl -boot /home/me/ssl/start_ssl
Erlang (BEAM) emulator version 5.0
 
Eshell V5.0  (abort with ^G)
1> whereis(ssl_server).
<0.32.0>    ]]></code>
    <p>The <c>whereis</c> function call verifies that the SSL
      application is really started.</p>
    <p>As an alternative to building a bootscript, one can explicitly
      add the path to the ssl <c>ebin</c> directory on the command
      line. This is done with the command line option <c>-pa</c>. This
      works as the ssl application really need not be started for the
      distribution to come up, a primitive version of the ssl server
      is started by the distribution module itself, so as long as the
      primitive code server can reach the code, the distribution will
      start. The <c>-pa</c> method is only recommended for testing
      purposes.</p>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Specifying distribution module for net_kernel</title>
    <p>The distribution module for SSL is named <c>inet_ssl_dist</c>
      and is specified on the command line whit the <c>-proto_dist</c>
      option. The argument to <c>-proto_dist</c> should be the module
      name without the <c>_dist</c> suffix, so this distribution
      module is specified with <c>-proto_dist inet_ssl</c> on the
      command line.</p>
    <p></p>
    <p>Extending the command line from above gives us the following:</p>
    <code type="none">
$ erl -boot /home/me/ssl/start_ssl -proto_dist inet_ssl    </code>
    <p>For the distribution to actually be started, we need to give
      the emulator a name as well:</p>
    <code type="none">
$ erl -boot /home/me/ssl/start_ssl -proto_dist inet_ssl -sname ssl_test
Erlang (BEAM) emulator version 5.0 [source]
 
Eshell V5.0  (abort with ^G)
(ssl_test@myhost)1>     </code>
    <p>Note however that a node started in this way will refuse to talk
      to other nodes, as no certificates or key files are supplied
      (see below).</p>
    <p>When the SSL distribution starts, the OTP system is in its
      early boot stage, why neither <c>application</c> nor <c>code</c>
      are usable. As SSL needs to start a port program in this early
      stage, it tries to determine the path to that program from the
      primitive code loaders code path. If this fails, one need to
      specify the directory where the port program resides. This can
      be done either with an environment variable 
      <c>ERL_SSL_PORTPROGRAM_DIR</c> or with the command line option
      <c>-ssl_portprogram_dir</c>. The value should be the directory
      where the <c>ssl_esock</c> port program is located. Note that
      this option is never needed in a normal Erlang installation.</p>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Specifying security options and other SSL options</title>
    <p>For SSL to work, you either need certificate files or a
      key file. Certificate files can be specified both when working as
      client and as server (connecting or accepting). </p>
    <p></p>
    <p>On the <c>erl</c> command line one can specify options that the
      ssl distribution will add when creation a socket. It is
      mandatory to specify at least a key file or client and server
      certificates. One can specify any <em>SSL option</em> on the
      command line, but must not specify any socket options (like
      packet size and such). The SSL options are listed in the
      Reference Manual. The only difference between the
      options in the reference manual and the ones that can be
      specified to the distribution on the command line is that
      <c>certfile</c> can (and usually needs to) be specified as
      <c>client_certfile</c> and <c>server_certfile</c>. The
      <c>client_certfile</c> is used when the distribution initiates a
      connection to another node and the <c>server_cerfile</c> is used
      when accepting a connection from a remote node. </p>
    <p>The command line argument for specifying the SSL options is named 
      <c>-ssl_dist_opt</c> and should be followed by an even number of
      SSL options/option values. The <c>-ssl_dist_opt</c> argument can
      be repeated any number of times.</p>
    <p>An example command line would now look something like this
      (line breaks in the command are for readability, 
      they should not be there when typed):</p>
    <code type="none">
$ erl -boot /home/me/ssl/start_ssl -proto_dist inet_ssl 
  -ssl_dist_opt client_certfile "/home/me/ssl/erlclient.pem" 
  -ssl_dist_opt server_certfile "/home/me/ssl/erlserver.pem" 
  -ssl_dist_opt verify 1 depth 1     
  -sname ssl_test
Erlang (BEAM) emulator version 5.0 [source]
 
Eshell V5.0  (abort with ^G)
(ssl_test@myhost)1>     </code>
    <p>A node started in this way will be fully functional, using SSL
      as the distribution protocol.</p>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Setting up environment to always use SSL</title>
    <p>A convenient way to specify arguments to Erlang is to use the
      <c>ERL_FLAGS</c> environment variable. All the flags needed to
      use SSL distribution can be specified in that variable and will
      then be interpreted as command line arguments for all
      subsequent invocations of Erlang.</p>
    <p></p>
    <p>In a Unix (Bourne) shell it could look like this (line breaks for
      readability):</p>
    <code type="none">
$ ERL_FLAGS="-boot \\"/home/me/ssl/start_ssl\\" -proto_dist inet_ssl 
  -ssl_dist_opt client_certfile \\"/home/me/ssl/erlclient.pem\\" 
  -ssl_dist_opt server_certfile \\"/home/me/ssl/erlserver.pem\\" 
  -ssl_dist_opt verify 1 -ssl_dist_opt depth 1"
$ export ERL_FLAGS
$ erl -sname ssl_test
Erlang (BEAM) emulator version 5.0 [source]
 
Eshell V5.0  (abort with ^G)
(ssl_test@myhost)1> init:get_arguments().
[{root,["/usr/local/erlang"]},
 {progname,["erl "]},
 {sname,["ssl_test"]},
 {boot,["/home/me/ssl/start_ssl"]},
 {proto_dist,["inet_ssl"]},
 {ssl_dist_opt,["client_certfile","/home/me/ssl/erlclient.pem"]},
 {ssl_dist_opt,["server_certfile","/home/me/ssl/erlserver.pem"]},
 {ssl_dist_opt,["verify","1"]},
 {ssl_dist_opt,["depth","1"]},
 {home,["/home/me"]}]    </code>
    <p>The <c>init:get_arguments()</c> call verifies that the correct
      arguments are supplied to the emulator. </p>
  </section>
</chapter>


