<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<!DOCTYPE appref SYSTEM "appref.dtd">

<appref>
  <header>
    <copyright>
      <year>1999</year><year>2013</year>
      <holder>Ericsson AB. All Rights Reserved.</holder>
    </copyright>
    <legalnotice>
      The contents of this file are subject to the Erlang Public License,
      Version 1.1, (the "License"); you may not use this file except in
      compliance with the License. You should have received a copy of the
      Erlang Public License along with this software. If not, it can be
      retrieved online at http://www.erlang.org/.

      Software distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS"
      basis, WITHOUT WARRANTY OF ANY KIND, either express or implied. See
      the License for the specific language governing rights and limitations
      under the License.

    </legalnotice>

    <title>ssl</title>
    <file>ssl_app.sgml</file>
  </header>
  <app>ssl</app>
  <appsummary>The SSL application provides secure communication over
  sockets.</appsummary>

  <section>
    <title>DEPENDENCIES</title>
    <p>The ssl application uses the Erlang applications public_key and
    crypto to handle public keys and encryption, hence these
    applications needs to be loaded for the ssl application to work. In
    an embedded environment that means they need to be started with
    application:start/[1,2] before the ssl application is started.
    </p>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>ENVIRONMENT</title>
    <p>The following application environment configuration parameters
    are defined for the SSL application. See <seealso
    marker="kernel:application">application(3)</seealso>for more
    information about configuration parameters.
      </p>
    <p>Note that the environment parameters can be set on the command line,
      for instance,</p>
    <p><c>erl ... -ssl protocol_version '[sslv3, tlsv1]' ...</c>.
      </p>
    <taglist>
      <tag><c><![CDATA[protocol_version = [sslv3|tlsv1] <optional>]]></c>.</tag>
      <item>
	<p>Protocol that will be supported by started clients and
	servers. If this option is not set it will default to all
	protocols currently supported by the erlang ssl application.
	Note that this option may be overridden by the version option
	to ssl:connect/[2,3] and ssl:listen/2.
	</p>
      </item>

      <tag><c><![CDATA[session_lifetime = integer() <optional>]]></c></tag>
      <item>
	<p>The lifetime of session data in seconds. 
	</p>
      </item>

        <tag><c><![CDATA[session_cb = atom() <optional>]]></c></tag>
      <item>
        <p>
	  Name of session cache callback module that implements
	  the ssl_session_cache_api behavior, defaults to
	  ssl_session_cache.erl.
          </p>
      </item>

      <tag><c><![CDATA[session_cb_init_args = list() <optional>]]></c></tag>
      <item>
	<p>
	  List of arguments to the init function in session cache
	  callback module, defaults to [].
	</p>
      </item>

    </taglist>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>SEE ALSO</title>
	<p><seealso marker="kernel:application">application(3)</seealso></p>
  </section>
  
</appref>
