<?xml version="1.0" encoding="latin1" ?>
<!DOCTYPE erlref SYSTEM "erlref.dtd">

<erlref>
  <header>
    <copyright>
      <year>1996</year>
      <year>2012</year>
      <holder>Ericsson AB, All Rights Reserved</holder>
    </copyright>
    <legalnotice>
  The contents of this file are subject to the Erlang Public License,
  Version 1.1, (the "License"); you may not use this file except in
  compliance with the License. You should have received a copy of the
  Erlang Public License along with this software. If not, it can be
  retrieved online at http://www.erlang.org/.

  Software distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS"
  basis, WITHOUT WARRANTY OF ANY KIND, either express or implied. See
  the License for the specific language governing rights and limitations
  under the License.

  The Initial Developer of the Original Code is Ericsson AB.
    </legalnotice>

    <title>toolbar</title>
    <prepared>Gunilla Hugosson</prepared>
    <docno></docno>
    <date>1997-04-21</date>
    <rev>A</rev>
    <file>toolbar.sgml</file>
  </header>
  <module>toolbar</module>
  <modulesummary>GUI for Starting Tools and User Contributions</modulesummary>
  <description>
    <warning>
      <p>
	The Toolbar application is deprecated and will be removed in R16.
      </p>
    </warning>
    <p>Toolbar makes it easier to use
      the different Erlang tools - and the user contributions - which are provided.
      It has a graphical user interface with an icon for each tool.
      Clicking the icon activates the corresponding tool.
      </p>
    <p>All tools to be included on Toolbar must
      have a configuration file containing information about the tool,
      for example its start function and help information location.
      Configuration files must have the <c>.tool</c> suffix.
      </p>
    <p>When started, Toolbar automatically checks for <c>*.tool</c>
      files in the current path and adds the corresponding tools. For
      each <c>ebin</c> directory found in the path, it will also look
      in a <c>priv</c> directory next to it. This is a feature of the Erlang
      file structure.</p>
  </description>
  <funcs>
    <func>
      <name>start() -> ok | already_started</name>
      <fsummary>Start Toolbar</fsummary>
      <desc>
        <p>Creates a window containing tool icons.</p>
      </desc>
    </func>
    <func>
      <name>version() -> string()</name>
      <fsummary>Return current version number</fsummary>
      <desc>
        <p>Returns the current version number of Toolbar.</p>
      </desc>
    </func>
    <func>
      <name>update() -> ok | {error,not_started}</name>
      <fsummary>Update Toolbar</fsummary>
      <desc>
        <p>Makes a search for new tool files in the current path and
          adds the corresponding tools to Toolbar window.</p>
      </desc>
    </func>
    <func>
      <name>quit() -> ok | {error,not_started}</name>
      <fsummary>Quit Toolbar.</fsummary>
    </func>
    <func>
      <name>create_tool_file() -> ok | {error,not_started}</name>
      <fsummary>Create tool files</fsummary>
      <desc>
        <p>Starts the GUI used for creating and editing tool files.</p>
      </desc>
    </func>
    <func>
      <name>add_gs_contribs() -> ok | {error,not_started}</name>
      <fsummary>Add GS contributions</fsummary>
      <desc>
        <p>Adds the path to the directory where the GS contributions are
          situated and add the tools found there, if any.</p>
      </desc>
    </func>
  </funcs>
</erlref>

