<?xml version="1.0" encoding="latin1" ?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter SYSTEM "chapter.dtd">

<chapter>
  <header>
    <copyright>
      <year>2004</year><year>2009</year>
      <holder>Ericsson AB. All Rights Reserved.</holder>
    </copyright>
    <legalnotice>
      The contents of this file are subject to the Erlang Public License,
      Version 1.1, (the "License"); you may not use this file except in
      compliance with the License. You should have received a copy of the
      Erlang Public License along with this software. If not, it can be
      retrieved online at http://www.erlang.org/.
    
      Software distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS"
      basis, WITHOUT WARRANTY OF ANY KIND, either express or implied. See
      the License for the specific language governing rights and limitations
      under the License.
    
    </legalnotice>

    <title>Orber Release Notes History</title>
    <prepared></prepared>
    <responsible></responsible>
    <docno></docno>
    <approved></approved>
    <checked></checked>
    <date>99-02-12</date>
    <rev>A</rev>
  </header>

  <section>
    <title>Orber 3.5.4</title>

    <section>
      <title>Fixed Bugs and Malfunctions</title>
      <list type="bulleted">
        <item>
          <p>In some cases, it was possible for a user to delete the
            NameService root context.</p>
          <p>Own Id: OTP-5202</p>
        </item>
        <item>
          <p>Invoking two, or more, concurrent oe_register operations
            it could corrupt the IFR. If this is the case, the
            INTF_REPOS system exception is raised. The risk for this
            to occur is rather slim.</p>
          <p>Own Id: OTP-5526</p>
        </item>
      </list>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Orber 3.5.3</title>

    <section>
      <title>Improvements and New Features</title>
      <list type="bulleted">
        <item>
          <p>To avoid malicious attacks, it is now possible to configure
            Orber to only accept incoming requests up to a certain size.
            To be able to use this option, it must be supported by inet
            and SSL.</p>
          <p>Own id: OTP-5129</p>
        </item>
      </list>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Orber 3.5.2</title>

    <section>
      <title>Fixed Bugs and Malfunctions</title>
      <list type="bulleted">
        <item>
          <p>If a client tried to connect to Orber and immediately
            closed the connection, then the process accepting new
            connections could end up with a message in the queue
            that would never be removed.</p>
          <p>Own id: OTP-5105</p>
        </item>
        <item>
          <p>The INS corbaloc/corbaname URL:s did only accept DNS style host
            names. Now it is also possible to use, none compressed, IPv6
            addresses.</p>
          <p>Own id: OTP-5108</p>
        </item>
        <item>
          <p>When Orber was configured to use IPv6 for inter-ORB communication, 
            exported IOR:s did not contain a correct IPv6 address. This did not
            cause any problems if Orber was configured to use DNS style hostname
            instead.</p>
          <p>Own id: OTP-5109</p>
        </item>
        <item>
          <p>Orber used external operations not exported in R9B.</p>
          <p>Own id: OTP-5111</p>
        </item>
      </list>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Orber 3.5.1</title>

    <section>
      <title>Fixed Bugs and Malfunctions</title>
      <list type="bulleted">
        <item>
          <p>When using Light IFR it was not possible unregister data 
            (i.e., invoking 'MyModule':oe_unregister()).
            Introduced in Orber-3.5.0.1.</p>
          <p>Own id: OTP-5034</p>
        </item>
      </list>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Orber 3.5.0.1</title>

    <section>
      <title>Fixed Bugs and Malfunctions</title>
      <list type="bulleted">
        <item>
          <p>orber_ifr:contents/3 always returned an empty list when using
            Light IFR. Little or no effect.</p>
          <p>Own id: OTP-5018</p>
        </item>
      </list>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Orber 3.5</title>

    <section>
      <title>Improvements and New Features</title>
      <list type="bulleted">
        <item>
          <p>It is now possible to configure Orber to use NAT (Network Address 
            Translation) friendly parameters. A new section in the User's Guide
            describes how to handle communication via firewalls.</p>
          <p>Own id: OTP-4698</p>
        </item>
        <item>
          <p>A new module called <c>orber_diagnostics</c> have been added, which
            is intended to aid a user during the test and development phase.
            For more information, see the reference manual.</p>
          <p>Own id: OTP-4699</p>
        </item>
        <item>
          <p><c>IPv6</c> supported.</p>
          <p>Own id: OTP-4937</p>
        </item>
        <item>
          <p>Possible to configure Orber so that exported IOR:s contain
            multiple IIOP components for different interfaces.</p>
          <p>Own id: OTP-4938</p>
        </item>
        <item>
          <p>Improved typechecking of typecode supplied to the operations
            <c>orber_tc:check_tc/1</c>, <c>any:create/2</c> and 
            <c>any:set_typecode/2</c>.</p>
          <p>Own id: OTP-4939</p>
        </item>
        <item>
          <p>Server objects can now be started as EXIT tolerant.</p>
          <p>Own id: OTP-4940</p>
        </item>
        <item>
          <p>Possible to use interceptors for local invocations as well.</p>
          <p>Own id: OTP-4941</p>
        </item>
        <item>
          <p>If the IFR is not explicitly used, Orber can be configured
            to use a minimal IFR to reduce memory usage and installation
            time.</p>
          <p>Own id: OTP-5001</p>
        </item>
        <item>
          <p>To avoid malicious attacks it is now possible to configure
            Orber to limit the number of concurrent connections and
            requests and the amount of IIOP fragments.</p>
          <p>Own id: OTP-5002</p>
        </item>
        <item>
          <p>The operation <c>orber:iiop_connections/0</c> now also include
            incoming connections.</p>
          <p>Own id: OTP-5004</p>
        </item>
        <item>
          <p>The function <c>orber:add_node/2</c> now accepts more options.</p>
          <p>Own id: OTP-5006</p>
        </item>
        <item>
          <p>The module <c>orber_diagnostics</c> now exports a function
            which list missing modules generated by IC and required by
            Orber.</p>
          <p>Own id: OTP-5007</p>
        </item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Fixed Bugs and Malfunctions</title>
      <list type="bulleted">
        <item>
          <p>Orber's NameService did not return a NIL object reference if the total 
            number of existing bindings was less than, or equal to, 
            the <c>HowMany</c> parameter passed to 
            <c>'CosNaming_NamingContext':list/2</c> operation. This have now been
            changed to be compliant with the OMG standard. Furthermore, the operation
            <c>'CosNaming_BindingIterator':next_n/2</c> did not handle the index
            correctly in all situations.</p>
          <p>Own id: OTP-4700</p>
        </item>
        <item>
          <p>If the Orber internal gen_server orber_iiop_pm was stopped
            in such a way that the terminate function was not invoked,
            then ghost processes would appear.</p>
          <p>Own id: OTP-5003</p>
        </item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Incompatibilities</title>
      <list type="bulleted">
        <item>
          <p>The work-around introduced in version 3.4.1 (OTP-4608) has
            now been removed. Make sure you are using IC-4.2 or later.</p>
        </item>
        <item>
          <p>Since the OMG has defined a default port number (2809),
            Orber no longer support the bootstrap port.</p>
          <p>Own id: OTP-5005</p>
        </item>
      </list>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Orber 3.4.2.2</title>

    <section>
      <title>Fixed Bugs and Malfunctions</title>
      <list type="bulleted">
        <item>
          <p>Due to IFR DB lock mechanisms, concurrent creation 
            of non-anonymous IFR types could still result in duplicated
            entries.</p>
          <p>Own id: OTP-4781</p>
        </item>
      </list>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Orber 3.4.2.1</title>

    <section>
      <title>Fixed Bugs and Malfunctions</title>
      <list type="bulleted">
        <item>
          <p>The operation <c>orber:start()</c> could return before
            all Mnesia tables were accessible.</p>
          <p>Own id: OTP-4780</p>
        </item>
        <item>
          <p>Concurrent creation of non-anonymous IFR types
            could result in duplicates in the DB.</p>
          <p>Own id: OTP-4781</p>
        </item>
      </list>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Orber 3.4.2</title>

    <section>
      <title>Improvements and New Features</title>
      <list type="bulleted">
        <item>
          <p>Improved type tests for string, wide string and sequence when
            passed via IIOP.</p>
          <p>Own id: OTP-4759</p>
        </item>
        <item>
          <p>Less (internal) processes are needed when Orber act as client-side ORB
            and communicate with another ORB. Due to this change, closed connections
            and socket errors are dealt with in a more gentle way. If the latter
            occurs, the error_logger application is used to generate an error 
            report containing a description of what went wrong.</p>
          <p>Own id: OTP-4655</p>
        </item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Fixed Bugs and Malfunctions</title>
      <list type="bulleted">
        <item>
          <p>When communicating with another ORB, via SSL, and a socket error occurred,
            Orber did not recognize the error message. This occurred when Orber
            acted as client-side ORB.</p>
          <p>Own id: OTP-4656</p>
        </item>
        <item>
          <p>If an out-going connection was closed and the receiving process had not
            been scheduled yet, the close connection message was delivered before
            the correct message.</p>
          <p>Own id: OTP-4657</p>
        </item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Incompatibilities</title>
      <list type="bulleted">
        <item>
          <p>Since strstream is deprecated and not accepted by gcc-3.3,
            Orber no longer includes the InitalReference lib. The source
            code is still included.</p>
          <p>Own id: OTP-4767</p>
        </item>
      </list>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Orber 3.4.1</title>

    <section>
      <title>Improvements and New Features</title>
      <list type="bulleted">
        <item>
          <p>It is now possible to use IC-versions older than 4.2. But, this is 
            only temporary so it is still necessary upgrade to a correct 
            version.</p>
          <p>Own id: OTP-4608</p>
        </item>
      </list>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Orber 3.4</title>

    <section>
      <title>Improvements and New Features</title>
      <list type="bulleted">
        <item>
          <p>If a call-back module illegally caused an EXIT, clients
            residing on another ORB was not notified (hanged).</p>
          <p>Own id: OTP-4577</p>
        </item>
        <item>
          <p>The stub/skeleton-files generated by IC have been improved,
            i.e., depending on the IDL-files, reduced the size of the
            erl- and beam-files and decreased dependencies off Orber's
            Interface Repository. It is necessary to re-compile all IDL-files
            and use COS-applications, including Orber, compiled with
            IC-4.2.</p>
          <p>Own id: OTP-4576</p>
        </item>
        <item>
          <p>It is now possible to configure Orber to use the host name
            in exported IOR:s instead of the IP-number.</p>
          <p>Own id: OTP-4541</p>
        </item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Fixed Bugs and Malfunctions</title>
      <list type="bulleted">
        <item>
          <p>When Orber acted as server-side ORB and one tried to setup a 
            SSL-connection and using native Interceptors at the same time
            it failed.</p>
          <p>Own Id: OTP-4542</p>
        </item>
        <item>
          <p>Oneway operations, using a multi-node Orber, failed for inter-node
            communication.</p>
          <p>Own Id: OTP-4543</p>
        </item>
      </list>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Orber 3.3</title>

    <section>
      <title>Improvements and New Features</title>
      <list type="bulleted">
        <item>
          <p>Orber now supports fragmented IIOP messages for 1.2.</p>
          <p>Own Id: OTP-4462</p>
        </item>
        <item>
          <p>Orber now has its own set of unique VMCID:s which
            is used for minor codes in system exceptions. All system exceptions raised
            by Orber now uses this VMCID base or OMG:s VMCID base. See also the function
            <c>orber:exception_info/1</c>.</p>
          <p>Own Id: OTP-4463</p>
        </item>
        <item>
          <p>Since some ORB:s, non-compliant with the OMG specification,
            have problems using IOR:s which embeds a CodeSet component, it is now
            possible to configure Orber to exclude it from exported IOR:s.</p>
          <p>Own Id: OTP-4469</p>
        </item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Fixed Bugs and Malfunctions</title>
      <list type="bulleted">
        <item>
          <p>When combining interceptors and oneway operations, Orber
            incorrectly sent a MessageError over the connection to the 
            client ORB.</p>
          <p>Own Id: OTP-4460</p>
        </item>
        <item>
          <p>After (2^32)-1 requests, Orber used the request number 0 twice
            in a row.</p>
          <p>Own Id: OTP-4461</p>
        </item>
        <item>
          <p>The COMM_FAILURE exception should only be raised when connection
            problems occur. Now Orber raises the correct exceptions. Note, when
            Orber act as client side ORB you must be able to handle any of the system
            exceptions defined by the OMG. Some of the COMM_FAILURE exceptions
            have been replaced with the correct TRANSIENT and TIMEOUT exceptions.</p>
          <p>Own Id: OTP-4465</p>
        </item>
        <item>
          <p>The default port used for corbaloc and corbaname was
            incorrect. Now changed to follow the OMG standard (2809).</p>
          <p>Own Id: OTP-4466</p>
        </item>
        <item>
          <p>When Orber acted as a client-side ORB, it failed to encode
            unions with a default case (i.e. defined in the IDL-code and a
            default label used).</p>
          <p>Own Id: OTP-4472</p>
        </item>
        <item>
          <p>The operation corba:print_object/1/2 did not include host/port
            data for IIOP-1.0 IOR:s.</p>
          <p>Own Id: OTP-4483</p>
        </item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Incompatibilities</title>
      <list type="bulleted">
        <item>
          <p>Some of the COMM_FAILURE exceptions have been replaced with the correct
            TRANSIENT and TIMEOUT exceptions. All minor codes used by Orber
            is now based on the OMG assigned VMCIDs.</p>
          <p>Own Id: OTP-4465, OTP-4463</p>
        </item>
        <item>
          <p>The default port used for corbaloc and corbaname have been changed
            to 2809.</p>
          <p>Own Id: OTP-4466</p>
        </item>
        <item>
          <p>To reduce extra overhead Orber now uses a flag parameter,
            which makes it possible to configure Orber's behavior in different ways.
            Hence, the global activation of Local Typechecking, introduced in the previous
            version, have now been changed.</p>
          <p>Own Id: OTP-4467</p>
        </item>
      </list>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Orber 3.2.13</title>

    <section>
      <title>Improvements and New Features</title>
      <list type="bulleted">
        <item>
          <p>It is now possible to activate automatic typechecking when
            invoking operations on CORBA Objects locally. For more
            information, see the configuration and debugging chapters
            in the User's Guide regarding the <c>local_typecheck</c>
            option.</p>
          <p>Own Id: OTP-4410</p>
        </item>
        <item>
          <p>Due to the success of the pre-compiled IIOP-trace interceptor, a less
            verbose trace interceptor, called <c>orber_iiop_tracer_silent</c>,
            have been added as well.</p>
          <p>Own Id: OTP-4257</p>
        </item>
        <item>
          <p>Orber now support the Fixed datatype defined by the OMG. To be able
            to define Fixed types in an IDL-specification, check that your current
            IC version supports this type as well. If not, the only option is
            to encapsulate it in an <c>any</c> type.</p>
          <p>Own id: OTP-4375</p>
        </item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Fixed Bugs and Malfunctions</title>
      <list type="bulleted">
        <item>
          <p>It was not possible to use the function <c>corba:print_object/2</c>,
            which was introduced in the previous release, only 
            <c>corba:print_object/1</c>. Now it is also possible to use
            the <c>error_logger</c> or receive the data in string form.</p>
          <p>Own Id: OTP-4376</p>
        </item>
        <item>
          <p>The functions <c>orber_tc:principal</c> and <c>orber_tc:exception</c>
            returned incorrect.</p>
          <p>Own Id: -</p>
        </item>
        <item>
          <p>The function <c>orber_ifr:get_primitive</c> tried to access a
            non-existing (primitivdefs) table.</p>
          <p>Own Id: -</p>
        </item>
      </list>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Orber 3.2.12</title>

    <section>
      <title>Improvements and New Features</title>
      <list type="bulleted">
        <item>
          <p>Orber now check if an external IOR contains any 
            TAG_ALTERNATE_IIOP_ADDRESS components when trying to setup
            a connection to another ORB.</p>
          <p>Own id: OTP-4294</p>
        </item>
        <item>
          <p>It is now possible to add TAG_ALTERNATE_IIOP_ADDRESS components
            to a local object reference. See corba:add_alternate_iiop_address/3.</p>
          <p>Own id: OTP-4294</p>
        </item>
        <item>
          <p>Orber now allows unions with no default value defined and a
            discriminator out of range to be sent via IIOP. The value-field
            is set to the atom undefined.</p>
          <p>Own id: OTP-4295</p>
        </item>
        <item>
          <p>The corba module now exports a function, print_object/1/2, which
            prints IOR's in a more readable form.</p>
          <p>Own id: OTP-4296</p>
        </item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Fixed Bugs and Malfunctions</title>
      <list type="bulleted">
        <item>
          <p>Since "all" ORB's accept ISO-8859-1 encoding of chars and strings,
            Orber assumed that it could be used at all time to reduce the overhead.
            The JDK-1.3 only accepts ISO 646:1991 IRV (US-ASCII), even though
            ISO-8859-1 is default, which is why Orber now checks which codeset 
            is accepted.</p>
          <p>Own Id: OTP-4298</p>
        </item>
        <item>
          <p>When invoking a Locate Request, Orber in some cases did not reply
            with a Locate Reply header (used a Reply header).</p>
          <p>Own Id: OTP-4293</p>
        </item>
      </list>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Orber 3.2.11</title>

    <section>
      <title>Improvements and New Features</title>
      <list type="bulleted">
        <item>
          <p>If the underlying OS was not configured to allow Erlang to use the
            fully qualified host name the result could an incorrect IP-address.
            Hence, if you want to upgrade to Orber-3.2.11 and the fully 
            qualified name must be used you must upgrade your kernel version.
            Most likely, this change will NOT cause any problems, but if in doubt
            please contact support or use the mailing-list. 
            See also the release notes for Orber-3.2.6.</p>
          <p>Own id: OTP-3966</p>
        </item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Fixed Bugs and Malfunctions</title>
      <list type="bulleted">
        <item>
          <p>When looking up Initial Service (e.g. using <c>corbaloc</c>,
            <c>corbaname</c> or <c>corba:resolve_initial_references_remote/2</c>)
            and communicating via SSL, Orber used the wrong port number.</p>
          <p>Own Id: OTP-4264</p>
        </item>
      </list>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Orber 3.2.10</title>

    <section>
      <title>Improvements and New Features</title>
      <list type="bulleted">
        <item>
          <p>It is now possible to add new initial references, which can,
            for example, be accessed via <c>corba:resolve_initial_references/1</c>
            or the <c>corbaloc</c> schema.</p>
          <p>Own Id: OTP-4258</p>
        </item>
        <item>
          <p>The orber module now exports functions, <c>iiop_connections</c> 
            and <c>iiop_connections_pending</c>, which, respectively, list
            all currently open connections to other ORB's and connections
            which are in process of being set up to another ORB.</p>
          <p>Own Id: OTP-4262</p>
        </item>
        <item>
          <p>Orber now allows the user to define an interval of ports
            which Orber is may use (i.e. ports on the local machine)
            when trying to connect to another ORB. This behavior is useful
            if Orber resides behind a firewall which only allow applications
            to use certain ports when communicating with the outside world.
            If this option is set, it is absolutely necessary to
            set <c>iiop_connection_timeout</c>. If not, there is risk that
            Orber run out of ports, which will result in communication failure.
            This option cannot be used when using SSL since it does not support
            this feature. The default behavior is that any available port
            will be used (as before).</p>
          <p>Own Id: OTP-4260</p>
        </item>
        <item>
          <p>One can now install Orber's NameService as disc_copies, but
            the default behavior is that Orber uses ram_copies.</p>
          <p>Own Id: OTP-4259</p>
        </item>
        <item>
          <p>A pre-compiled IIOP-trace interceptor is now
            included in the Orber release. For more information,
            see the <c>Debugging</c> chapter in the User's Guide.</p>
          <p>Own Id: OTP-4257</p>
        </item>
        <item>
          <p>It is now possible to set Orber's configuration parameters
            in, for example, an Erlang shell. Consult <c>corba:orb_init/1</c> and
            <c>orber:configure/2</c>.</p>
          <p>Own Id: OTP-4261</p>
        </item>
        <item>
          <p>The Orber release now include <c>OrberWeb</c>, which is an extension of
            the <c>WebTool</c> application (first released in R8B). Hence, 
            <c>WebTool</c> must be installed to enable this feature. For more
            information, see the chapter <c>OrberWeb</c> in the User's Guide.
            <c>OrberWeb</c> is intended to be used during test and development.</p>
          <p>Own Id: OTP-4257</p>
        </item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Fixed Bugs and Malfunctions</title>
      <list type="bulleted">
        <item>
          <p>When setting up two Orber ORB's, where one of the ORB's domain
            name was a prefix of the other ORB's, communication via IIOP would fail.
            To eliminate any further configuration problems, one may not
            use <c>^G</c> (i.e. <c>"\\007"</c>) in the domain name. Due to this
            change it is not possible to upgrade during run-time.</p>
          <p>Own Id: OTP-4229</p>
        </item>
        <item>
          <p>When using a mix of IIOP-versions (1.0 vs 1.1/1.2) and 
            sending/receiving IOR's to/from Orber could result in a
            MARSHAL exception.</p>
          <p>Own Id: OTP-4230</p>
        </item>
        <item>
          <p>Encoding/decoding of wchar/wstring when using IIOP-1.2 do now
            follow the OMG standard. If your ORB do not follow the
            standard, contact support for information how to make a work-around
            to solve this problem. In most cases it is sufficient to
            configure the ORB's to communicate via IIOP-1.1.</p>
          <p>Own Id: OTP-4263</p>
        </item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Incompatibilities</title>
      <list type="bulleted">
        <item>
          <p>The encoding/decoding of wchar/wstring when using IIOP-1.2
            have been updated. See above.</p>
          <p>Own Id: OTP-4263</p>
        </item>
        <item>
          <p>Orber no longer returns a 'EXIT' message when trying
            to install Orber, i.e., invoking orber:install/1/2,
            on a disc-less node. But if if the installation fails due
            to any other reason, Orber still return a 'EXIT' message.</p>
          <p>Own Id: OTP-4256</p>
        </item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Known bugs and problems</title>
      <list type="bulleted">
        <item>
          <p><c>OrberWeb</c> only tested with <c>Netscape-4.75</c>. Furthermore,
            until <c>WebTool</c> reaches version 1.0 OrberWeb should also
            be considered to be a beta version.</p>
          <p>Own Id: OTP-4257</p>
        </item>
        <item>
          <p><c>OrberWeb</c> do not escape arguments passed when, for example,
            creating a new context. Hence, for now you are recommended to
            only use letters.</p>
          <p>Own Id: OTP-4257</p>
        </item>
      </list>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Orber 3.2.9</title>

    <section>
      <title>Fixed Bugs and Malfunctions</title>
      <list type="bulleted">
        <item>
          <p>External IOR:s containing unsupported or incorrectly placed
            TaggedComponents was corrupted when Orber forwarded the 
            IOR via IIOP. This bug was introduced in 3.2.6.</p>
          <p>Own Id: OTP-4170</p>
        </item>
      </list>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Orber 3.2.8</title>

    <section>
      <title>Improvements and New Features</title>
      <list type="bulleted">
        <item>
          <p>Orber now support interceptors.</p>
          <p>Own Id: -</p>
        </item>
      </list>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Orber 3.2.7</title>

    <section>
      <title>Improvements and New Features</title>
      <list type="bulleted">
        <item>
          <p>When Orber acted as server-side and communicating via IIOP the overhead
            was unreasonably large and memory consuming (depended on the 
            IDL-specification). This have now been fixed and will, especially, 
            improve the performance when invoking operations with no, or simple,
            arguments on a complex interface. This change will have little effect
            on objects started as pseudo since this problem did not affect them.</p>
          <p>Own Id: OTP-4063</p>
        </item>
        <item>
          <p>When Orber tried to set up a connection to another ORB which did not 
            respond all IIOP access where blocked until the TCP protocol
            generated a timeout. Now only requests to that particular ORB are
            queued.</p>
          <p>Own Id: OTP-4060</p>
        </item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Fixed Bugs and Malfunctions</title>
      <list type="bulleted">
        <item>
          <p>It was not possible to invoke the operation
            CosNaming_BindingIterator:next_one via IIOP if no more bindings 
            existed.</p>
          <p>Own id: OTP-4004</p>
        </item>
      </list>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Orber 3.2.6</title>

    <section>
      <title>Improvements and New Features</title>
      <list type="bulleted">
        <item>
          <p>Registering data in the IFR overhead reduced.</p>
          <p>Own id: OTP-3904</p>
        </item>
        <item>
          <p>The overhead for the function <c>is_a/1</c> have been reduced, which also
            affects remote <c>narrow</c> operations for inherited interfaces
            (e.g. using Java or C++ ORBs).</p>
          <p>Own id: OTP-3904</p>
        </item>
        <item>
          <p>If the underlying OS was not configured to allow Erlang to
            lookup the host-name by using the short-name the result was
            always the IP-address 127.0.0.1 (loop-back). Now Orber uses
            the full name. Hence, make sure the <c>net_adm:localhost/0</c> and
            <c>inet:getaddr/2</c> return proper values.</p>
          <p>Own id: OTP-3966</p>
        </item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Fixed Bugs and Malfunctions</title>
      <list type="bulleted">
        <item>
          <p>The CONV_FRAME_CodeSetComponentInfo struct was not placed 
            correctly in IOR:s. Each profile must be self-sustained 
            which is why this information must be duplicated in each 
            profile. Currently this only applies for the IIOP-profile 
            but will also concern future protocols.</p>
          <p>Own id: OTP-3992</p>
        </item>
      </list>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Orber 3.2.5</title>

    <section>
      <title>Improvements and New Features</title>
      <list type="bulleted">
        <item>
          <p>Orber now defines the configuration variable, 
            <c>iiop_setup_connection_timeout</c>, which makes it possible to
            timeout connection attempts to another ORB before the OS TCP timeout
            is activated.</p>
          <p>Own id: OTP-3961</p>
        </item>
        <item>
          <p>It is now possible to configure Orber to generate reports when abnormal
            situations occurs. For more information consult the User's Guide
            regarding the configuration parameter <c>orber_debug_level</c>.
            Note, it is not recommended to use this option for delivered systems 
            since some of the reports is not to be considered as errors.</p>
          <p>Own id: OTP-3962</p>
        </item>
        <item>
          <p>Orber now accepts a list of addresses as value for the configuration
            parameter <c>orbInitRef</c>.</p>
          <p>Own id: OTP-3945</p>
        </item>
        <item>
          <p>Orber now includes services defined by the configuration parameter
            <c>orbInitRef</c> when invoking <c>corba:list_initial_services/0</c>.</p>
          <p>Own id: OTP-3946</p>
        </item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Fixed Bugs and Malfunctions</title>
      <list type="bulleted">
        <item>
          <p>When using the configuration variable 'orbDefaultInitRef' with
            a value pointing to another Orber-ORB it was not possible to
            install Orber since Orber used to create default <c>NamingContexts</c>.
            Orber no longer add these contexts.</p>
          <p>Own id: OTP-3943</p>
        </item>
        <item>
          <p>Orber accessed <c>corbaloc</c> addresses in reverse order. Now fixed.</p>
          <p>Own id: OTP-3944</p>
        </item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Incompatibilities</title>
      <list type="bulleted">
        <item>
          <p>When installing Orber no default <c>NamingContext's</c>, i.e.,
            <c>host</c>, <c>hosts</c>, <c>resources</c>, <c>development</c>, 
            <c>factories</c> and <c>workgroup</c>, will be added. These contexts
            was defined in a cancelled specification.</p>
          <p>Own id: OTP-3942</p>
        </item>
        <item>
          <p><c>corbaloc</c> addresses are now accessed in FIFO order (instead of
            LIFO).</p>
          <p>Own id: OTP-3944</p>
        </item>
      </list>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Orber 3.2.4</title>

    <section>
      <title>Improvements and New Features</title>
      <p>-</p>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Fixed Bugs and Malfunctions</title>
      <list type="bulleted">
        <item>
          <p>When communicating via IIOP using version 1.2 Orber used incorrect
            offset for reply bodies containing system exceptions, exceptions and
            location forward.</p>
          <p>Own id: OTP-3912</p>
        </item>
        <item>
          <p>Orber did not return correct IFR Id:s when raising system exceptions
            via IIOP.</p>
          <p>Own id: OTP-3911</p>
        </item>
        <item>
          <p>If two different processes concurrently manipulated a 
            <c>CosNaming::NamingContext</c> the data could become corrupted.
            For single-node Orber this error occurred in version 3.2.1, 3.2.2 and
            3.2.3. For multi-node Orber this behavior have been present at all time.</p>
          <p>Own id: OTP-3910</p>
        </item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Incompatibilities</title>
      <list type="bulleted">
        <item>
          <p>Since Orber now returns a different, and correct, IFR-id for 
            systems exceptions other ORB:s and older versions of Orber
            might raise a different exception, probably MARSHAL or UNKNOWN. 
            This only occurs when communicating via IIOP. It is not possible to 
            upgrade during runtime. Use <c>orber:stop()</c>, load new version and
            restart Orber by invoking <c>orber:start()</c>.</p>
          <p>Own id: OTP-3911</p>
        </item>
      </list>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Orber 3.2.3</title>

    <section>
      <title>Improvements and New Features</title>
      <list type="bulleted">
        <item>
          <p>Improved performance for all types, simple and complex, when
            communicating via IIOP. It is not possible to upgrade during
            runtime. Use <c>orber:stop()</c>, load new version and restart 
            Orber by invoking <c>orber:start()</c>.</p>
          <p>Own id: OTP-3905</p>
        </item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Fixed Bugs and Malfunctions</title>
      <list type="bulleted">
        <item>
          <p>If a pseudo object raises an exception or exits the exception
            was only returned, not thrown.</p>
          <p>Own id: OTP-3907</p>
        </item>
        <item>
          <p>Orber defined an incorrect ID for CodeSets. This may cause
            INV_OBJREF or DATA_CONVERSION exceptions to be thrown, it
            depends on the other ORB.</p>
          <p>Own id: OTP-3899</p>
        </item>
      </list>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Orber 3.2.2</title>

    <section>
      <title>Improvements and New Features</title>
      <list type="bulleted">
        <item>
          <p>The behavior of Orber when receiving unsupported or incorrect
            messages have now been improved.</p>
          <p>Own id: OTP-3903</p>
        </item>
        <item>
          <p>Time consumed by <c>oe_MyModule:oe_register()</c> decreased.</p>
          <p>Own id: OTP-3904</p>
        </item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Fixed Bugs and Malfunctions</title>
      <list type="bulleted">
        <item>
          <p>When Orber received a 'location_forward' reply, the result
            from the second invocation was never delivered to the
            client. Now fixed.</p>
          <p>Own id: OTP-3814</p>
        </item>
      </list>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Orber 3.2.1</title>

    <section>
      <title>Improvements and New Features</title>
      <list type="bulleted">
        <item>
          <p>It is now possible to use external <c>NamingContexts</c>
            when, for example, using
            <c>'CosNaming_NamingContextExt':bind_context/3</c>.</p>
          <p>Own id: OTP-3902</p>
        </item>
      </list>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Orber 3.2</title>

    <section>
      <title>Improvements and New Features</title>
      <list type="bulleted">
        <item>
          <p>Orber now supports IIOP-version 1.2.</p>
          <p>Own id: OTP-3901</p>
        </item>
        <item>
          <p>Improved encoding and decoding performance for IIOP requests containing 
            <c>struct</c>, <c>union</c> or user defined <c>exceptions</c>.</p>
          <p>Own id: OTP-3900</p>
        </item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Fixed Bugs and Malfunctions</title>
      <list type="bulleted">
        <item>
          <p>Setting the <c>bootstrap_port</c> configuration parameter to a value
            less than 1024 made it impossible to start Orber properly.
            Now fixed.</p>
          <p>Own id: OTP-3898</p>
        </item>
      </list>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Orber 3.1.8</title>

    <section>
      <title>Improvements and New Features</title>
      <list type="bulleted">
        <item>
          <p>Orber now accepts <c>Indirection/Repeated</c><c>CORBA::TypeCode</c> as input and/or
            return value when communicating via IIOP.</p>
          <p>Own id: -</p>
        </item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Fixed Bugs and Malfunctions</title>
      <list type="bulleted">
        <item>
          <p>When another ORB replied with <c>location forward</c> Orber
            failed to decode this. Now fixed.</p>
          <p>Own id: OTP-3709</p>
        </item>
        <item>
          <p>Orber failed to encode <c>CORBA::TypeCode</c> containing <c>tk_alias</c>, e.g.,
            sending an <c>#any{}</c> which encapsulates data defined by <c>typedef</c>.</p>
          <p>Own id: OTP-3689</p>
        </item>
      </list>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Orber 3.1.7</title>

    <section>
      <title>Improvements and New Features</title>
      <list type="bulleted">
        <item>
          <p>Earlier, Orber did not use the IIOP/GIOP version specified
            in an external object key when invoking an intra-ORB request.</p>
          <p>Own id: OTP-3663</p>
        </item>
        <item>
          <p>The OMG standard now support an Interoperable Naming Service.
            Initially there where two proposals of which Orber earlier
            supported one of them. Now both standards are supported.</p>
          <p>Own id: OTP-3664</p>
        </item>
        <item>
          <p>The OMG have redefined the operator, used when encoding requests via IIOP,
            for the function <c>corba_object:non_existent/1</c>. CORBA version 2.0 and
            2.2 compliant ORB:s is supposed to support the old definition, while
            later versions, i.e., 2.3, is supposed to use the new operator 
            (<c>_non_existent</c> instead of <c>_not_existent</c>). Orber accepts
            both versions.</p>
          <p>Own id: OTP-3679</p>
        </item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Fixed Bugs and Malfunctions</title>
      <list type="bulleted">
        <item>
          <p>If an Orber node crashed and was restarted the object keys could
            point to other processes than it should, which may cause problems if,
            for example, the other process terminates due to it does not handle
            unknown messages. Now Orber GC object keys for objects residing on the
            crashed node. If Orber is started as a multi-node ORB of which one or 
            more nodes runs an older Orber version they can still communicate but
            with an increased overhead. Hence, all nodes should be upgraded during
            a relatively short time. If Orber is stopped, i.e., orber:stop() or
            a shutdown is generated, objects residing on that node will be terminated.</p>
          <p>Own id: OTP-3678</p>
        </item>
        <item>
          <p>If an IDL-file contains two interfaces of which the first one
            contains an exception and the second interface, which inherits the first
            one, contain an operation which raises this exception the IFR
            failed since multiple references where found when invoking 
            orber_ifr:lookup_id/2. Now fixed.</p>
          <p>Own id: OTP-3665</p>
        </item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Incompatibilities</title>
      <list type="bulleted">
        <item>
          <p>To be able to start Orber as lightweight the mnesia application
            cannot be listed in the "orber.app" file. You might find it
            necessary to add 'mnesia' to the applications-list. 
            For example, you cannot upgrade an older version
            of Orber (not started as lightweight) to this version without
            adding mnesia to the application dependencies list.</p>
          <p>Own id: OTP-3666</p>
        </item>
        <item>
          <p>The function <c>corba_object:non_existent/1</c> have been updated
            to follow the CORBA 2.3 standard. Hence, Intra-ORB communication
            with ORB:s not supporting this standard will fail. The operation 
            <c>corba_object:not_existent/1</c> allow users to use the old standard.
            Consult the ORB vendor's documentation to decide which function to use.</p>
          <p>Own id: OTP-3679</p>
        </item>
      </list>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Orber 3.1.6</title>

    <section>
      <title>Improvements and New Features</title>
      <list type="bulleted">
        <item>
          <p>Cosmetic update of internal functions.</p>
          <p>Own id: -</p>
        </item>
      </list>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Orber 3.1.5</title>

    <section>
      <title>Fixed Bugs and Malfunctions</title>
      <list type="bulleted">
        <item>
          <p>When decoding TypeCode for an object reference, e.g., as a part of 
            an #any{}, Orber failed. This is no longer the case. </p>
          <p>Own id: OTP-3631</p>
        </item>
      </list>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Orber 3.1.4</title>

    <section>
      <title>Improvements and New Features</title>
      <list type="bulleted">
        <item>
          <p>The function <c>start_lightweight/1</c> have been added to the
            <c>orber</c> module. This function allow us to start orber as
            lightweight without, or override, the configuration parameter 
            <c>-orber lightweight</c>.</p>
          <p>Own id: -</p>
        </item>
        <item>
          <p>A new configuration parameter, 'iiop_connection_timeout Secs', is now
            available. This parameter's purpose, is to terminate the socket 
            connection on the client side if a time span of Secs seconds have passed.
            The connection will, however, NOT be terminated if a client still waits
            for a reply. For the last scenario to happen, the client have been 
            configured to use a larger timeout value than the configuration 
            parameter 'iiop_connection_timeout' have been set to.</p>
          <p>Own id: -</p>
        </item>
        <item>
          <p>Up until now, invoking an an operation with an extra Timeout parameter
            (using the IC option: ic:gen(IdlFile, [{timeout,"module::interface"}])),
            only applied to local Objects. Now, using the IC option above, when 
            compiling the stubs, and adding the extra Timeout parameter, a timeout
            will also be triggered when calling Objects residing on other ORB:s.
            The return value, after a timeout has been triggered, have changed from
            an EXIT message to raising the system exception COMM_FAILURE. For more
            information, about how this feature interacts with the configuration 
            parameter 'iiop_timeout', consult the documentation.</p>
          <p>Own id: -</p>
        </item>
        <item>
          <p>When using invalid intra-ORB configuration, i.e., incorrect 
            Port/IP-address, when trying to connect to another ORB, 
            a CRASH REPORT was generated if the configuration
            parameter '-boot start_sasl' was used. This behavior has now changed.</p>
          <p>Own id: -</p>
        </item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Fixed Bugs and Malfunctions</title>
      <list type="bulleted">
        <item>
          <p>If a client-side ORB terminated the IIOP connection immediately there 
            was a possibility that the server responsible detecting this did not.</p>
          <p>Own id: OTP-3593</p>
        </item>
        <item>
          <p>Setting the configuration parameter 'iiop_timeout' did not result in a 
            correct behavior, i.e., no timeout triggered.</p>
          <p>Own id: OTP-3555</p>
        </item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Incompatibilities</title>
      <list type="bulleted">
        <item>
          <p>When using the IC option, ic:gen(IdlFile, [{timeout,"module::interface"}]),
            an EXIT was the timeout result. Now, the system exception COMM_FAILURE is
            raised.</p>
        </item>
      </list>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Orber 3.1.3</title>

    <section>
      <title>Fixed Bugs and Malfunctions</title>
      <list type="bulleted">
        <item>
          <p>Orber did not ignore unrecognized TaggedProfiles. Other vendors may have 
            registered own TAG's with the OMG. These TAG's are valid but not
            necessarily handled by other vendors.</p>
          <p>Own id: OTP-3514</p>
        </item>
        <item>
          <p>When passing Object references over IIOP, decoding local references could
            fail. Now fixed.</p>
          <p>Own id: OTP-3515</p>
        </item>
      </list>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Orber 3.1.2</title>

    <section>
      <title>Fixed Bugs and Malfunctions</title>
      <list type="bulleted">
        <item>
          <p>Previously the OMG have published two suggestions for <c>Interoperable Name Service</c>,
            of which, the <c>CORBA 3</c> specify <c>orbos/98-10-11</c> to be implemented.
            Unfortunately, the Interoperable Name Service Orber supports, is the one not chosen.
            Hence, the <c>InitialReferences.idl</c> will not be according to the future standard. 
            The modules name is now changed from <c>CORBA</c> to <c>Orber</c>. This will affect 
            code which are using this interface. The idl specification must be recompiled and 
            then <c>CORBA</c> must be changed to <c>Orber</c> in the client.</p>
          <p>Own id: OTP-3468, OTP-3155</p>
        </item>
        <item>
          <p>Now possible to run oe_unregister when the IDL-specification contains 
            exceptions correctly.</p>
          <p>Own Id: OTP-3447</p>
        </item>
        <item>
          <p>Now possible to run oe_unregister when the IDL-specification contains 
            attributes.</p>
          <p>Own Id: OTP-3439</p>
        </item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Incompatibilities</title>
      <p>The change in <c>InitialReferences.idl</c> to clash with the Corba standard implies changes
        in code that use this interface. See the OTP-3468 and OTP-3155 in the <c>Fixed Bugs and Malfunctions</c>
        chapter above.</p>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Orber 3.1.1</title>

    <section>
      <title>Fixed Bugs and Malfunctions</title>
      <list type="bulleted">
        <item>
          <p>When introducing the configuration parameter <c>ip_address</c> 
            it was no longer possible to have the same default behavior
            as before. Now fixed.</p>
          <p>Own Id: OTP-3431</p>
        </item>
        <item>
          <p>The internal request number handling never checked if maximum reached.
            Now the counter restart at 0 after reaching max.</p>
          <p>Own Id: OTP-3415</p>
        </item>
        <item>
          <p>Orber did not handle locate-requests correctly, i.e., not able to
            recognize the new internal representation of object references.</p>
          <p>Own Id: OTP-3414</p>
        </item>
      </list>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Orber 3.1</title>

    <section>
      <title>Improvements and New Features</title>
      <list type="bulleted">
        <item>
          <p>It is now possible to start Orber as lightweight.</p>
          <p>Own Id: -</p>
        </item>
        <item>
          <p>It is now possible to create pseudo objects, i.e., not server objects.</p>
          <p>Own Id: -</p>
        </item>
        <item>
          <p>One new system exception introduced; 'BAD_QOS'.</p>
          <p>Own Id: -</p>
        </item>
        <item>
          <p>Orber now supports the types 'long long' and 'unsigned long long'</p>
          <p>Own Id: -</p>
        </item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Fixed Bugs and Malfunctions</title>
      <list type="bulleted">
        <item>
          <p>Encoding typecode for complex exceptions (non-empty body) was not done 
            correctly.</p>
          <p>Own Id: OTP-3390</p>
        </item>
        <item>
          <p>orber_iiop_pm crashed when it received an 'EXIT'. Now fixed.</p>
          <p>Own Id: OTP-3391</p>
        </item>
      </list>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Orber 3.0.1</title>

    <section>
      <title>Improvements and New Features</title>
      <list type="bulleted">
        <item>
          <p>Orber is now able to handle upgrade properly.</p>
          <p>Own Id: -</p>
        </item>
      </list>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Orber 3.0</title>

    <section>
      <title>Improvements and New Features</title>
      <list type="bulleted">
        <item>
          <p>It is now possible to use secure IIOP connections to and from Orber.
            Orber currently only supports security with the help of SSL and not SECIOP.</p>
          <p>Own Id: OTP-1510</p>
        </item>
        <item>
          <p>It is now possible to start Orber objects as supervisor children using
            Module_Interface:oe_create_link/2 or corba:create_link/4 as the start function.</p>
          <p>Own Id: -</p>
        </item>
        <item>
          <p>It is now possible to start a Orber object and be able to tell apart if it is in
            the process of being restarted or has permanently terminated. This is also the reason
            for introducing <c>objectkeys_gc_time</c> configuration parameter.</p>
          <p>Own Id: -</p>
        </item>
        <item>
          <p>The service CosEvent has been removed from orber and become its own application, called cosEvent.</p>
          <p>Own Id: -</p>
        </item>
        <item>
          <p>The service CosTransactions is now available as a separate application, called cosTransactions.</p>
          <p>Own Id: OTP-1741</p>
        </item>
        <item>
          <p>Three new system exceptions, 'TRANSACTION_REQUIRED', 'TRANSACTION_ROLLEDBACK' 
            and 'INVALID_TRANSACTION', introduced. Required by the cosTransactions application.</p>
          <p>Own Id: -</p>
        </item>
        <item>
          <p>An configuration variable ip_address has been added, so it's possible
            to listen on a specific ip interface on a multi interface host.
            The value is the ip address as a string or a tuple of four integers, 
            default value is all interfaces.</p>
          <p>Own Id: OTP-3294</p>
        </item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Fixed Bugs and Malfunctions</title>
      <list type="bulleted">
        <item>
          <p>set- and get-operations for the 'any'-module now behaves properly.</p>
          <p>Own Id: OTP-3355</p>
        </item>
        <item>
          <p>Orber can now handle IORs which contain more than one "Tagged Profile".</p>
          <p>Own Id: OTP-3266</p>
        </item>
      </list>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Incompatibilities</title>
      <list type="bulleted">
        <item>
          <p>CosEvent include paths have changed since it is now a separate application, called cosEvent.</p>
        </item>
        <item>
          <p>The internal representation of object references have changed. Orber do, however, 
            recognize the old representation. But object references (created by Orber 2.2.2 or older) 
            stored and used through several Orber upgrades may not be supported.</p>
        </item>
        <item>
          <p>The functions oe_create/2 and oe_create_link/2 now take an 
            options list as its second argument. Orber still allow 
            oe_create*(Env, {Type,RegName}) to be used, but may not in future releases.</p>
        </item>
      </list>
    </section>
  </section>
</chapter>

