<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter SYSTEM "chapter.dtd">

<chapter>
  <header>
    <copyright>
      <year>2014</year><year>2016</year>
      <holder>Ericsson AB. All Rights Reserved.</holder>
    </copyright>
    <legalnotice>
      Licensed under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the "License");
      you may not use this file except in compliance with the License.
      You may obtain a copy of the License at
 
          http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0

      Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
      distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,
      WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
      See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
      limitations under the License.
    
    </legalnotice>

    <title>Versions</title>
    <prepared></prepared>
    <responsible></responsible>
    <docno></docno>
    <approved></approved>
    <checked></checked>
    <date>2014-02-19</date>
    <rev></rev>
    <file>versions.xml</file>
  </header>
  <marker id="versions section"></marker>

  <section>
    <title>OTP Version</title>
    <p>As of OTP release 17, the OTP release number corresponds to
    the major part of the OTP version. The OTP version as a concept was
    introduced in OTP 17. The version scheme used is described in detail in
    <seealso marker="#version_scheme">Version Scheme</seealso>.</p>
    <p>OTP of a specific version is a set of applications of specific
    versions. The application versions identified by an OTP version
    corresponds to application versions that have been tested together
    by the Erlang/OTP team at Ericsson AB. An OTP system can, however, be
    put together with applications from different OTP versions. Such a
    combination of application versions has not been tested by the
    Erlang/OTP team. It is therefore <em>always preferred to use OTP
    applications from one single OTP version</em>.</p>
    <p>Release candidates have an <c>-rc&lt;N&gt;</c>
    suffix. The suffix <c>-rc0</c> is used during development up to
    the first release candidate.</p>

    <section>
      <title>Retrieving Current OTP Version</title>
      <p>In an OTP source code tree, the OTP version can be read from
      the text file <c>&lt;OTP source root&gt;/OTP_VERSION</c>. The
      absolute path to the file can be constructed by calling
      <c>filename:join([</c><seealso marker="kernel:code#root_dir/0"><c>code:root_dir()</c></seealso><c>, "OTP_VERSION"])</c>.</p>
      <p>In an installed OTP development system, the OTP version can be read
      from the text file <c>&lt;OTP installation root&gt;/releases/&lt;OTP release number&gt;/OTP_VERSION</c>.
      The absolute path to the file can by constructed by calling
      <c>filename:join([</c><seealso marker="kernel:code#root_dir/0"><c>code:root_dir()</c></seealso><c>, "releases", </c><seealso marker="erts:erlang#system_info_otp_release"><c>erlang:system_info(otp_release)</c></seealso><c>, "OTP_VERSION"]).</c></p>
      <p>If the version read from the <c>OTP_VERSION</c> file in a
      development system has a <c>**</c> suffix, the system has been
      patched using the
      <seealso marker="../installation_guide/OTP-PATCH-APPLY"><c>otp_patch_apply</c></seealso>
      tool. In this case, the system consists of application
      versions from multiple OTP versions. The version preceding the <c>**</c>
      suffix corresponds to the OTP version of the base system that
      has been patched. Notice that if a development system is updated by
      other means than <c>otp_patch_apply</c>, the file <c>OTP_VERSION</c>
      can identify an incorrect OTP version.</p>
      <p>No <c>OTP_VERSION</c> file is placed in a
      <seealso marker="create_target">target system</seealso> created
      by OTP tools. This since one easily can create a target system
      where it is hard to even determine the base OTP version. You can,
      however, place such a file there if you know the OTP version.</p>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>OTP Versions Table</title>
      <p>The text file <c>&lt;OTP source root&gt;/otp_versions.table</c>,
      which is part of the source code, contains information about all
      OTP versions from OTP 17.0 up to the current OTP version. Each line
      contains information about application versions that are part of a
      specific OTP version, and has the following format:</p>
      <pre>
&lt;OtpVersion&gt; : &lt;ChangedAppVersions&gt; # &lt;UnchangedAppVersions&gt; :</pre>
      <p><c>&lt;OtpVersion&gt;</c> has the format <c>OTP-&lt;VSN&gt;</c>,
      that is, the same as the git tag used to identify the source.</p>
      <p><c>&lt;ChangedAppVersions&gt;</c> and
      <c>&lt;UnchangedAppVersions&gt;</c> are space-separated lists of
      application versions and has the format
      <c>&lt;application&gt;-&lt;vsn&gt;</c>.</p>
      <list type="bulleted">
	<item><c>&lt;ChangedAppVersions&gt;</c> corresponds to changed
	applications with new version numbers in this OTP version.</item>
	<item><c>&lt;UnchangedAppVersions&gt;</c> corresponds to unchanged
	application versions in this OTP version.</item>
      </list>
      <p>Both of them can be empty, but not at the same time.
      If <c>&lt;ChangedAppVersions&gt;</c> is empty, no changes have
      been made that change the build result of any application. This could,
      for example, be a pure bug fix of the build system. The order of lines
      is undefined. All white-space characters in this file are either space
      (character 32) or line-break (character 10).</p>
      <p>By using ordinary UNIX tools like <c>sed</c> and <c>grep</c> one
      can easily find answers to various questions like:</p>
      <list type="bulleted">
	<item><p>Which OTP versions are <c>kernel-3.0</c> part of?</p>
	<p><c>$ grep ' kernel-3\.0 ' otp_versions.table</c> </p></item>
	<item><p>In which OTP version was <c>kernel-3.0</c> introduced?</p>
	<p><c>$ sed 's/#.*//;/ kernel-3\.0 /!d' otp_versions.table</c>
	</p></item>
      </list>
      <p>The above commands give a bit more information than the exact
      answers, but adequate information when manually searching for answers
      to these questions.</p>
      <warning><p>The format of the <c>otp_versions.table</c> might be
      subject to changes during the OTP 17 release.</p></warning>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Application Version</title>
    <p>As of OTP 17.0 application versions use the same
    <seealso marker="#version_scheme">version scheme</seealso> as the
    OTP version. Application versions part of a release candidate will
    however not have an <c>-rc&lt;N&gt;</c> suffix as the OTP version.
    Also note that a major increment in an application version does not
    necessarily imply a major increment of the OTP version. This depends
    on whether the major change in the application is considered as a
    major change for OTP as a whole or not.</p>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Version Scheme</title>
    <marker id="version_scheme"/>
    <note><p>The version scheme was changed as of OTP 17.0. This implies
    that application versions used prior to OTP 17.0 do not adhere to this
    version scheme. <seealso marker="#otp_17_0_app_versions">A list of
    application versions used in OTP 17.0</seealso> is included at the
    end of this section</p></note>
    <p>In the normal case, a version is constructed as
    <c>&lt;Major&gt;.&lt;Minor&gt;.&lt;Patch&gt;</c>,
    where <c>&lt;Major&gt;</c> is the most significant part.</p>
    <p>However, more dot-separated parts than this can exist.
    The dot-separated parts consist of non-negative integers. If
    all parts less significant than <c>&lt;Minor&gt;</c> equals
    <c>0</c>, they are omitted. The three normal parts
    <c>&lt;Major&gt;.&lt;Minor&gt;.&lt;Patch&gt;</c> are changed as
    follows:</p>
    <list type="bulleted">
      <item><c>&lt;Major&gt;</c> - Increases when major changes,
      including incompatibilities, are made.</item>
      <item><c>&lt;Minor&gt;</c> - Increases when new
      functionality is added.</item>
      <item><c>&lt;Patch&gt;</c> - Increases when pure bug fixes
      are made.</item>
    </list>
    <p>When a part in the version number increases, all less significant
    parts are set to <c>0</c>.</p>
    <p>An application version or an OTP version identifies source code
    versions. That is, it implies nothing about how the application
    or OTP has been built.</p>

    <section>
      <title>Order of Versions</title>
      <p>Version numbers in general are only partially ordered. However,
      normal version numbers (with three parts) as of OTP 17.0 have a total
      or linear order. This applies both to normal OTP versions and
      normal application versions.</p>
      <p>When comparing two version numbers that have an order, one
      compare each part as ordinary integers from the most
      significant part to less significant parts. The order is
      defined by the first parts of the same significance that
      differ. An OTP version with a larger version includes all
      changes that are part of a smaller OTP version. The same
      goes for application versions.</p>
      <p>In general, versions can have more than three parts.
      The versions are then only partially ordered. Such
      versions are only used in exceptional cases. When an extra
      part (out of the normal three parts) is added to a version number,
      a new branch of versions is made. The new branch has a linear
      order against the base version. However, versions on different
      branches have no order, and therefore one can only conclude
      that they all include what is included in their
      closest common ancestor. When branching multiple times from the
      same base version, <c>0</c> parts are added between the base
      version and the least significant <c>1</c> part until a unique
      version is found. Versions that have an order can be compared
      as described in the previous paragraph.</p>
      <p>An example of branched versions: The version <c>6.0.2.1</c>
      is a branched version from the base version <c>6.0.2</c>.
      Versions on the form <c>6.0.2.&lt;X&gt;</c> can be compared
      with normal versions smaller than or equal to <c>6.0.2</c>,
      and other versions on the form <c>6.0.2.&lt;X&gt;</c>. The
      version <c>6.0.2.1</c> will include all changes in
      <c>6.0.2</c>. However, <c>6.0.3</c> will most likely
      <em>not</em> include all changes in <c>6.0.2.1</c> (note that
      these versions have no order). A second branched version from the base
      version <c>6.0.2</c> will be version <c>6.0.2.0.1</c>, and a
      third branched version will be <c>6.0.2.0.0.1</c>.</p>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>OTP 17.0 Application Versions</title>
    <marker id="otp_17_0_app_versions"/>
    <p>The following list details the application versions that
    were part of OTP 17.0. If
    the normal part of an application version number compares
    as smaller than the corresponding application version in the list,
    the version number does not adhere to the version scheme introduced
    in OTP 17.0 and is to be considered as not having an order against
    versions used as of OTP 17.0.</p>
    <list>
      <item><c>asn1-3.0</c></item>
      <item><c>common_test-1.8</c></item>
      <item><c>compiler-5.0</c></item>
      <item><c>cosEvent-2.1.15</c></item>
      <item><c>cosEventDomain-1.1.14</c></item>
      <item><c>cosFileTransfer-1.1.16</c></item>
      <item><c>cosNotification-1.1.21</c></item>
      <item><c>cosProperty-1.1.17</c></item>
      <item><c>cosTime-1.1.14</c></item>
      <item><c>cosTransactions-1.2.14</c></item>
      <item><c>crypto-3.3</c></item>
      <item><c>debugger-4.0</c></item>
      <item><c>dialyzer-2.7</c></item>
      <item><c>diameter-1.6</c></item>
      <item><c>edoc-0.7.13</c></item>
      <item><c>eldap-1.0.3</c></item>
      <item><c>erl_docgen-0.3.5</c></item>
      <item><c>erl_interface-3.7.16</c></item>
      <item><c>erts-6.0</c></item>
      <item><c>et-1.5</c></item>
      <item><c>eunit-2.2.7</c></item>
      <item><c>gs-1.5.16</c></item>
      <item><c>hipe-3.10.3</c></item>
      <item><c>ic-4.3.5</c></item>
      <item><c>inets-5.10</c></item>
      <item><c>jinterface-1.5.9</c></item>
      <item><c>kernel-3.0</c></item>
      <item><c>megaco-3.17.1</c></item>
      <item><c>mnesia-4.12</c></item>
      <item><c>observer-2.0</c></item>
      <item><c>odbc-2.10.20</c></item>
      <item><c>orber-3.6.27</c></item>
      <item><c>os_mon-2.2.15</c></item>
      <item><c>ose-1.0</c></item>
      <item><c>otp_mibs-1.0.9</c></item>
      <item><c>parsetools-2.0.11</c></item>
      <item><c>percept-0.8.9</c></item>
      <item><c>public_key-0.22</c></item>
      <item><c>reltool-0.6.5</c></item>
      <item><c>runtime_tools-1.8.14</c></item>
      <item><c>sasl-2.4</c></item>
      <item><c>snmp-4.25.1</c></item>
      <item><c>ssh-3.0.1</c></item>
      <item><c>ssl-5.3.4</c></item>
      <item><c>stdlib-2.0</c></item>
      <item><c>syntax_tools-1.6.14</c></item>
      <item><c>test_server-3.7</c></item>
      <item><c>tools-2.6.14</c></item>
      <item><c>typer-0.9.6</c></item>
      <item><c>webtool-0.8.10</c></item>
      <item><c>wx-1.2</c></item>
      <item><c>xmerl-1.3.7</c></item>
    </list>
  </section>
</chapter>

