<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter SYSTEM "chapter.dtd">

<chapter>
  <header>
    <copyright>
      <year>1997</year><year>2016</year>
      <holder>Ericsson AB. All Rights Reserved.</holder>
    </copyright>
    <legalnotice>
      Licensed under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the "License");
      you may not use this file except in compliance with the License.
      You may obtain a copy of the License at
 
          http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0

      Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
      distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,
      WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
      See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
      limitations under the License.
    
    </legalnotice>

    <title>Combine Mnesia with SNMP</title>
    <prepared>Claes Wikstr&ouml;m, Hans Nilsson and H&aring;kan Mattsson</prepared>
    <responsible></responsible>
    <docno></docno>
    <approved></approved>
    <checked></checked>
    <date></date>
    <rev></rev>
    <file>Mnesia_chap8.xml</file>
  </header>

  <section>
    <title>Combine Mnesia and SNMP</title>
    <p>Many telecommunications applications must be controlled and
      reconfigured remotely. It is sometimes an advantage to perform
      this remote control with an open protocol such as the Simple
      Network Management Protocol (SNMP). The alternatives to this would
      be the following:</p>
    <list type="bulleted">
      <item>Not being able to control the application remotely
      </item>
      <item>Using a proprietary control protocol
      </item>
      <item>Using a bridge that maps control messages in a
       proprietary protocol to a standardized management protocol and
       conversely
      </item>
    </list>
    <p>All these approaches have different advantages and
      disadvantages. <c>Mnesia</c> applications can easily be opened to
      the SNMP protocol. A direct 1-to-1 mapping can be established
      between <c>Mnesia</c> tables and SNMP tables. This means
      that a <c>Mnesia</c> table can be configured to be <em>both</em>
      a <c>Mnesia</c> table and an SNMP table. A number of functions to
      control this behavior are described in the Reference Manual.</p>
  </section>
</chapter>

